<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Writing on Xaprb </title>
      <generator uri="https://hugo.spf13.com">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://www.xaprb.com/categories/writing/index.xml/</link>
    
    
    
    <updated>Sat, 07 Feb 2015 00:00:00 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making High Performance MySQL&#39;s New Website</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2015/02/07/creating-high-performance-mysql-new-website/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2015 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2015/02/07/creating-high-performance-mysql-new-website/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2015/02/hpm-cover-perspective.png&#34; alt=&#34;HPM Cover&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently updated the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.highperfmysql.com&#34;&gt;High Performance MySQL&lt;/a&gt;
website to modernize it. I am impressed at how easy it is these days to get a
great little brochure site hosted. It used to be a lot more work. I used a
variety of tools and services to do this and decided to share this for people
who are interested. Hopefully you&amp;rsquo;ll add comments and point me towards more
tools and tips to make these things even easier for me in the future!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Before&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The website used to be a WordPress blog. This used to be my go-to solution for
everything. It used to be the easiest way to whip together something quickly and
put it online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But WordPress sites have a bunch of problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They need a database. Database down, website down.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They need care and feeding. WordPress is a major hack target and you have to
update it or you&amp;rsquo;re going to end up serving malware and ads without knowing
it. You also have to update the plugins and themes. It&amp;rsquo;s just a lot of hassle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re not high performance, primarily because of the dynamic content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just can&amp;rsquo;t make time to babysit sites like this anymore.
As a result I&amp;rsquo;ve been moving everything to good old static sites again.
Static sites used to be a lot of work too. Not anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Static Site Generators&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Static site generators like &lt;a href=&#34;http://jekyllrb.com/&#34;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; are a whole new world
of writing ease. Write Markdown, run the generator, get a static site fully
rendered. It&amp;rsquo;s great. Jekyll, though, still has some annoyances. It requires a
lot of dependencies (my nemesis is &lt;code&gt;bundle install&lt;/code&gt;&amp;hellip; I hate how often that
breaks and takes a long time to work around for whatever version of Ruby gems
and dependencies and compilers and stuff are involved) and Jekyll itself isn&amp;rsquo;t
really a site, it&amp;rsquo;s just the scaffolding for a site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; for this site because of the amount and
complexity of content on it. Hugo is nicer than Jekyll in my opinion, much
better actually. But for a site like High Performance MySQL, a one-page brochure
is really what&amp;rsquo;s needed. For that, a simple static &lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt; is better. No
need for a site generator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Bootstrap and Bootstrap Themes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably the biggest part of making a site these days is creating a good design
that will look good on everything from a desktop browser to an old iPhone.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://getbootstrap.com/&#34;&gt;Twitter Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; provides a foundation for doing a
lot of that. It&amp;rsquo;s an amazing advancement over the bad old days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combine that with thousands of freely available designs/themes based on
Bootstrap, and you have lots of great options for a brochure site. For this
site, I chose the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.blacktie.co/2013/10/pratt-app-landing-page/&#34;&gt;Pratt&lt;/a&gt; theme from
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.blacktie.co/about/&#34;&gt;BlackTie&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks, Carlos! If you need a custom
theme, Carlos does freelance work too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2015/02/pratt-copia.png&#34; alt=&#34;Pratt&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;Hosting On GitHub Pages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d say &amp;ldquo;GitHub Pages is the best-kept secret&amp;rdquo;, but it&amp;rsquo;s not really a secret
anymore among the people likely to be reading this blog. If you&amp;rsquo;re not familiar
with GitHub Pages, you should really look into it. It&amp;rsquo;s easily the best way to
host small sites these days. Anything that doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to be highly dynamic,
and doesn&amp;rsquo;t need HTTPS access, is a great fit. Even things like blogs that need
commenting functionality can work great this way. What you get is free, &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt;
hosting with a built-in CDN, and everything&amp;rsquo;s taken care of for you. You can use
Gist to host your source code examples and snippets nicely. And
maintaining and publishing the site just couldn&amp;rsquo;t be much easier, since GitHub
hosts the source code, issues, and so on for free as well. &lt;a href=&#34;https://pages.github.com/&#34;&gt;Learn more about
GitHub pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_4&#34;&gt;A Spash of Panache&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cover image you saw at the top of this post adds a dash of visual flair. If
you produce any content and want it to be more attractive and desirable, such as
ebooks or tutorials, an eye-catching cover image makes all the difference. If
you have a flat image of the cover, though, how do you turn it into something
more visually appealing? How do you do this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2015/02/hpm-rendering.png&#34; alt=&#34;HPM Rendered&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have access to Photoshop, and I found a great set of ready-made Photoshop
actions to do this. The site is called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psdcovers.com/&#34;&gt;PSD Covers&lt;/a&gt;
and it contains an action that&amp;rsquo;s ready to use for practically any kind of cover
you can dream up. One caveat, it didn&amp;rsquo;t initially work well for me due to a bug
in Photoshop CC 2014, but the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psdcovers.com/photoshop-cc-2014-1-0-canvas-dpi-bug/&#34;&gt;workaround&lt;/a&gt; is
easy. I used the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psdcovers.com/softcover019/&#34;&gt;Softcover Handbook&lt;/a&gt;
action. Thanks very much to Simon Lord for sharing this great set of resources
freely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_5&#34;&gt;Making The Image Smaller&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever I use an image like the above of the book cover, I tend to run it
through &lt;a href=&#34;http://tinypng.com/&#34;&gt;TinyPNG&lt;/a&gt;. I often reduce images to just 10% or 20%
of their original size with this great resource. This makes it a lot more
feasible to include high-resolution versions of such images so they&amp;rsquo;ll look
really sharp on devices with very high-resolution screens, like a
Retina or better Apple device, or even my own favorite Android tablet, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2015/01/19/install-cyanogenmod-nook-hdplus/&#34;&gt;B&amp;amp;N
Nook
HD+&lt;/a&gt;.
If you have a JPEG image, there&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;https://tinyjpg.com/&#34;&gt;TinyJPEG&lt;/a&gt; site too.
The resulting hi-res images look great and download fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_6&#34;&gt;Writing The Content&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the easy and fun part for me, because I like to write. In this case, I
mostly just copy-pasted the content off the old Wordpress site, and then
massaged it a bit. I did discard all of the old blog posts that used to exist on
that site, but I don&amp;rsquo;t think anyone cares. It never should have been a &amp;ldquo;blog&amp;rdquo; to
begin with; a single-page brochureware site is all that&amp;rsquo;s necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s your opinion of High Performance MySQL?</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/09/05/whats-your-opinion-of-high-performance-mysql/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Sep 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/09/05/whats-your-opinion-of-high-performance-mysql/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The second edition of High Performance MySQL has 27 reviews on Amazon, but the third edition only has 5 so far. By this point I assume many of you have a copy and have read it cover to cover. I&amp;rsquo;d really appreciate your reviews &amp;ndash; when purchasing, people look not only at the star rating but at the number of reviews. You can create a review &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/High-Performance-MySQL-Optimization-Replication/product-reviews/1449314287/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. And thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>High Performance MySQL 3rd edition now available</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/03/08/high-performance-mysql-3rd-edition-now-available/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/03/08/high-performance-mysql-3rd-edition-now-available/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920022343.do&#34;&gt;third edition&lt;/a&gt; is now available in ePub, Mobi, and PDF formats. Print format should be available early next week.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What sets O&#39;Reilly apart: attention to detail</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/02/16/what-sets-oreilly-apart-attention-to-detail/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/02/16/what-sets-oreilly-apart-attention-to-detail/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;O&amp;rsquo;Reilly isn&amp;rsquo;t the only excellent tech publisher, but they&amp;rsquo;re the one whose books most consistently give me pleasure to read. After going through the process of writing two books with them, one of the things that&amp;rsquo;s struck me is how much they invest into the thankless tasks such as indexing, proofreading, and copyediting their authors&amp;rsquo; work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are probably many steps in the production process &amp;ndash; what happens after the author &amp;ldquo;finishes&amp;rdquo; the book &amp;ndash; that I know nothing about. But these are areas where I&amp;rsquo;ve had enough opportunity to see the specialists in action to understand that it&amp;rsquo;s brutally hard work, which must also be quite expensive for O&amp;rsquo;Reilly. And yet there are few things that make a book less enjoyable to me than a crappy index, confusing writing, or obvious lack of proofreading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an author and a perfectionist, I appreciate O&amp;rsquo;Reilly&amp;rsquo;s investments in these areas even more than I used to. I&amp;rsquo;ve even reviewed a topical book from another publisher that misspelled the product name on the back cover in one-inch-high font! Every time I think about my book, I feel glad that I&amp;rsquo;m with O&amp;rsquo;Reilly instead of one of the other publishers who might try to save money by sending my book to the press unpolished.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Get a free copy of High Performance MySQL 3rd Edition!</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/02/15/get-a-free-copy-of-high-performance-mysql-3rd-edition/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/02/15/get-a-free-copy-of-high-performance-mysql-3rd-edition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Want a free copy of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/High-Performance-MySQL-Optimization-Replication/dp/1449314287/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;High Performance MySQL, Third Edition&lt;/a&gt;? If you &lt;a href=&#34;http://perconalive-mysql-conference-expo-2012.eventbrite.com/&#34;&gt;register&lt;/a&gt; before the early-bird pricing expires for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/live/mysql-conference-2012/&#34;&gt;MySQL Conference in April&lt;/a&gt;, and use the discount code PL-Book, you&amp;rsquo;ll get to take a free copy home from the conference!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://vividcortex.com/&#34;&gt;VividCortex&lt;/a&gt; is the startup I founded in 2012. It&amp;rsquo;s the easiest way to monitor what
your servers are doing in production. It does TCP network
traffic analysis. VividCortex offers &lt;a href=&#34;https://vividcortex.com/monitoring/mysql/&#34;&gt;MySQL performance
monitoring&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://vividcortex.com/monitoring/postgres/&#34;&gt;PostgreSQL
performance management&lt;/a&gt; among many
other features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now, a status update: I&amp;rsquo;m currently proofing the QC2 (quality control #2) revision of the book; after this, the book goes to manufacturing. The PDF is now 820 pages, which is a lot of work to proofread. You can imagine how much more in-depth we&amp;rsquo;ve been able to go with so many more pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.highperfmysql.com/sample-chapter/&#34;&gt;free sample&lt;/a&gt; online is Chapter 8, on optimizing MySQL configuration. Liz van Dijk just &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/#!/lizztheblizz/status/169805049403424768&#34;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt; this about it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sample chapter of High Perf MySQL 3rd Ed is both amazingly to the point and hilarious at times. Instant buy for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven&amp;rsquo;t yet, I encourage you to take a look at the sample. Then go register for the conference to get your free copy, and I&amp;rsquo;ll see you in Santa Clara! We&amp;rsquo;re also arranging a book-signing at the conference, so you can get some scribbles on your copy if you want!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>High Performance MySQL Third Edition pre-order available</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/01/13/high-performance-mysql-third-edition-pre-order-available/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/01/13/high-performance-mysql-third-edition-pre-order-available/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You can pre-order the new edition of High Performance MySQL now on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/High-Performance-MySQL-Optimization-Replication/dp/1449314287/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; or via &lt;a href=&#34;http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920022343.do&#34;&gt;O&amp;rsquo;Reilly&amp;rsquo;s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Bergen called the second edition &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ebergen.net/wordpress/2010/07/20/how-to-be-a-mysql-dba-and-the-best-mysql-book-on-the-planet/&#34;&gt;the best MySQL book on the planet&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;. What will the third edition be called? The best in the solar system? This reminds me of a joke, supposed to be a true story: three pizza restaurants next to each other had signs saying &amp;ldquo;best pizza in town,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;best pizza in the world,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;best pizza on this block.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Status update on High Performance MySQL</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2011/11/21/status-update-on-high-performance-mysql/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2011 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2011/11/21/status-update-on-high-performance-mysql/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The third edition is nearly done. I&amp;rsquo;ve committed first drafts of all chapters, and all but one appendix. I need to do the last appendix and then rewrite the preface, which is a few days of work at my current pace. After that, it&amp;rsquo;s the usual tech review, copyediting, updates to figures, etc &amp;ndash; and then it&amp;rsquo;s off to production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m really pleased with this edition. I was planning on it just being a refresh of the second edition to reflect what&amp;rsquo;s new in MySQL-land, but it&amp;rsquo;s almost a complete rewrite. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot more focus on a logical approach throughout: what happens in the server, what are the limitations, why this matters, what are the practical consequences and applications, and therefore&amp;hellip;. The &amp;ldquo;and therefore&amp;rdquo; is the real reason you buy a book such as this one.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Progress on High Performance MySQL 3rd Edition</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2011/10/12/progress-on-high-performance-mysql-3rd-edition/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2011 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2011/10/12/progress-on-high-performance-mysql-3rd-edition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few people have asked me how it&amp;rsquo;s going, so I thought I&amp;rsquo;d just share it with everyone. Things are going great. I&amp;rsquo;m writing much more quickly than I thought I would be, and as a result I&amp;rsquo;m finding I have time to do more changes than I thought I could, which makes me happy. I should be finished drafting the chapters by the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, the faster than expected pace is giving me a chance to address one of the big weaknesses of the second edition. In many places, the second edition is a collection of facts and experiences. It says what and why, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t convey a process or method, and it doesn&amp;rsquo;t teach you how to think about things and apply the results to situations beyond what the book covers. I&amp;rsquo;m finding a number of key areas to remedy that: performance optimization, profiling, indexing, high availability, scalability, and so on. I&amp;rsquo;m adding an explanation of the principles and consequences, and actually showing real case studies selected from the most interesting customer issues I&amp;rsquo;ve seen at Percona. These illustrate the process or method I explain, and then I wrap that up by pointing out the key bits and reinforcing why they&amp;rsquo;re important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m also adding chapter summaries. Summaries are hard to write. They should synthesize, not restate, the main points, and they should organize the reader&amp;rsquo;s thoughts for the transition to the next chapter. I hope I&amp;rsquo;m doing a good enough job at this, but it&amp;rsquo;s bound to be better than the second edition, which didn&amp;rsquo;t have summaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Detailed outlining is saving me. After writing the second edition, I realized that I&amp;rsquo;d spent about four times as much time rewriting as I did writing. This time I did a lot of outlining before I went to the writing stage, down to the level of individual thoughts and the relationship between them &amp;ndash; nearly prose level, but not quite. Prose is much harder to reorganize and cut-and-paste than bullet points, because it requires correct grammar. Outlining doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be grammatically correct. The effort I put into outlining in exhaustive detail is definitely paying off. When I find a section or chapter that I want to rewrite instead of just updating, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t plan for that, I back off and go back to the outlining. It&amp;rsquo;s so much more efficient. For example, I just caught myself starting to spin my wheels on partitioning, which is a section that I decide to rewrite to convey a how-to-think approach instead of what-to-think. I noticed the inefficiency, went to the outline in a text file, came back to the chapter, and ended up finishing it very quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, and I never thought I&amp;rsquo;d say this, but I&amp;rsquo;m using Microsoft Word and it&amp;rsquo;s making my life easier. The copyeditors use Word, and I knew I was going to have to use something that reads and writes .doc files eventually, so I decided to just use Word all the way through. I threw up a virtualbox with Windows XP, went out and bought a copy of Word 2010 for $150 or so, and installed it. It runs great in the virtual machine, and it is so much better than Open Office it&amp;rsquo;s not even in the same league. It works very well, with a lot of features that really do enhance my productivity. It isn&amp;rsquo;t Free Software, but maybe I&amp;rsquo;m growing up and coming to terms with the real world: sometimes getting things done is more important than principles, and $150 is less valuable than the time I&amp;rsquo;m saving. (I knew that I definitely was not going to use Open Office this time around, no matter what. I was planning on plain-text and Vim. But Word is actually more productive, I believe, by the time I factor in the interaction with the editors and other back-and-forth.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>High Performance MySQL, Third Edition</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2011/09/14/high-performance-mysql-third-edition/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2011 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2011/09/14/high-performance-mysql-third-edition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have just signed the contract for High Performance MySQL, Third Edition. The third edition will include major updates and new content in these areas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recent performance and reliability advances, particularly in MySQL 5.5 and the InnoDB storage engine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A new chapter on using MySQL in cloud computing environments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Updates on modern hardware, including many CPUs, large memory, and solid-state storage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improvements in clustering and high availability, including middleware and third-party solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improvements in replication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New material on profiling MySQL, benchmarking, and tools and techniques to help you measure, monitor, and manage your MySQL installations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book will be available for purchase early next year. It&amp;rsquo;s been a great three years since the &lt;a href=&#34;http://tinyurl.com/highperfmysql&#34;&gt;second edition&lt;/a&gt; was published, and although it&amp;rsquo;s selling strongly and is still referred to as &amp;ldquo;the&amp;rdquo; book for MySQL performance, it&amp;rsquo;s outdated and needs to be revised. And frankly I&amp;rsquo;ve learned a lot since 2008. The third edition will again be our best effort to give away everything we know, and help you help yourself as much as you can.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>High Performance MySQL in your language</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/12/08/high-performance-mysql-in-your-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2008 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/12/08/high-performance-mysql-in-your-language/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oreilly.com/&#34;&gt;O&amp;rsquo;Reilly&lt;/a&gt; tells me that translation rights for our book, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/dp/0596101716?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;High Performance MySQL Second Edition&lt;/a&gt; have been purchased in the following languages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Korean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Russian&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Portuguese&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Polish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spanish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Czech&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of them were sold quite a while ago, and some are more recent. Portuguese was the first. I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to learning all these languages (except for Spanish, which I already sort of know) so I can read the book in them&amp;hellip; in my copious spare time!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Update on High Performance MySQL, 2nd Edition</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/10/04/update-on-high-performance-mysql-2nd-edition/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2008 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/10/04/update-on-high-performance-mysql-2nd-edition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just thought I&amp;rsquo;d drop a line about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/dp/0596101716?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;our book&lt;/a&gt;. Sales appear to be doing well still: the book is still at Amazon sales rank 3,213 and seems to hold pretty steady there. A lot of people have discovered it and are recommending it &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;http://fallenpegasus.livejournal.com/758972.html&#34;&gt;including members of MySQL&amp;rsquo;s professional services team&lt;/a&gt;. There are several positive reviews on Amazon (though if you like the book, a few more wouldn&amp;rsquo;t hurt either). I&amp;rsquo;ve been hearing pretty much nothing but good things about it. So, all in all I am very happy about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t actually seen any royalties, though. I assume it will be a long time before my advances are paid back. A friend of mine who&amp;rsquo;s an author told me that after a few years he got his first royalty check, for a few bucks. I plan on spending mine all in one place.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>High Performance MySQL is going to press, again</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/07/15/high-performance-mysql-is-going-to-press-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2008 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/07/15/high-performance-mysql-is-going-to-press-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Apparently &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.highperfmysql.com/&#34;&gt;High Performance MySQL, 2nd Edition&lt;/a&gt; is selling quite well &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;m not sure exactly how well &amp;ndash; because we&amp;rsquo;re preparing for a second printing. This makes me very happy. I don&amp;rsquo;t think they anticipated going back to the press for quite some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book fluctuates between sales rank 1000 and 2000 on Amazon during the day, and has reached as high as 600 or so. This is just phenomenal. The O&amp;rsquo;Reilly team was psyched when it broke 5000, and so was I &amp;ndash; but now we&amp;rsquo;ve stayed under 2000 for a long time (except when Amazon sold out of it). Frankly I&amp;rsquo;d have thought that for a niche-market book like this, we&amp;rsquo;d have been in the 10,000 range or something like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly we (the authors, editors, publisher, etc) have done something right! This is a great feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for sending errata, by the way. I have just completed proofreading the whole book myself, and found a number of things that may be fixed in the second printing. I think certain types of errors won&amp;rsquo;t be fixed, but the important ones certainly will be.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What if you find errors in High Performance MySQL?</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/06/28/what-if-you-find-errors-in-high-performance-mysql/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2008 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/06/28/what-if-you-find-errors-in-high-performance-mysql/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The book is done now, right? What&amp;rsquo;s next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t tell my wife this, but a book is never done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now I&amp;rsquo;m proofreading the printed copy. I proofread PDF after PDF during production, but some problems will always slip through and make it to paper. I&amp;rsquo;m finding quite a few little mistakes. For example, at one point we refer to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tpc.org/&#34;&gt;TPC&lt;/a&gt; as TCP three times in a row. Oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These problems will be corrected in the next printing. Please notify me if you find any errors yourself, and I&amp;rsquo;ll add them to the list of things to fix! Also let me know if you find things that should just be &amp;ldquo;fixed&amp;rdquo; in general. For example, the layout and page-breaking on pages 364 and 365 is totally confusing &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s hard to tell which figures are associated with which text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not offering rewards like Donald Knuth, sorry&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will place a list of errata on the official &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.highperfmysql.com/&#34;&gt;High Performance MySQL Second Edition&lt;/a&gt; website, including a non-mangled Figure 8-12. (Another thing that didn&amp;rsquo;t make it through production unscathed.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What it&#39;s like to write a technical book, continued</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/06/23/what-its-like-to-write-a-technical-book-continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2008 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/06/23/what-its-like-to-write-a-technical-book-continued/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;My post on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/06/15/what-is-it-like-to-write-a-technical-book/&#34;&gt;what it&amp;rsquo;s like to write a technical book&lt;/a&gt; was a stream-of-consciousness look at the process of writing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.highperfmysql.com/&#34;&gt;High Performance MySQL, Second Edition&lt;/a&gt;. I got a lot of responses from it and learned some neat things I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have learned if I hadn&amp;rsquo;t written the post. I also got a lot of questions, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://toc.oreilly.com/2008/06/oreilly-author-and-editor-air.html&#34;&gt;my editor wrote a response&lt;/a&gt; too. I want to follow up on these things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Was I fair, balanced and honest?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really intended to write the post as just &amp;ldquo;here&amp;rsquo;s what it&amp;rsquo;s like, just so you&amp;rsquo;re prepared.&amp;rdquo; But at some point I got really deep into it and lost my context. That&amp;rsquo;s when I started to write about the things that didn&amp;rsquo;t go so smoothly with the publisher, and some of these things had a little extra sting in them that I would have done well to edit out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of us are human and the process wasn&amp;rsquo;t that bad, all things considered &amp;ndash; the book was just a massive project that put huge demands on all of us and stressed everything from the capabilities of our chosen tools to our patience. As the &lt;a href=&#34;http://toc.oreilly.com/2008/06/oreilly-author-and-editor-air.html&#34;&gt;editor points out in his response to my blog post&lt;/a&gt;, this is precisely why nobody else has ever been able to pull this off. This book stands head and shoulders above the crowd. It&amp;rsquo;s just hard to write, and very few people in the world actually have the knowledge to do it, much less the time, inclination, and ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything I said was (I believe) factual and correct, although as the editor points out there are different stories behind them. I also want to mention that I&amp;rsquo;d shared all those concerns with my editor; I avoid criticizing people behind their backs. In hindsight, throwing all of my concerns onto a blog post without warning isn&amp;rsquo;t the kind of thing I like to do either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I believe I was honest, but unfair to the editor. I&amp;rsquo;ve apologized to him. And by the way, yes I would work with him again, and I fully expect that it would be easier because I have learned more about the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran this post by my editor before publishing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;A deeper explanation of my heuristics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several people asked me to say more about my heuristics for improving the quality of the writing. I&amp;rsquo;ve already explained many of them, but here&amp;rsquo;s more:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(were|was|is|are|has been|be)( [a-zA-Z]+)? [a-zA-Z]+ed\&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This regular expression can help find some occurrences of passive voice. It finds a word or phrase that&amp;rsquo;s some variation on the verb &amp;ldquo;to be,&amp;rdquo; usually in the past tense; followed by an optional word (probably an adjective); followed by another word that ends in &amp;ldquo;-ed,&amp;rdquo; which is also potentially a verb in the past tense. This is not the only way to write in the passive voice, but it&amp;rsquo;s kind of the classic. Here are some examples: &amp;ldquo;the blog post was posted,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;the benchmark was rapidly created.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(were|was|is|are|ha[sd] been|be)( [a-zA-Z]+)? [a-zA-Z]+e[dn]\&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An enhanced version. As I looked at the preceding point, I saw some other simple examples it doesn&amp;rsquo;t catch. For example, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t catch &amp;ldquo;had been&amp;rdquo; and it doesn&amp;rsquo;t catch verbs like &amp;ldquo;written.&amp;rdquo; Ironically, the first thing that came to mind as I thought about examples was &amp;ldquo;the book had been written.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;while|since&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s nothing wrong with these words, except when they&amp;rsquo;re used in lieu of &amp;ldquo;because&amp;rdquo; to indicate causality. This is a problem for non-native English speakers, because these words have a temporal meaning too. For example, &amp;ldquo;Since MySQL 4.1 has no stored procedures, you have to use MySQL 5.0 if you want stored procedures.&amp;rdquo; If you aren&amp;rsquo;t a native English speaker, and even if you are, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to read that as &amp;ldquo;MySQL has had no stored procedures since version 4.1, &amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; and then when your eyes reach the part about MySQL 5.0, it makes no sense. My rule for this is to say &amp;ldquo;because&amp;rdquo; when I mean &amp;ldquo;because.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;using&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real examples: &amp;ldquo;Using MyISAM tables works very well&amp;rdquo; can become &amp;ldquo;MyISAM tables work very well.&amp;rdquo; And &amp;ldquo;A final possibility is simply to switch to using a table&amp;rdquo; can become &amp;ldquo;Finally, you can use a table&amp;rdquo; instead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;in order&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The phrase &amp;ldquo;in order to&amp;rdquo; can almost always be replaced by &amp;ldquo;to.&amp;rdquo; It also tends to show a rough transition between the first and second phrases in a sentence. Perhaps these phrases should be integrated into a single phrase. &amp;ldquo;You can use this regex in order to find poorly constructed sentences&amp;rdquo; can become &amp;ldquo;this regex can find poorly constructed sentences&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;You can find poorly constructed sentences with this regex.&amp;rdquo; I prefer the latter; it is very direct, and that straightforward, simple writing style is really important in complex subject matter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;of course|without saying|obviously|clearly|needless&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It goes &lt;strong&gt;without saying&lt;/strong&gt;, but &lt;strong&gt;of course&lt;/strong&gt; these words &lt;strong&gt;obviously&lt;/strong&gt; point out when I&amp;rsquo;m writing stupid things that I &lt;strong&gt;clearly&lt;/strong&gt; need to take a closer look at. &lt;strong&gt;Needless to say&lt;/strong&gt;, most of the phrases in this paragraph are indeed needless to say. They are a red flag for lazy writing, such as glossing over a difficult point that should instead be explained &amp;ndash; hard work, but necessary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;whether&lt;/code&gt;
I found quite a few places where the phrase &amp;ldquo;whether or not&amp;rdquo; was used. This can be shortened: &amp;ldquo;to see whether or not the disk is the problem&amp;rdquo; can become &amp;ldquo;to see whether the disk is the problem.&amp;rdquo; But better yet, the phrase often glues together poorly written phrases into an awkward sentence, just as &amp;ldquo;in order to&amp;rdquo; does. Can &amp;ldquo;whether&amp;rdquo; be replaced by &amp;ldquo;if?&amp;rdquo; Or does the sentence or paragraph just need to be reworked completely?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;allow&lt;/code&gt;
This word can usually be replaced by &amp;ldquo;let.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;The remaining settings allow MySQL to allocate more RAM&amp;rdquo; can become &amp;ldquo;The remaining settings let MySQL allocate more RAM.&amp;rdquo; Occasionally, it is part of a larger phrase or thought needs to be shortened and clarified. &amp;ldquo;When nobody is writing, readers obtain read locks that allow other readers to do the same&amp;rdquo; became &amp;ldquo;When nobody is writing, readers can obtain read locks, which don&amp;rsquo;t conflict with other read locks.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ensure&lt;/code&gt;
I found that this word is often subtly misused. It really means &amp;ldquo;guarantee&amp;rdquo; but is often used as &amp;ldquo;double-check&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;make sure.&amp;rdquo; I don&amp;rsquo;t want to be too dogmatic about this word: its usage in modern English is complex (&lt;a href=&#34;http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/assure&#34;&gt;see the usage note on assure here&lt;/a&gt;; that in itself might be a reason to avoid it). But I found many places where I wanted to remove it in favor of an explicit instruction that tells the reader to take action. &amp;ldquo;Ensure&amp;rdquo; as an instruction is kind of a politically correct way to tell someone to do something, and I&amp;rsquo;m not afraid to just tell you to do it if I think you need to. I don&amp;rsquo;t want you to miss my meaning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;only&lt;/code&gt;
I have a habit of using this word incorrectly. &amp;ldquo;I only have ten fingers&amp;rdquo; should be &amp;ldquo;I have only ten fingers.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;as (we|you)|again,&lt;/code&gt;
These phrases usually show a place where the writing is confused and redundant. They show up in places like &amp;ldquo;as we already said, you should tune your server&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;again, you should tune your server.&amp;rdquo; Any instruction to the reader to break the narrative flow is a place to examine whether the concepts are in the right order. Cross-references, footnotes, and reminders are not always evil, but they&amp;rsquo;re to be regarded with suspicion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Readability metrics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tools I used to find sentences and phrases that score badly on some readability metric were pretty helpful to me as I tightened the writing up more and more. Nobody has reviewed the book yet, but I think when they do, they&amp;rsquo;ll be unlikely to mention &amp;ldquo;oh, and by the way the writing is wonderfully compact!&amp;rdquo; If we pulled this off right, you won&amp;rsquo;t notice that the writing is clear and compact. Writing is like a stereo system: you&amp;rsquo;re supposed to hear the music, not the speakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, my point is that we expanded the first edition&amp;rsquo;s actual coverage many times over, and ended up with only 658 pages of actual material. So the writing is much more compressed, and to do that you have to find and eliminate confusing writing. Confusing writing usually means that the concepts don&amp;rsquo;t flow clearly, and it takes more words to say the same thing because you&amp;rsquo;re kind of bumbling about, gesturing at your meaning from several angles instead of saying it clearly just once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s how I analyzed each chapter:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I used OpenOffice&amp;rsquo;s export feature to export the file to MediaWiki format. This is a plain-text markup format. I forget now why I didn&amp;rsquo;t just export to text, but there was something about MediaWiki format that made it easier to munge with Perl.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I ran my clean_text.pl program against the exported file to convert the format to a simpler one without special characters and markup. Some of the markup (footnotes, for example) stayed in the text and confused the metrics, but that&amp;rsquo;s life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I ran my analyze_text.pl program against this to find the &amp;ldquo;worst&amp;rdquo; places.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I wrote in my previous post, the analyzer uses a combination of readability metrics and &amp;ldquo;other stuff&amp;rdquo; to measure the badness of each sentence and paragraph. It aggregates sentences and paragraphs by the metrics. I calculated the number of words, percent of complex words, syllables per word, number of sentences, words per sentence, and a bunch of other things, as well as the standard readability metrics. Each sentence and paragraph got scored on these. Then I printed overall metrics, and sorted the sentences and paragraphs worst-first and printed out a snippet of the offending text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a lot of work. If I had been writing with Vim, I could have done better. I could have used the compiler integration and set my &amp;ldquo;make&amp;rdquo; program to the analysis program. If you use Vim and you don&amp;rsquo;t know about this, it&amp;rsquo;s a pity. My next book will be written in Vim, by the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I probably could have done better regardless, but this was good enough. I just searched for the snippets and then examined what was going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were some false positives. For example, bullet-points often scored badly on the readability metrics, and so a five-word bullet point item would look like terrible writing just because it was short enough that it had a high percentage of complex words. It&amp;rsquo;s not an exact science. Maybe next time will be better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;d like to see the source code and its results at some intermediate stage in the writing process, it&amp;rsquo;s all &lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/xaprb/8492226&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>High Performance MySQL is here!</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/06/20/high-performance-mysql-is-here/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2008 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/06/20/high-performance-mysql-is-here/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The book, that is. My dog is already studying it. You should buy a few copies for yourself, your family, and all your pets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2008/06/hpmysql_carbon.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;High Performance MySQL is here!&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>