<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Conferences on Xaprb </title>
      <generator uri="https://hugo.spf13.com">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://www.xaprb.com/categories/conferences/index.xml/</link>
    
    
    
    <updated>Mon, 03 Nov 2014 00:00:00 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can You Bring A Guitar To Velocity?</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/11/03/bring-guitar-velocity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/11/03/bring-guitar-velocity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I need help. I&amp;rsquo;m giving an Ignite talk at &lt;a href=&#34;http://velocityconf.com/velocityeu2014/&#34;&gt;Velocity
EU&lt;/a&gt; that involves a guitar. I
don&amp;rsquo;t want to bring a guitar all the way from America just for this. Would you
please loan me one?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2014/01/4542297929_49286da35a.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;guitar&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to be anything special &amp;ndash; any old classical or acoustic 6-string
standard guitar will do. All I&amp;rsquo;m going to do is tune it.&lt;br /&gt;
If you can bring a guitar to loan me, please post in the comments or give me a
shout on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/xaprb&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you in advance!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/doug88888/4542297929/&#34;&gt;Pic Credit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Win a Free Pass to Velocity</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/10/30/win-free-pass-velocity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/10/30/win-free-pass-velocity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://velocityconf.com&#34;&gt;O&amp;rsquo;Reilly Velocity&lt;/a&gt; is November 17-19 in Barcelona. O’Reilly gave me a 2-day pass to give away, and I decided to have some fun with it. We’re also giving away a pass on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://vividcortex.com/blog/2014/10/30/win-a-free-pass-to-velocity-barcelona/&#34;&gt;VividCortex blog&lt;/a&gt;, so you can double your odds of winning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For your chance to win a 2-day pass, do one of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Answer any of the following questions; or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a haiku that’s somehow relevant to Velocity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tweet your answers to @xaprb with #velocitytrivia. You can find the answers to the questions on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://velocityconf.com&#34;&gt;velocityconf.com&lt;/a&gt; website. Speed and accuracy is your friend in this game, as answers will not be accepted after November 6. I’ll announce the winner November 7. Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q.1: Which sessions are about anomaly detection? Make sure you look for one that doesn’t have “anomaly” in the title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q.2: Which session (link to it) might help you avoid cognitive traps?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q.3: Which session (link to it) is absolutely swimming in puns?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q.4:What are the “five reasons” to come to Velocity? Bolded reasons are fine. (hint, reading About Velocity will help)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q.5: Which Velocity EU Event gives you 5 minutes to get on stage and talk your latest passion, idea or hack?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Q.6: Who’s going to get up on stage and use math and physics to tune a musical instrument, and what does that have to do with web performance and operations?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meditate With Me At Velocity</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/06/24/meditate-at-velocity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/06/24/meditate-at-velocity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Join me and other &lt;a href=&#34;http://velocityconf.com/&#34;&gt;Velocity&lt;/a&gt; attendees during the Wednesday afternoon 2:40pm break for a 10-15 minute guided meditation session appropriate for people of any faith or of none.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meditation has a host of scientifically proven immediate and long-term benefits. If you get an extra 10% of clarity and effectiveness for the rest of the afternoon, you&amp;rsquo;ll end up learning more and making your conference experience more worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2014/06/stones.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;meditation&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll guide you through a process of checking in and becoming aware of your body and mind. Then we&amp;rsquo;ll let the body rest until we come back for it, while we turn our attention to the breath for a few minutes. During this time we&amp;rsquo;ll notice and be gently curious about thoughts and feelings that spontaneously arise. Then we&amp;rsquo;ll bring our attention back to our bodies and senses, and finish with a few deep breaths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This practice is easy and nonjudgmental. Your mileage may vary, but I find that I&amp;rsquo;m able to take the resulting sense of calm and clarity with me into my other activities afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll begin at 3pm sharp, so please arrive a few minutes early. I haven&amp;rsquo;t yet finalized the meeting location. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/xaprb&#34;&gt;Follow me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and when I settle on a good location, I&amp;rsquo;ll announce it. Retweet my announcement if you plan to join us, so I have a sense of how much room we&amp;rsquo;ll need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to add this to your Google Calendar, here&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;https://www.google.com/calendar/event?action=TEMPLATE&amp;tmeid=djBmbGRuM2RhZm5rMjBwazc4Yml2b2RjOTAgYmFyb25Adml2aWRjb3J0ZXguY29t&amp;tmsrc=baron%40vividcortex.com&#34;&gt;link to an event&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/villamon/4468869725/&#34;&gt;Pic Credit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two of My Favorite Conferences: Velocity and Surge</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/06/18/my-favorite-conferences-velocity-surge/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/06/18/my-favorite-conferences-velocity-surge/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Two of my favorite conferences are coming up. One&amp;rsquo;s just next week, and
another&amp;rsquo;s in the fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Velocity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kqzyfj.com/click-7094008-11742203&#34;&gt;Velocity&lt;/a&gt; is such a great event.
I wanted to go for years, and when I finally did it was honestly one of the
highlights of my professional career. I still don&amp;rsquo;t know what I did get get
invited to speak that first year. It was a golden horseshoe falling out of the
sky and landing right in front of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2014/06/velocity.png&#34; alt=&#34;Velocity&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not the talks (though those are great). It&amp;rsquo;s the people. The people
at Velocity are the people I want to spend my career with, the people thinking
about the same types of problems I am, the people trying to work on similar
solutions. They&amp;rsquo;re building companies, they&amp;rsquo;re making open source, they&amp;rsquo;re
customers, they&amp;rsquo;re consultants, they&amp;rsquo;re just passionate practitioners. It&amp;rsquo;s just
amazing what happens when this kind of group gets together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yeah, it&amp;rsquo;s partially because I&amp;rsquo;m a loyal O&amp;rsquo;Reilly fan. I admit it: I love
O&amp;rsquo;Reilly, I truly do. It&amp;rsquo;s a remarkable group of people that has inspired me for
more than a decade, and I owe a lot of who I am to O&amp;rsquo;Reilly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Velocity starts next Tuesday in Santa Clara. If you don&amp;rsquo;t go to that one,
there&amp;rsquo;s several other incarnations in New York, Barcelona, and Beijing at
different times of the year. I&amp;rsquo;ll be in Santa Clara next week, in the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://vividcortex.com/&#34;&gt;VividCortex&lt;/a&gt; booth. Come say hi if you&amp;rsquo;re there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an affiliate link that has a 20% discount code embedded in it:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kqzyfj.com/click-7094008-11742203&#34;&gt;Velocity AFF20&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Surge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve often said that &lt;a href=&#34;http://surge.omniti.com/&#34;&gt;Surge&lt;/a&gt; is Velocity without the grandiosity and with more
emphasis on hardcore software and systems engineering &amp;mdash; and a much smaller
price tag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2014/06/surge.png&#34; alt=&#34;Surge&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been at every Surge event since the beginning, and I would not miss it.
It&amp;rsquo;s that good. I can say all the same things about Surge as I can about
Velocity, except it&amp;rsquo;s a lot easier and less expensive to get to, and it&amp;rsquo;s a lot
easier to decide to attend the talks there. At Velocity sometimes I feel lost
because the event is so big, and I end up not really attending many
presentations, and just hanging out in the hallway track. Not so at Surge.
Bonus: talks are always recorded and online, so you can go find out for yourself
how good they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The climate at Surge is also quite different in terms of the topics. Velocity is
ostensibly about the Web: backend, frontend, browser, and mobile are front and
center. As a result, you can certainly find yourself in an unfamiliar clique, if
you&amp;rsquo;re, say, a database administrator at a lunch table full of people who want to
argue about how much hardware acceleration will save battery life in a mobile
browser. Whether that bothers you or not is up to you, but I&amp;rsquo;ve found that Surge
is birds of my feather for sure. It&amp;rsquo;s all about people who build what runs the
Internet (not necessarily what you use to engage with the Internet).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m pretty loyal to the folks behind Surge, too. For one thing, a lot of them
are the same people who make Velocity awesome. For another, many of them have
helped me tremendously in my career and in founding VividCortex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surge is in early-bird pricing right now. Having run conferences before, I know
why early-bird pricing exists. If you think you&amp;rsquo;ll attend, do yourself and them
a favor and sign up at a discount now. Here, click &lt;a href=&#34;http://surge.omniti.com/2014&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no conclusions. Conferences are good. I love Velocity. I love Surge.
Go. Learn a lot. Share a lot. Make the world a better place.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monitorama 2014: This One Weird Time-Series Math Trick</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/05/06/one-weird-time-series-math-trick/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/05/06/one-weird-time-series-math-trick/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Monitorama 2014 Portland has been a great show. I&amp;rsquo;ve enjoyed the technical
nature of the talks, the diversity of the speakers, the topics from hilarious to
thought-provoking, and the stage in a theater, set up for a Shakespearean
tragedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also taken a lot of notes. For example, Toufic from Metafor Software
suggested that the audience look into the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. I am proud of
the slide that made its way into my talk as a result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2014/05/smirnov.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Smirnov&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My slides are embedded below. Enjoy. I&amp;rsquo;ve also uploaded an &lt;a href=&#34;/media/2014/05/time-series-tricks.xlsx&#34;&gt;Excel spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt; you
can use to tinker with the math and reproduce my results. Let me know if I did
anything wrong, please!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://app.box.com/embed_widget/hnd0llg8tzut/s/o60h3cxbp5fa1u5jw1pu?view=list&amp;sort=name&amp;direction=ASC&amp;theme=blue&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;400&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen oallowfullscreen msallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Freeing some Velocity videos</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/11/09/freeing-some-velocity-videos/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/11/09/freeing-some-velocity-videos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Following my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/10/24/should-velocity-videos-be-free/&#34; title=&#34;Should Velocity videos be free?&#34;&gt;previous post on Velocity videos&lt;/a&gt;, I had some private email conversations with good folks at O&amp;rsquo;Reilly, and a really nice in-person exchange with a top-level person as well. I was surprised to hear them encourage me to publish my videos online freely!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still believe that nothing substitutes for the experience of attending an O&amp;rsquo;Reilly conference in-person, but I&amp;rsquo;ll also be the first to admit that my talks are usually more conceptual and academic than practical, and designed to start a conversation rather than to tell you the Truth According To Baron. Thus, I think they&amp;rsquo;re worth sharing more widely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O&amp;rsquo;Reilly alleviated my concerns about &amp;ldquo;killing the golden goose,&amp;rdquo; but I like one person&amp;rsquo;s take on the cost of O&amp;rsquo;Reilly&amp;rsquo;s conferences. &amp;ldquo;You think education is expensive? Try ignorance.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll post some of my past talks soon for your enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Get out of your comfort zone</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/10/25/get-out-of-your-comfort-zone/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/10/25/get-out-of-your-comfort-zone/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the most valuable life skills you can ever develop is to overcome the urge to stay within your comfort zone. If you stay where you&amp;rsquo;re familiar and feel safe, two things might happen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might find out that it&amp;rsquo;s not safe after all. Bad things can happen where you feel at home just as well as out of the familar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nothing good will happen. You might skate through life without even living it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week at Velocity I responded to an invitation from O&amp;rsquo;Reilly to join a lunch with Per Scholas. I didn&amp;rsquo;t know much about Per Scholas, but I&amp;rsquo;ve learned to say yes to invitations from O&amp;rsquo;Reilly. The night before, I watched an inspiring &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t0qcDwDPQ-Q&#34;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; during Ignite, from the founder of Per Scholas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impressed, I began to really look forward to spending some time with the Per Scholas folks the next day at lunch. The idea was pretty simple: people who were working through the Per Scholas training would pair up one-for-one (as I understand it) with people like myself &amp;ndash; technologists, entrepreneurs, hackers, makers, people with perhaps something to share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sat down at a table in the designated area, leaving lots of room beside me for people to join. None of the Per Scholas students was there yet. I chatted idly with two other people at the table. Soon one of the Per Scholas staff members sat down with us. I asked her a series of questions for ten minutes or so. She explained that she helped people with basic life and work skills, coaching and mentoring even after they leave the intensive study program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still no students had joined us. Suddenly I looked over at another table and saw that it had filled entirely with Per Scholas students, shoulder to shoulder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Basic life skill number 1 is to build your network and learn from unfamiliar people,&amp;rdquo; I remarked to the staffer next to me. &amp;ldquo;They are missing an opportunity to mingle with us.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Yes,&amp;rdquo; she answered. &amp;ldquo;They are.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then you could (metaphorically) hear the crickets chirping. I finished my lunch and left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;rsquo;t brag about myself, but I can say that the other people at that table were damn sure worth getting to know. As for me, I considered it a complete waste of my time; I&amp;rsquo;d chosen it over a conversation I really wanted to attend elsewhere. There&amp;rsquo;s another blog post in here somewhere &amp;ndash; this isn&amp;rsquo;t the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve had this kind of experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Per Scholas students aren&amp;rsquo;t paying anything (financially) for their training. Are they getting what they&amp;rsquo;re paying for? You bet they are. Like all of us, they will get out of it exactly what they put into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get out of your comfort zone. If you don&amp;rsquo;t, the worst thing in the world happens to you: &lt;em&gt;nothing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should Velocity videos be free?</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/10/24/should-velocity-videos-be-free/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/10/24/should-velocity-videos-be-free/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the closing keynote of the recent Velocity conference in New York, an audience member stepped up to the microphone and called for O&amp;rsquo;Reilly to provide videos of the event free to the public, instead of behind a paywall. The conference chairs, who don&amp;rsquo;t call the shots on such matters, squirmed and looked at the person who does call the shots, a few feet away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone volunteered the information that speakers are able to download their own talks and post them freely if they wish. The original commenter then asked the audience, which presumably included most of the speakers, to do so en masse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a speaker, frequent conference-goer, author, technologist, and even a sometimes-organizer of such events, I can&amp;rsquo;t say I agree with this suggestion. I think it&amp;rsquo;s self-defeating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The commenter&amp;rsquo;s request was prefaced by something to the effect of &amp;ldquo;we should open up all this great content and thought-provoking conversation more widely.&amp;rdquo; But I think that sometimes, you gotta want something badly enough to pay for it, even if it feels like it&amp;rsquo;s a shame to ask people to pay for access to the club that makes the world a better place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know O&amp;rsquo;Reilly&amp;rsquo;s numbers, but I know conferences are a tough business. O&amp;rsquo;Reilly&amp;rsquo;s in an even tougher industry in general &amp;ndash; publishing. Much of the thought leadership at events like Velocity comes from the authors, editors, bloggers, and other communicators of technical and cultural excellence. Most of these people have worked really hard for comparatively little financial reward. I never got the impression that my editor Andy Oram, who is really dedicated to his life&amp;rsquo;s passion, is a rich man. I would be surprised if O&amp;rsquo;Reilly is raking in the cash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The videos of the content are, as I understand, quite lucrative for O&amp;rsquo;Reilly. Maybe O&amp;rsquo;Reilly could consider something like making videos of conferences free after a couple of years when they&amp;rsquo;re selling less actively, but those videos are probably a big part of what makes Velocity possible &amp;ndash; and sustains their business overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Velocity conference, and those like it, is a venue for changing the world. I&amp;rsquo;ve witnessed it time and time again. The network that lives in and around the conferences, publishing, blogging, and so on is a symbiotic ecosystem. It&amp;rsquo;s all a very real part of O&amp;rsquo;Reilly&amp;rsquo;s mission to &amp;ldquo;spread the knowledge of innovators.&amp;rdquo; I know I sound like a shill, but seriously, not many organizations do what O&amp;rsquo;Reilly does, and you can&amp;rsquo;t undercut them without broad consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s not kill the golden goose. If you think the videos are valuable, great. Tell people they&amp;rsquo;re worth paying for. Better yet &amp;ndash; put your money where your mouth is and show up at the conference yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit&lt;/strong&gt; Just to clarify, I&amp;rsquo;m not advocating for O&amp;rsquo;Reilly to remove the freedom for speakers to do as they see fit with their own videos. I just don&amp;rsquo;t think it&amp;rsquo;s a good thing if every speaker decides to post the video just to make an end run around O&amp;rsquo;Reilly&amp;rsquo;s policy en masse. John Allspaw said it well in an email to me: &amp;ldquo;You think education is expensive? Try ignorance!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaking at Percona University Sept 12th</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/08/18/speaking-at-percona-university-sept-12th/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/08/18/speaking-at-percona-university-sept-12th/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be joining Percona for a free day of MySQL education and insight at their upcoming &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/news-and-events/percona-university/washington-dc&#34;&gt;Percona University Washington DC event on September 12th&lt;/a&gt;. My topic is accessing MySQL from Google&amp;rsquo;s Go programming language. I&amp;rsquo;ve learned a lot about this over the past year or so, and hopefully I can help you get a quick-start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re not familiar with Go, it&amp;rsquo;s the darling of the Hacker News crowd these days. Anything with &amp;ldquo;Go&amp;rdquo; in its title gets to the front page for at least a little while! Go is a great systems programming language. It&amp;rsquo;s safe to say I&amp;rsquo;ve fallen in love with it, and it&amp;rsquo;s now my favorite programming language of all those I&amp;rsquo;ve used over my entire career. I chose it because it&amp;rsquo;s ideally suited for VividCortex&amp;rsquo;s agent programs (zero dependencies, compiled, lightweight, high performance, robust, makes concurrency easy and safe), and we&amp;rsquo;re using it for our API servers and backend processing jobs for many of the same reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of great content at these free Percona University events. If you&amp;rsquo;re not near Washington DC, you should sign up for Percona&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/subscribe&#34;&gt;conferences and training newsletter&lt;/a&gt; so you find out about the next one near you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaking at Strata NYC: Making Big Data Small</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/08/18/speaking-at-strata-nyc-making-big-data-small/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/08/18/speaking-at-strata-nyc-making-big-data-small/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m off to my first &lt;a href=&#34;http://strataconf.com/stratany2013/&#34;&gt;Strata&lt;/a&gt; conference, and I&amp;rsquo;m speaking! I&amp;rsquo;ve always wanted to attend Strata. (OSCON too, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t yet made it there.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My session will be about &lt;a href=&#34;http://strataconf.com/stratany2013/public/schedule/detail/31435&#34;&gt;ways to make big data small&lt;/a&gt;, in both the storage and processing dimensions, without losing much of the value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/08/4985831624_fc6cc446c9-300x156.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;4985831624_fc6cc446c9&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;156&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3248&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re familiar with Bloom Filters, this is an example. Bloom Filters let you answer the question,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is value X a member of this data set? Yes, or no?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;by substituting the question,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is value X a member of this data set? Probably yes, or definitely no?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You lose a small and quantifiable amount of precision in the &amp;ldquo;yes,&amp;rdquo; and you gain massive savings in storage and processing cost. Bloom Filters are typically used when you need a definite answer, but only as a pre-filtering step, because if the answer happens to be No, you save the effort of looking through the set to try to find your data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That worldview or philosophy is a valuable thing to keep in your pocket when you&amp;rsquo;re working with large amounts of data, and that&amp;rsquo;s the topic of my Strata Conference / Hadoop World NYC 2013 talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/dwysiu/4985831624/&#34;&gt;(photo credit)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My recipe for more enjoyable presentations</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/02/my-recipe-for-more-enjoyable-presentations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/02/my-recipe-for-more-enjoyable-presentations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since I started making my presentations more beautiful, people have often asked me my secret. It&amp;rsquo;s not a secret, and it&amp;rsquo;s really quite simple to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, realize that it&amp;rsquo;s not about you. It&amp;rsquo;s about your audience. Now, get &lt;em&gt;and read&lt;/em&gt; a few good books on presentations. Your presentations, and your presentation skills, need to be good. You can&amp;rsquo;t just make things beautiful to compensate for badness in other areas. This is something I&amp;rsquo;m always working on. (On the other hand, many a great presenter has doomed him/herself with awful slides.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My list of recommended books includes those from Nancy Duarte, especially &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/slide-ology-Science-Creating-Presentations/dp/0596522347/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Slide:ology&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Resonate-Present-Stories-Transform-Audiences/dp/0470632011/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Resonate&lt;/a&gt;. I have also found &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/TJ-Walkers-Secret-Foolproof-Presentations/dp/1929774885/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;these&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Confessions-Public-Speaker-English/dp/1449301959/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;books&lt;/a&gt; really helpful. Some of these I found in the airport, of all places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, develop great content, and practice it. See the books above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, use a good professionally-designed template. Pay $30 for crying out loud. Are you a graphic designer? No? How much is your time worth? I&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.keynotepro.com/&#34;&gt;bought Keynote templates from Keynote Pro&lt;/a&gt; among other places. I&amp;rsquo;ve also hired people to help build custom slides for important talks, such as keynote addresses at major conferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, and this is the part I enjoy the most: I rarely put text alone on a slide. I&amp;rsquo;ll almost always choose a master that has space for a little text (and I usually try to use only a few words) and an image. I&amp;rsquo;ll emphasize this: use only a couple of words on the slides. The words on the slide should cue you, if necessary, to remember what to talk about. For the audience, they should convey the overall theme &amp;ndash; think of it as hashtags &amp;ndash; of the things you&amp;rsquo;re talking about now. Do not put the full content on the slides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I find an image that seems to fit. My favorite way to do this is a Flickr search for CC-licensed content, sorted by interestingness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Chrome, I use a custom search engine. The keyword is &amp;ldquo;f&amp;rdquo; and the URL pattern is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
    http://www.flickr.com/search/?q=%s&amp;#038;l=cc&amp;#038;ct=0&amp;#038;mt=photos&amp;#038;adv=1&amp;#038;s=int
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try it. Here&amp;rsquo;s a Flickr search for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/search/?q=heart&amp;amp;#038;l=cc&amp;amp;#038;ct=0&amp;amp;#038;mt=photos&amp;amp;#038;adv=1&amp;amp;#038;s=int&#34;&gt;heart&lt;/a&gt;, for example. Isn&amp;rsquo;t that a beautiful page full of images?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if your slides are a boring template, and your talk isn&amp;rsquo;t that great, and your presentation skills aren&amp;rsquo;t that polished, your audience will automatically find your talk much more pleasant now. And it&amp;rsquo;s all about your audience. Remember that!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying Abnormal Behavior in System Metrics</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/06/25/quantifying-abnormal-behavior-in-system-metrics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/06/25/quantifying-abnormal-behavior-in-system-metrics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve posted &lt;a href=&#34;https://vividcortex.comhttp://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/06/25/quantifying-abnormal-behavior/&#34;&gt;slides for my Velocity talk on VividCortex&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt;. The talk explained how we use exponentially weighted moving statistics to generate a meta-metric of abnormality for the time-series metrics measured from MySQL. That&amp;rsquo;s kind of a mouthful. Maybe you had to be there :-)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A great talk on Go concurrency patterns</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/05/24/a-great-talk-on-go-concurrency-patterns/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/05/24/a-great-talk-on-go-concurrency-patterns/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/events/io/sessions/332768653&#34;&gt;35-minute video&lt;/a&gt; from the recent Google I/O conference explains how to use Go&amp;rsquo;s concurrency primitives &amp;ndash; goroutines, channels, and the &lt;code&gt;select&lt;/code&gt; statement &amp;ndash; to do things elegantly, correctly, and safely in a few lines of Go, which would otherwise turn your brain into a pretzel in most programming languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite thing about Go is that a good Go program looks self-evident and obvious, even when it may be doing things that would be insanely complex in another language. Callbacks, closures, mutexes, and so on just disappear, and the program itself emerges, looking completely unimpressive. In many cases I think &amp;ldquo;what&amp;rsquo;s the big deal about that?&amp;rdquo; until I realize how hard it would be to write in Java, or Perl, or so on. A lot of the code in Percona Toolkit, for example, involved &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://bazaar.launchpad.net/~percona-toolkit-dev/percona-toolkit/2.1/view/head:/bin/pt-query-digest#L11835&#34;&gt;pipelines&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; of callbacks passing data along to other callbacks for further processing. These were hard to reason about, hard to make resilient to errors and allow clean termination, and were redesigned several times, never very successfully in my opinion. In Go, channels make those kinds of tasks so simple. Such a program in Go looks suspiciously like a Unix | pipe | and | filter | program. If you think about it, the Unix shell itself is a great example of using &amp;ldquo;channels&amp;rdquo; successfully to trivialize what would otherwise be a migraine-inducing task.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two upcoming Go-related talks I&#39;m giving</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/04/16/two-upcoming-go-related-talks-im-giving/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/04/16/two-upcoming-go-related-talks-im-giving/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m scheduled to talk about Go a couple times in the upcoming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is May 4th in Arlington at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dayoffosterly.com/&#34;&gt;A Day Of Foster.ly&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ll be a participant in a panel titled &lt;em&gt;Add To Your Programming Toolkit: Languages You Should Know About (Erlang, Clojure, R, Go, etc&amp;hellip;)&lt;/em&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m talking about Go, naturally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second May 7th is at my local technology guild, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://neonguild.org/&#34;&gt;Neon Guild&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m going to be giving a &amp;ldquo;gentle introduction&amp;rdquo; to Go. I&amp;rsquo;ve been programming in Go for less than a year, so my first impressions are still fresh. If you are in the Charlottesville area and you haven&amp;rsquo;t been to a Neon Guild meeting, do yourself a favor and show up. It&amp;rsquo;s free and no RSVP is required. Description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems that every time I tell someone we&amp;rsquo;ve chosen Go as our primary language at VividCortex, they respond with something like &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve heard about Go! Neat! What is it like? Why did you choose it? Are you happy with it?&amp;rdquo; The answer is that Go is a fascinating language that&amp;rsquo;s working great for us. After many years of programming in everything from C to Java to C# to Perl to LISP to Shell, I&amp;rsquo;m pretty much in love with Go. There are particular reasons I chose it for our special use case, but beyond just niche considerations, it&amp;rsquo;s working great as a general-purpose, high-performance, very productive systems language. I&amp;rsquo;ll try to contain my enthusiasm and tell a story about evaluating it, learning it, and then learning it more deeply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to see you at one of these events. If you see me, wave and introduce yourself, and give me a business card so I can &lt;s&gt;stalk&lt;/s&gt; connect with you on LinkedIn!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Fault Detection food fight</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/03/12/adaptive-fault-detection-food-fight/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/03/12/adaptive-fault-detection-food-fight/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was a guest on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://foodfightshow.org/2013/03/adaptive-fault-detection.html&#34;&gt;Food Fight Show&lt;/a&gt; last week, along with a bevy of really smart people asking and answering tough questions on fault detection. We didn&amp;rsquo;t talk a lot about MySQL, but given that &lt;a href=&#34;https://vividcortex.com/&#34;&gt;VividCortex&lt;/a&gt; is focusing on MySQL initially, pretty much all of my experience with zero-threshold, zero-configuration fault detection is MySQL-based.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a fun conversation with a lot of insights into the industry, what&amp;rsquo;s wrong with current monitoring tools, and where monitoring is going. Also, it&amp;rsquo;s sold out now, but &lt;a href=&#34;http://monitorama.com/&#34;&gt;Monitorama&lt;/a&gt; is a conference you might be interested in if you&amp;rsquo;re doing monitoring (and who isn&amp;rsquo;t?)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>