<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>About on Xaprb </title>
      <generator uri="https://hugo.spf13.com">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://www.xaprb.com/categories/about/index.xml/</link>
    
    
    
    <updated>Wed, 15 Jan 2014 00:00:00 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Xaprb now uses Hugo</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/01/15/using-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/01/15/using-hugo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve switched this blog from Wordpress to &lt;a href=&#34;http://hugo.spf13.com&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;. If you see any broken links or
other problems, let me know. I&amp;rsquo;ll re-enable comments and other features in the
coming days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why not Wordpress?&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ve used Wordpress since very early days, but I&amp;rsquo;ve had my
fill of security problems, the need to worry about whether a database is up and
available, backups, plugin compatibility problems, upgrades, and performance
issues. In fact, while converting the content from Wordpress to Markdown, I
found a half-dozen pages that had been hacked by some link-farm since around
2007. This wasn&amp;rsquo;t the first such problem I&amp;rsquo;d had; it was merely the only one I
hadn&amp;rsquo;t detected and fixed. And I&amp;rsquo;ve been really diligent with Wordpress
security; I have done things like changing my admin username and customizing my
&lt;code&gt;.htaccess&lt;/code&gt; file to block common attack vectors, in addition to the usual
&amp;ldquo;lockdown&amp;rdquo; measures that one takes with Wordpress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to Wordpress or other CMSes that use a database, static content is
secure, fast, and worry-free. I&amp;rsquo;m particularly happy that my content is all in
Markdown format now. Even if I make another change in the future, the content is
now mostly well-structured and easy to transform as desired. (There are some
pages and articles that didn&amp;rsquo;t convert so well, but I will clean them up later.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why Hugo? There are &lt;a href=&#34;http://staticsitegenerators.net&#34;&gt;lots&lt;/a&gt; of static site generators. Good ones include
Octopress and Jekyll, and I&amp;rsquo;ve used those. However, they come with some of their
own annoyances: dependencies, the need to install Ruby and so on, and
particularly bothersome for this blog, performance issues. Octopress ran my CPU
fan at top speed for about 8 minutes to render this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hugo is written in Go, so it has zero dependencies (a single binary) and is
fast. It renders this blog in a couple of seconds. That&amp;rsquo;s fast enough to run it
in server mode, &lt;code&gt;hugo server -w&lt;/code&gt;, and I can just alt-tab back and forth between
my writing and my browser to preview my changes. By the time I&amp;rsquo;ve tabbed over,
the changes are ready to view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hugo isn&amp;rsquo;t perfect. For example, it lacks a couple of features that are present
in Octopress or Jekyll. But it&amp;rsquo;s more than good enough for my needs, and I
intend to contribute some improvements to it if I get time. I believe it has the
potential to be a leading static site/blog generator going forward. It&amp;rsquo;s already
close to a complete replacement for something like Jekyll.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking for a freelancer</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/10/26/looking-for-a-freelancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/10/26/looking-for-a-freelancer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m looking for a freelancer to convert this WordPress blog into Markdown for use with Octopress. It should be straightforward &amp;ndash; I have already used a plugin to export the data as Markdown. However, a few extra things will need to be taken care of. I have posted this job on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.elance.com/j/convert-wordpress-site-octopress/48229999/&#34;&gt;Elance&lt;/a&gt;. Please submit proposals there!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updated spam controls</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/02/18/updated-spam-controls/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/02/18/updated-spam-controls/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not using my previous combination of Bad Behaviour + WP-Gatekeeper anymore. I&amp;rsquo;ve removed them in favor of ordinary reCAPTCHA. Although it lets a lot of spammers through (almost a thousand spam comments in the day I&amp;rsquo;ve had it enabled) and Bad Behaviour let only 1 or 2 a month through, it became clear that a lot of people were getting blocked wrongly by Bad Behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that I can&amp;rsquo;t practically moderate the spam queue. If you submit a comment and it doesn&amp;rsquo;t get published, you either went into the spam queue that I ignore, or I decided to censor you ;-) Feel free to email me if you think anything&amp;rsquo;s wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Be bold, but not too bold</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/10/08/be-bold-but-not-too-bold/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/10/08/be-bold-but-not-too-bold/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Someone&amp;rsquo;s testing my blog recently, trying by hand to get comments through my spam blockers. They&amp;rsquo;re trying by hand because automated attempts are blocked and the server simply doesn&amp;rsquo;t respond. Hand-submitting spam doesn&amp;rsquo;t scale, so only a few have popped up on my admin screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have fun, I.P. addresses 173.213.212.234 and 219.91.208.244 (remember the Internet isn&amp;rsquo;t anonymous). If you look around this blog you won&amp;rsquo;t notice any spam comments. There&amp;rsquo;s a reason for that &amp;ndash; a combination of reasons, actually. You&amp;rsquo;re unlikely to defeat the measures I&amp;rsquo;ve put in place, unless you try things that most people would consider hacking. And if you do that, be prepared for the consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, if you&amp;rsquo;re actually trying to leave a comment, just do it. All appropriate comments are approved, although sometimes it takes me a few hours to moderate them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The first guest post on Xaprb blog</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/05/03/the-first-guest-post-on-xaprb-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 May 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/05/03/the-first-guest-post-on-xaprb-blog/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I got a really intriguing email today. As you might imagine, I get a lot of email offering to advertise, or trade links, or guest post, etc etc. But this is the most compelling one I&amp;rsquo;ve ever gotten:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came across your blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2009/03/13/50-things-to-know-before-migrating-oracle-to-mysql/&#34;&gt;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2009/03/13/50-things-to-know-before-migrating-oracle-to-mysql/&lt;/a&gt; a few weeks ago as while conducting research for a website that I contribute to. The website aims to look at the progressive areas of early childhood psychology. The idea was originally to create an objective collection of resources for people interested in psychology but it has since grown into something much wider (the resources come together at [redacted]). Today, the project looks at important factors in childhood development that pay dividends in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think a guest blog post that illuminates the the advancement of our understanding of childhood development would be interesting for your audience. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested, I would love to write something for you and perhaps start a friendly dialogue. What do you think?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks, and I look forward to hearing from you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All my best,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sarah Thompson (sarahjthompson5@gmail.com)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing is, I know someone who&amp;rsquo;s been on the Oprah show and written many, many bestselling books on child psychology, so this perked up my ears right away. The more I thought about it, the more I realized that this is an incredible value to my readers. Everyone interested in migrating between database servers ought to know about childhood psychology. I plan to say yes and to start an entire series of blog posts on this and other highly relevant topics, such as the mating behavior of slugs, the history of central Asia, air pressure in a vacuum, and how many disciples Jesus really had. Look forward to the first installment shortly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Xaprb uses a hybrid of Journalist and deLight themes</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2009/03/07/xaprb-uses-a-hybrid-of-journalist-and-delight-themes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2009 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2009/03/07/xaprb-uses-a-hybrid-of-journalist-and-delight-themes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A while ago I switched my theme to Journalist (link at the very bottom of the page) because I thought it was well laid out and solidly designed &amp;ndash; I mean it uses sensible CSS and XHTML etc. The only thing I didn&amp;rsquo;t care for was that it was a little too minimal, if anything. There are lots of themes out there that look gorgeous, but when I tested them they don&amp;rsquo;t render right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I have made a hybrid. Just a few edits to CSS and borrowing a few images from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://webdemar.com/wordpress/wordpress-theme-delight-1-2/&#34;&gt;deLight&lt;/a&gt; theme later, and now I have something that pleases me visually too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the process I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be surprised if I&amp;rsquo;ve broken something for Windows IE users or what have you. But I&amp;rsquo;m sure someone will let me know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For future reference, I&amp;rsquo;m attaching an image of what it looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;attachment_899&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption alignnone&#34; style=&#34;width: 310px&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2009/03/xaprb-delight-journalist-theme.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2009/03/xaprb-delight-journalist-theme-300x185.png&#34; alt=&#34;Theme preview&#34; title=&#34;xaprb-delight-journalist-theme&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;185&#34; class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-899&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;
    Theme preview
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I moved this blog to pairLite with zero downtime, and it was easy</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/05/21/i-moved-this-blog-to-pairlite-with-zero-downtime-and-it-was-easy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2008 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/05/21/i-moved-this-blog-to-pairlite-with-zero-downtime-and-it-was-easy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Did you notice that I moved this blog from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pair.com/&#34;&gt;pair Networks&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pairlite.com/&#34;&gt;pairLite hosting&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably not, unless you check the DNS of xaprb.com regularly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t you hate it when people say &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m moving my blog, I hope there won&amp;rsquo;t be more than a few days of downtime, blah blah&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; Why is this ever necessary, I wonder? I wonder the same thing about a lot of hosting providers &amp;ndash; recently I had a client in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/&#34;&gt;consulting practice&lt;/a&gt; whose (very large, well-known) hosting provider tried to help them with some very simple MySQL work and ended up causing them an obscene amount of downtime, like many many days, and there was no end in sight. As I spoke on the phone with him and asked him about his business, he said &amp;ldquo;we have X thousand users in our beta.&amp;rdquo; long pause. &amp;ldquo;Well, we did anyway.&amp;rdquo; The poor man hadn&amp;rsquo;t slept in I don&amp;rsquo;t know how long. I could only empathize with what it must have felt like to say those words in that mental and physical state. And as I spoke with him I had to tell him, cringing as I said it, that his downtime was completely unnecessary. His host was utterly ignorant of what they were doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this ever happen to someone you know? It&amp;rsquo;s such a shame. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be surprised, really, if this client has a hard time recovering fully from this blow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to demonize hosting providers. They are often great at hosting. But they are not MySQL experts. (Some of them hire Percona to do their MySQL support, and that is good.) If you need expert MySQL help, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/&#34;&gt;hire an expert&lt;/a&gt;. We can also tell you what to watch out for on your shared hosting &amp;ndash; the hosting providers often don&amp;rsquo;t understand the hardware requirements for a database server, and we constantly see simple and really bad avoidable mistakes such as a 32-bit OS on 64-bit hardware or a misconfigured RAID controller. Don&amp;rsquo;t rely on your hosting provider for anything database-related, especially backups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, if you need expert hosting, call an expert hosting provider, not someone who&amp;rsquo;s just reselling. I&amp;rsquo;ve had such good luck with pair Networks (and now pairLite, their budget service) that I write love letters like this blog post constantly. And I recently &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2007/11/23/why-is-embarq-hijacking-my-dns/&#34;&gt;switched away from Embarq for my DSL&lt;/a&gt; provider, to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.briworks.com/&#34;&gt;BRIWorks, a local shop with really friendly, smart people&lt;/a&gt; who charge me more money than Embarq, and yet I love them for it. (By the way, they&amp;rsquo;re not just local; they can help you if you don&amp;rsquo;t live in Charlottesville. If I wasn&amp;rsquo;t already a pairLite customer, I&amp;rsquo;d use them.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My point? With good hosting, and my skills with MySQL and PHP and Apache, I moved with no downtime. OK, it&amp;rsquo;s not hard &amp;ndash; but neither is a non-corrupt MySQL backup that doesn&amp;rsquo;t kill your entire business. If you know what you&amp;rsquo;re doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t know what you&amp;rsquo;re doing, hire someone who does!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I have joined Percona</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/03/26/i-have-joined-percona/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2008 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/03/26/i-have-joined-percona/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Effective April 1, I will join &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.percona.com/&#34;&gt;Percona&lt;/a&gt; full-time as a consultant. I&amp;rsquo;ll be helping people build high-performance applications with MySQL, but I&amp;rsquo;ll also be continuing to develop and improve tools such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.google.com/p/maatkit/&#34;&gt;Maatkit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This career change has been a long time in progress. I&amp;rsquo;m really looking forward to it, but at the same time it&amp;rsquo;s hard to leave my current employer, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rimmkaufman.com/&#34;&gt;The Rimm-Kaufman Group (RKG)&lt;/a&gt;. Working with them has been the best job I&amp;rsquo;ve ever had. But ultimately, my dream job is to help as many people as I can, and consulting will be a better way to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a time like this, I like to reflect on the trail that has led here. It&amp;rsquo;s a good opportunity to realize how fortunate I really am and fill up my gratitude tank. So I&amp;rsquo;d like to thank everyone who has helped me reach this point. All the people who have encouraged me, sponsored me, suggested new options&amp;hellip; all kinds of help. A special thanks to my wife Lynn, to Alan Rimm-Kaufman and all my colleagues at RKG, to the many fine people at MySQL, and to the MySQL community as a whole. My deep gratitude to all of you. I look forward to working with you even more in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Google thinks I might be a nerd</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/01/11/google-thinks-i-might-be-a-nerd/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2008 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/01/11/google-thinks-i-might-be-a-nerd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;m almost insulted! Look at this!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2008/01/erd_nerd.png&#34; alt=&#34;Google image search for ERD&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Legal</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2007/08/07/legal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Aug 2007 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2007/08/07/legal/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Copyright Statement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All material contained at xaprb.com and its subdomains is copyright &amp;copy; the site owner; all rights reserved. Comments submitted, if accepted for publication, become the property of the site owner and are subject to the same license.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Republishing content that does not appear in RSS feeds is not permitted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Terms of Use&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By accessing this website, you are agreeing to these Terms of Use. You access this site entirely at your own risk. The material provided here is made available on an as-is basis. The site owner explicitly disclaims any warranty, express or implied, about the information provided on this site or any site which links to this site. Under no circumstances shall the site owner be liable in any manner for any harm arising from accessing or using in any manner any material on this site or sites which link to this site. The site owner may at any time revise these Terms of Use by updating this posting. By using this site, you agree to be bound by the most current text of this posting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Privacy Policy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site owner does not make any personally identifiable information available to any other entity, except as required by law.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I&#39;ve been doing lately</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2007/07/10/what-ive-been-doing-lately/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2007 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2007/07/10/what-ive-been-doing-lately/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t been blogging about the things I used to &amp;ndash; how-tos and technical hacks &amp;ndash; because I&amp;rsquo;ve been working quite hard on &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.google.com/p/maatkit/&#34;&gt;MySQL Toolkit&lt;/a&gt; and, believe it or not, &lt;a href=&#34;http://code.google.com/p/innotop/projects/innotop/&#34;&gt;innotop&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve made it possible to write innotop plugins, which have been very useful to our team at work, and I&amp;rsquo;m working on documentation. Plugins won&amp;rsquo;t make it into the upcoming release; it&amp;rsquo;ll just be bug fixes and documentation. These projects have taken up most of my free time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve also tentatively joined a group of people working on a very large, exciting, secret project which may consume the rest of my summer and/or much of the rest of the year. (I&amp;rsquo;ve been turning down consulting gigs and other projects because of this). If this secret project works out, I&amp;rsquo;ll be writing more about it here, you can count on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I&amp;rsquo;m still planning to finish some of the work I&amp;rsquo;ve started on MySQL Table Sync, which I continue to need because of a replication bug I haven&amp;rsquo;t been able to isolate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someday, maybe even soon, I might finish some of my 60+ drafts, such as &amp;ldquo;how to implement event listeners and notification in MySQL.&amp;rdquo; But I think the other projects I&amp;rsquo;m working on are much more important and beneficial to many more people, so I have prioritized them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a slight glitch with my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/donate/&#34;&gt;Amazon wishlist&lt;/a&gt;. I was on vacation and when I came back, I saw about half a dozen things purchased from it, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t received any of them (thank you, whoever you are!). I didn&amp;rsquo;t really understand how the wish list worked, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t know I needed to specify a shipping address. I assumed Amazon would send them to my primary shipping address. Well, apparently that didn&amp;rsquo;t work, and in the meantime I also realized Amazon was sending mail somewhere I couldn&amp;rsquo;t receive it, so I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what is really going on. I&amp;rsquo;ve specified an address now, and I&amp;rsquo;m hoping that takes care of it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Support</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2006/10/11/donate/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2006 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2006/10/11/donate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spend many hundreds of hours writing tools and articles. If you want to say thanks, why not &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/registry/registry.html?id=LOE4ZUTKFU39&#34;&gt;send me something from my Amazon.com wishlist?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also send money to my PayPal account if you wish. It&amp;rsquo;s baron at [thisdomain].com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Come work with me!</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2006/07/03/come-work-with-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2006 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2006/07/03/come-work-with-me/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My current employer needs great coders. If you&amp;rsquo;re the type of person who reads my articles regularly, I want you on the team! &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/work-with-me/&#34;&gt;Come work with me&lt;/a&gt;! I&amp;rsquo;ve put up a page describing what we&amp;rsquo;re looking for. I&amp;rsquo;ll keep it current as our needs change.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Xaprb is featured on 9rules</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2006/05/28/xaprb-is-featured-on-9rules/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2006 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2006/05/28/xaprb-is-featured-on-9rules/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://9rules.com&#34;&gt;9rules network&lt;/a&gt;, a trusted filter that chooses the best content on the web, has &lt;a href=&#34;http://9rules.com/en/browse/featured/archive/94/&#34;&gt;named Xaprb as a featured blog&lt;/a&gt;. This means a lot to me. 9rules is a great place to go and find quality content on an Internet that&amp;rsquo;s drowning in garbage, so being featured there is no small matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a good time for to make a plug for 9rules, too. One great way to stay up-to-date on the best of the web is browse the &lt;a href=&#34;http://9rules.com/en/browse/&#34;&gt;communities&lt;/a&gt; and find one that has interesting content, then subscribe to the aggregated feed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re not yet &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/index.xml&#34;&gt;subscribed to Xaprb&amp;rsquo;s content via feeds or email&lt;/a&gt;, give that a try too :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, thanks for the very kind words, &lt;a href=&#34;http://warpspire.com/&#34;&gt;Kyle&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Subscribe</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2006/05/24/subscribe/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 May 2006 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2006/05/24/subscribe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I syndicate my articles via RSS feeds and emails.  Subscribing to syndication channels is the most convenient way to keep up with my latest articles.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>