<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Commentary on Xaprb </title>
      <generator uri="https://hugo.spf13.com">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://www.xaprb.com/categories/commentary/index.xml/</link>
    
    
    
    <updated>Sun, 23 Feb 2014 00:00:00 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Respectful Introductions and Recommendations</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/02/23/respectful-introductions-recommendations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/02/23/respectful-introductions-recommendations/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In the last few years of my career, I&amp;rsquo;ve increasingly been involved in meeting
people. This often involves requests or offers for recommendations,
introductions, and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve learned to be very careful about making or accepting such offers or
requests, and I&amp;rsquo;d like to share my current thoughts about that with you, because
a lot of trouble can come of a seemingly innocent request or offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2014/02/elephant.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Elephant&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;The Stakes Are High&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Martha, that&amp;rsquo;s so great that you are starting a business in the diabetes care
industry! You should really meet my friend Jack. He could be extremely helpful
to you, and I am sure he would appreciate knowing about your startup.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does that sound so dangerous? Believe me, it is. A lot is on the line for you,
Martha, and Jack. Consider:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How well do you know Martha? What if you&amp;rsquo;re wrong about her business? If you
introduce her to Jack, things might go wrong. They could turn out to be
competitors. Or perhaps Martha is doing something that Jack thinks is
unethical or is the wrong way to treat diabetes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How well do you know Jack? Is he really going to be helpful to Martha? Does he
want to be? Does he have time to spend with her?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Factors such as these mean that you are putting your relationship with Jack at
risk. You may wear out your welcome and Jack may not want to be your friend
anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are also risking your relationship with Martha. It sounds like this is a new
relationship, so you&amp;rsquo;re on tenuous ground here; the risk of a misstep is high.
If it&amp;rsquo;s more established, then you may be at lower risk, but the damage to you is
potentially higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are, finally, putting Martha and Jack at risk in various ways. You&amp;rsquo;re
imposing on Jack&amp;rsquo;s time and potentially risking his reputation, and ditto for
Martha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A seemingly innocent offer to help is actually writing a metaphorical check
against the Relationship Banking Account you have with Martha and Jack, and
asking them to extend credit to each other as well. Since they don&amp;rsquo;t have a
Relationship Bank Account with each other, the credit they&amp;rsquo;ll extend to each
other comes out of &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; accounts with them. If it&amp;rsquo;s not a productive match,
then that withdrawal becomes a bounced check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experiences over the last year or so, in particular, I&amp;rsquo;ve been introduced
to a lot of people with management experience, a desire to find companies to
invest in, and so on. Most of the time, courtesy obliges me to have a phone call
or meet them for a meal or similar. Very few of these meetings have been truly
helpful to either of us. I&amp;rsquo;m not saying anyone wasted my time, but I&amp;rsquo;ve ended up
talking to dozens of people and the only outcomes have been pleasant
conversations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Offering Versus Asking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above scenario is when you &lt;em&gt;offer&lt;/em&gt; a favor. You can see how much is at risk
in that scenario.  Consider how much more is at risk when you &lt;em&gt;ask&lt;/em&gt; for a favor,
such as an introduction. You are asking your friend to broker a meeting with
someone from whom you presumably &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; want to ask some favor. &amp;ldquo;Do me a favor,
would you, and ask your friend to do you a favor so I can ask him to do me a
favor?&amp;rdquo; It should be obvious how much credit you&amp;rsquo;re asking everyone to extend
everyone else. You need to treat this with great care, because again if things
don&amp;rsquo;t work out, you are not the only one who can get hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, if you&amp;rsquo;re the one who&amp;rsquo;s being asked for an introduction, consider the
consequences. If I said yes every time someone asked me to introduce them to a
friend of mine, soon I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have any friends. I need to know all of the
people well and be pretty certain that there will be a positive outcome for all
of them and myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This often means that I might need to check with my friend and see if they&amp;rsquo;d
like to meet. Or, instead of putting them in touch with each other directly, I
might just send the asker&amp;rsquo;s contact information on with a brief note. Or if I
don&amp;rsquo;t have enough relationship built up with the person who&amp;rsquo;s asking the favor,
I might need to explain that to them. This is certainly a more positive way to
build my relationship with them in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, you need to have &lt;em&gt;earned&lt;/em&gt; the favor with the person from whom you&amp;rsquo;re
asking it. Otherwise you risk ending up with a negative balance in your
Relationship Bank Account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2014/02/boardroom.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Boardroom&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I&amp;rsquo;m going to share a few examples of when things have gone wrong, as sort of case
studies. These are all real stories, and names have been slightly abbreviated
although sometimes the parties don&amp;rsquo;t deserve protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;The Pushy Investor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is true that &amp;ldquo;ask and you shall receive.&amp;rdquo; If you don&amp;rsquo;t ask, nothing happens.
But if all you do is ask, you end up &lt;em&gt;persona non grata&lt;/em&gt; pretty fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013 Kyle (my co-founder) and I were fundraising from venture capitalists. A
particular investor, Max G, listened to our pitch and said he&amp;rsquo;d like to follow
up on it by calling our advisors, one of whom is at a large company. The next
thing we heard was this email from the advisor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Phone call just ended. I think he was more interested in figuring out what
technologies my employer is interested in which wasn&amp;rsquo;t the purpose for the call.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That never went any further as far as fundraising/investment went, but not too
long after that I got an email from Max G:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subject: Quick Ask&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baron,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of our fastest growing software companies is looking for a VP for
training/educational services. Who are the rock stars in the open source world
that you can recommend? Are you at liberty to tell me who the best from [&amp;hellip;]
is? I can keep my source confidential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Translation: he&amp;rsquo;s asking me to help him poach from someone I respect highly.
Unfortunately, &lt;strong&gt;I did not think of it that way at the time.&lt;/strong&gt; My first thought
was that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/03/12/playing-matchmaker-for-job-seekers-and-recruiters/&#34;&gt;I could help a friend get a dream job&lt;/a&gt;, which is something I have
done several times in the past. So I responded. Not in a way that I feel badly
about now, but still, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t do it again. (How much would you bet that he
wrote an email that started out, &amp;ldquo;Baron said that you and I should talk&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; ?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radio silence for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, another email from Max G:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subject: Company you should look at&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[investor] and [name-drop] recently backed a high-profile entrepreneur
who most recently [&amp;hellip;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is super early (pre-product), but we’re eager to connect with some of the
best people in demand gen to run the concept by. [&amp;hellip;]’s name came up at
[&amp;hellip;]. Could you run this by [&amp;hellip;] to see if he’s open for an intro? Would
love to make the connection with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never replied. Max G already had a negative account balance with me and I
never should have let it get that far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moral of this story is to be careful when someone asks you for a favor, lest you
end up granting it and then wishing you hadn&amp;rsquo;t, as I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;The Veiled Sales Request&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got a connection request on LinkedIn from someone named Paul S, whose request
said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are a startup having developed a reactive programming based backend
service [database-specific details followed].
We are interested in your feedback on this and some new products we
are working on. Can we please set up a time on Webex for next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have often enjoyed giving feedback on products and their marketing position,
both to companies developing the products, friends trying to figure out what
products they need, investors doing diligence, etc. This sounded almost like
that, but something made an alarm bell go off. I responded:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you be more specific what kind of feedback you&amp;rsquo;re looking for? My
expertise is fairly narrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reply from Paul S:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our target market is database developer and architects and from your profile
it looks like you have lots of experience there. We are keen to get your
feedback on the usability of our product for these audience and the language
we ought to use to reach them. Also we are working on a new product and keen
to get your feedback on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope that helps and you can spare 30-45 minutes and see what we can show you and
give us some feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guy didn&amp;rsquo;t even have the decency to comply with my request and be honest
that he was going to give me a sales pitch. I disconnected from him on LinkedIn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_4&#34;&gt;The Shotgun Blast&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone named Nick emailed me this through LinkedIn:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could we please talk tomorrow, We started [&amp;hellip;] in EMEA and I would
 appreciate a call?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing is, the company he mentioned is someone I have a long and good
relationship with. So even though this request was out of the blue, there was no
context or reason why I&amp;rsquo;d want to comply, I had no idea what he wanted, etc I
was reluctant to just mark it as spam. If I ignored him, I would potentially be
offering some offense or lack of grace to that company and my relationships
there, however slight, even if nobody could really blame me for declining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I opted to write back:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy to talk, but I&amp;rsquo;d like to know the topic first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick responded that he was just looking to get to know me, and later in his
message mentioned that he is looking around for a job in management and sales.
I replied that we are too early for that. But I&amp;rsquo;d never hire someone with such
poor communications skills for a job like that anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_5&#34;&gt;The Request To Promote To My Friends&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We use a company called Intercom to embed a contact widget in our app. I haven&amp;rsquo;t
really been all that thrilled with the product; it&amp;rsquo;s not bad, but it&amp;rsquo;s not
amazing. This is relevant, because while I was asking them to fix bugs for me,
they implemented a new feature instead:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2014/02/intercom-asking-for-recommendation.png&#34; alt=&#34;Intercom&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intercom definitely had not earned my recommendation. What was more irritating,
and continues to be, is that &lt;em&gt;the feature itself is buggy&lt;/em&gt;. I had to email them
and ask how to disable it, because it kept showing on every page load. After
following their instructions, it continues to reappear every now and then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are being very foolish by continuing to show me this request. It&amp;rsquo;s pushed
me more towards the point of leaving them and going to a competitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moral of this story is that you had better earn the recommendation you ask
for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_6&#34;&gt;Requests For My Address Book&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, I was looking to add my existing network to my LinkedIn
account. I thought, sure, I&amp;rsquo;ll give them my Gmail login, why not? I&amp;rsquo;ll just
revoke it and change my password right afterwards. No harm there, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I learned what they did with that: &lt;a href=&#34;http://gigaom.com/2013/09/21/linkedin-is-breaking-into-user-emails-spamming-contacts-lawsuit/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn is &amp;ldquo;breaking into&amp;rdquo; user
emails, spamming contacts – lawsuit&lt;/a&gt;. And even after I deleted all of the
imported contacts from my account, I know they still have them, because they
continue to show me &amp;ldquo;connection recommendations&amp;rdquo; for people who don&amp;rsquo;t have
LinkedIn accounts and whose names and emails are distinctively the same as the
information from my address book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will never again do something like this. I will never again install a LinkedIn
app on my phone (because it requires access to my contact list). I do not trust
LinkedIn. It is a vital tool for my professional work and career, but still,
I&amp;rsquo;ve come close to deleting my account out of disgust and anger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I similarly distrust many other services that have anything to gain from getting
access to my contact list, and that keeps me from installing a lot of their apps
on my phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moral of the story: yuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_7&#34;&gt;The Favor Followed By An Awkward Moment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll end with a story where I was in the wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Kyle and I were fundraising I asked someone who had been very helpful to
me in the past for introductions to a couple of top-tier investors. This person
knows my work very well and has great stature in the industry. He could make a
strong representation that we were interesting to investors.  His introductions
were very helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later I hired one of his employees &amp;ndash; someone who lived practically next door to
me, whose wife had a close relationship with my wife.  The last thing I wanted
to do was burn any bridges for him; what if he got a better counter-offer, or
decided at the last minute not to join? So although I normally would have said
something to his boss at some safe point, I opted to stay completely out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then got an email from his boss, to the effect of, &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t mind that you
hired my employee.  But after all I&amp;rsquo;ve done to help you, I think I deserved the
courtesy to hear about it from you first.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was right, and I learned a valuable lesson from that. This was a delicate
situation, but I should have gotten advice on it. In hindsight I wish I&amp;rsquo;d waited
for the all-clear from the new employee and given this person a call as soon as
the new employee said it was OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moral? Well&amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;m still sad about this one. The moral is sometimes you can&amp;rsquo;t
put Humpty Dumpty back together again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_8&#34;&gt;Photo Credits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/adriensifre/8006712599/&#34;&gt;http://www.flickr.com/photos/adriensifre/8006712599/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/ericphoto2/8865468071/&#34;&gt;http://www.flickr.com/photos/ericphoto2/8865468071/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early-access books: a double-edged sword</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/12/26/early-access-books-a-double-edged-sword/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/12/26/early-access-books-a-double-edged-sword/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many technical publishers offer some kind of &amp;ldquo;early access&amp;rdquo; to unfinished versions of books. Manning has &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.manning.com/about/meap.html&#34;&gt;MEAP&lt;/a&gt;, for example, and there&amp;rsquo;s even &lt;a href=&#34;https://leanpub.com/&#34;&gt;LeanPub&lt;/a&gt; which is centered on this idea. I&amp;rsquo;m not a fan of buying these, in most circumstances. Why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many authors never finish their books. A prominent example: Nathan Marz&amp;rsquo;s book on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.manning.com/marz/&#34;&gt;Big Data&lt;/a&gt; was supposed to be published in 2012; the date has been pushed back to March 2014 now. At least a few of my friends have told me their feelings about paying for this book and &amp;ldquo;never&amp;rdquo; getting it. I&amp;rsquo;m not blaming Marz, and I don&amp;rsquo;t want this to be about authors. I&amp;rsquo;m just saying many books are never finished (and as an author, I know why!), and readers get irritated about this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the book is unfinished, it&amp;rsquo;s often of much less value. The whole is greater than the sum of the parts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the book is finished, you have to re-read it, which is a lot of wasted work, and figuring out what&amp;rsquo;s changed from versions you&amp;rsquo;ve already read is a big exercise too. To some extent, editions create a similar problem&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.manning.com/about/meap.html&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;. I think that successive editions of books are less likely to be bought and really read, unless there&amp;rsquo;s a clear signal that both the subject and the book have changed greatly. Unfortunately, most technical books are outdated before they&amp;rsquo;re even in print. Editions are a necessary evil to keep up with the changes in industry and practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that O&amp;rsquo;Reilly has tried to figure out how to address this, too, and I sent an email to my editor along the lines of this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know this is a very one-sided opinion. I had a lengthy email exchange with LeanPub, for example. I know they, and a lot of others including likely readers of this blog, see things very differently than I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, I don&amp;rsquo;t think anyone has a great solution to the combination of problems created by static books written about a changing world. But early-access to unfinished books has always seemed to me like compounding the problems, not resolving them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.manning.com/about/meap.html&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Rant: The classic counter-example for editions is math and calculus textbooks, which can charitably be described as a boondoggle. Calculus hasn&amp;rsquo;t changed much for generations, either in theory or practice. Yet new editions of two leading textbooks are churned out every couple of years. They offer slightly prettier graphics or newer instructions for a newer edition of the TI-something calculator &amp;ndash; cosmetic differences. But mostly, they offer new homework sets, so students can&amp;rsquo;t buy and use the older editions, nor can they resell them for more than a small fraction of the purchase price. Oh, and because the homework is always changing, bugs in the homework problems are ever-present. It&amp;rsquo;s a complete ripoff. Fortunately, technical writers generally behave better than this. OK, rant over.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Napkin math: How much waste does Celestial Seasonings save?</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/12/22/napkin-math-how-much-waste-does-celestial-seasonings-save/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/12/22/napkin-math-how-much-waste-does-celestial-seasonings-save/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was idly reading the Celestial Seasonings box today while I made tea. Here&amp;rsquo;s the end flap:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/12/tea-bag.png&#34; alt=&#34;tea-bag&#34; width=&#34;424&#34; height=&#34;410&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-3359&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seemed hard to believe that they really save 3.5 million pounds of waste just by not including that extra packaging, so I decided to do some back-of-the-napkin math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much paper is in each package of non-Celestial-Seasonings tea? The little bag is about 2 inches by 2 inches, it&amp;rsquo;s two-sided, and there&amp;rsquo;s a tag, staple, and string. Call it 10 square inches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How heavy is the paper? It feels about the same weight as normal copy paper. Amazon.com lists a box of 5000 sheets of standard letter-sized paper at a shipping weight of 50 pounds (including the cardboard box, but we&amp;rsquo;ll ignore that). Pretend that each sheet (8.5 * 11 inches = 93.5 square inches) is about 100 square inches. That&amp;rsquo;s .0001 pounds per square inch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much tea does Celestial Seasonings sell every year? Wikipedia says their sales in the US are over $100M, and they are a subsidiary of Hain Celestial, which has a lot of other large brands. Hain&amp;rsquo;s sales last year were just under $500M. $100M is a good enough ballpark number. Each box of 20 tea bags sells at about $3.20 on their website, and I think it&amp;rsquo;s cheaper at my grocery store. Call it $3.00 per box, so we&amp;rsquo;ll estimate the volume of tea bags on the high side (to make up for the low-side estimate caused by pretending there&amp;rsquo;s 100 square inches per sheet of paper). That means they sell about 33.3M boxes, or 667M bags, of tea each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they put bags, tags, and strings on all of them, I estimated 10 square inches of paper per bag, so at .0001 pound per square inch that&amp;rsquo;s .001 pound of extra paper and stuff per bag. That means they&amp;rsquo;d use about 667 thousand pounds of paper to bag up all that tea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s quite a difference from the 3.5 million pounds of waste they claim they save. Did I do the math wrong or assume something wrong?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Freeing some Velocity videos</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/11/09/freeing-some-velocity-videos/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/11/09/freeing-some-velocity-videos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Following my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/10/24/should-velocity-videos-be-free/&#34; title=&#34;Should Velocity videos be free?&#34;&gt;previous post on Velocity videos&lt;/a&gt;, I had some private email conversations with good folks at O&amp;rsquo;Reilly, and a really nice in-person exchange with a top-level person as well. I was surprised to hear them encourage me to publish my videos online freely!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still believe that nothing substitutes for the experience of attending an O&amp;rsquo;Reilly conference in-person, but I&amp;rsquo;ll also be the first to admit that my talks are usually more conceptual and academic than practical, and designed to start a conversation rather than to tell you the Truth According To Baron. Thus, I think they&amp;rsquo;re worth sharing more widely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O&amp;rsquo;Reilly alleviated my concerns about &amp;ldquo;killing the golden goose,&amp;rdquo; but I like one person&amp;rsquo;s take on the cost of O&amp;rsquo;Reilly&amp;rsquo;s conferences. &amp;ldquo;You think education is expensive? Try ignorance.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll post some of my past talks soon for your enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Get out of your comfort zone</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/10/25/get-out-of-your-comfort-zone/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/10/25/get-out-of-your-comfort-zone/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the most valuable life skills you can ever develop is to overcome the urge to stay within your comfort zone. If you stay where you&amp;rsquo;re familiar and feel safe, two things might happen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You might find out that it&amp;rsquo;s not safe after all. Bad things can happen where you feel at home just as well as out of the familar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nothing good will happen. You might skate through life without even living it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week at Velocity I responded to an invitation from O&amp;rsquo;Reilly to join a lunch with Per Scholas. I didn&amp;rsquo;t know much about Per Scholas, but I&amp;rsquo;ve learned to say yes to invitations from O&amp;rsquo;Reilly. The night before, I watched an inspiring &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t0qcDwDPQ-Q&#34;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; during Ignite, from the founder of Per Scholas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impressed, I began to really look forward to spending some time with the Per Scholas folks the next day at lunch. The idea was pretty simple: people who were working through the Per Scholas training would pair up one-for-one (as I understand it) with people like myself &amp;ndash; technologists, entrepreneurs, hackers, makers, people with perhaps something to share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sat down at a table in the designated area, leaving lots of room beside me for people to join. None of the Per Scholas students was there yet. I chatted idly with two other people at the table. Soon one of the Per Scholas staff members sat down with us. I asked her a series of questions for ten minutes or so. She explained that she helped people with basic life and work skills, coaching and mentoring even after they leave the intensive study program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still no students had joined us. Suddenly I looked over at another table and saw that it had filled entirely with Per Scholas students, shoulder to shoulder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Basic life skill number 1 is to build your network and learn from unfamiliar people,&amp;rdquo; I remarked to the staffer next to me. &amp;ldquo;They are missing an opportunity to mingle with us.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Yes,&amp;rdquo; she answered. &amp;ldquo;They are.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then you could (metaphorically) hear the crickets chirping. I finished my lunch and left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;rsquo;t brag about myself, but I can say that the other people at that table were damn sure worth getting to know. As for me, I considered it a complete waste of my time; I&amp;rsquo;d chosen it over a conversation I really wanted to attend elsewhere. There&amp;rsquo;s another blog post in here somewhere &amp;ndash; this isn&amp;rsquo;t the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve had this kind of experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Per Scholas students aren&amp;rsquo;t paying anything (financially) for their training. Are they getting what they&amp;rsquo;re paying for? You bet they are. Like all of us, they will get out of it exactly what they put into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get out of your comfort zone. If you don&amp;rsquo;t, the worst thing in the world happens to you: &lt;em&gt;nothing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is soliciting a review commercial or transactional?</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/10/21/is-soliciting-a-review-commercial-or-transactional/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/10/21/is-soliciting-a-review-commercial-or-transactional/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve booked rooms through hotels.com a few times, and they always send me followup emails asking me to rate the stay and so forth. In my view this is commercial/marketing email, not transactional, and I should be able to opt out of it. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to get the emails and I don&amp;rsquo;t want to rate the hotels, in part because I don&amp;rsquo;t believe in the validity of such ratings/reviews (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.forbes.com/sites/cherylsnappconner/2013/05/09/the-dark-side-of-reputation-management-how-it-affects-your-business/&#34;&gt;reference&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.edmunds.com/about/press/edmundscom-reaches-settlement-with-company-accused-of-submitting-fraudulent-car-dealer-ratings-and-reviews.html&#34;&gt;reference&lt;/a&gt;). But there&amp;rsquo;s no unsubscribe link at the bottom of the email, and there&amp;rsquo;s no setting in their website to opt out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I sent them a request:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why can&amp;rsquo;t I opt out of your leave-a-review emails after staying at a hotel? I am sure this is a gray area, but in my mind it&amp;rsquo;s a marketing email, not a transactional email, because it&amp;rsquo;s not required for you to fulfill an order or similar. Please include an unsubscribe link in these emails and please include a setting in the account preferences as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their response:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for contacting Hotels.com Customer Support regarding your request to unsubscribed from the leave-a-review emails after a completed stay.
We are sorry to hear about the inconvenience.
We regret to inform you that we were unable to unsubscribe your email address from guest reviews emails. Please be advised that we are requesting for reviews for us to have a useful source of feedback for a property to gauge performance in key areas such as service, cleanliness, and overall guest satisfaction.
We appreciate your business and we look forward to assisting you in the future.
Arlene T.
Hotels.com Customer Support Specialist&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Hotels.com needs to take an objective look at what they&amp;rsquo;re doing. What&amp;rsquo;s the real outcome of their policy? I believe they&amp;rsquo;re working at odds with their stated intentions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure one could quickly find lots of studies and statistics to show that the reviews they receive will be badly skewed towards the negative &amp;ndash; probably so skewed that any statistician would reject them out of hand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If people don&amp;rsquo;t want to leave reviews, they won&amp;rsquo;t leave reviews, period. No matter how many emails you send them. I can delete the email; I&amp;rsquo;m not forced to act on it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I resent having to delete an email I don&amp;rsquo;t want to get, and emails like this should be optional. It isn&amp;rsquo;t as if allowing an opt-out would decrease the chance of getting feedback. People who like to leave reviews will not opt-out. Anyone who opts out isn&amp;rsquo;t going to leave feedback anyway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re pissing off at least some customers (okay, at least one). Curmudgeonly people like myself are in fact likely to stop using Hotels.com altogether, thus reducing the possible audience from which to get feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really think this topic is common sense, but if common sense is in short supply, perhaps some valuable lessons about how to run a business and how to provide customer support can be gleaned upon deep inspection. I won&amp;rsquo;t even rant about the fake apology and fake appreciation of my business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to reply to them and send the URL of this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More Notebooks and Journals!</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/10/13/more-notebooks-and-journals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/10/13/more-notebooks-and-journals/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Something interesting happened after I published my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/10/ultimate-notebook-and-journal-face-off/&#34; title=&#34;Ultimate notebook and journal face-off&#34;&gt;ultimate notebook and journal face-off&lt;/a&gt; blog post a couple of months ago. I received an email from a company called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grandluxe.com/online-store.html&#34;&gt;Grandluxe&lt;/a&gt;, asking if I&amp;rsquo;d like to receive some stationery products in hopes that if I liked them, I&amp;rsquo;d write a review on them. I had never heard of them before, but they&amp;rsquo;ve been making paper products for 68 years, and apparently are trying to break out of the Asian market into international territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agreed, and they sent me quite a large box of notebooks. They also sent me their full product line catalog. So you could say that, as a notebook nerd, I&amp;rsquo;m in heaven!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like the products. (I&amp;rsquo;ve already disclosed my bias. But I&amp;rsquo;ll do it again. I was given these free of charge.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Monologue Ruled Notebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They sent me an entire set of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grandluxe.com/index.php/online-store/monologue-ruled-note-book-a5.html&#34;&gt;Monologue&lt;/a&gt; ruled notebook in A5 size, assorted attractive colors. It is very similar to a Moleskine-class notebook. It has a slightly softer and more &amp;ldquo;grippy&amp;rdquo; cover, but otherwise there&amp;rsquo;s little difference. I had enough to give one to my wife, to each of my coworkers, and keep the prettiest color for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/10/ruled-note-book.png&#34; alt=&#34;ruled-note-book&#34; width=&#34;587&#34; height=&#34;279&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-3277&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Mythology Notebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I received three small (A6) and one A5 in this product line. The paper is a little smoother and the edges are gilded in gold and silver colors. The covers are charcoal black with silvery/goldish undertones. They are hard and stiff, not soft and flexible like the Monologue, and have a knurled or bumpy feel. The spine is embossed with the product name in gilding to match the edge of the sheets. The A5 has a pseudo-reptile-skin pattern on the binding. These would make a great gift or promotional item, because they look really sophisticated. Note that the colors in the image below are a little exaggerated; in reality the gold/silver tones are more subtle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/10/mythology.png&#34; alt=&#34;mythology&#34; width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;425&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-3278&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This item doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to be available on their online store yet, but you can find more details and images &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grandluxe.com/notebooks-journals.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Monolette Notebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a slim notebook with a flexible cover (thick paper, not rigid at all) that comes in combination packs. Each pack has one ruled notebook and one blank notebook with perforated pages for easy tear-out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/10/monolette.png&#34; alt=&#34;monolette&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; height=&#34;600&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-3279&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This item doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to be available on their online store yet, but you can find more details and images &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grandluxe.com/notebooks-journals.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;Bullet Journaling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently stumbled on an interesting system of journaling / note-taking called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bulletjournal.com/&#34;&gt;Bullet Journal&lt;/a&gt;. Although it&amp;rsquo;s a little bit over-the-top in some ways, and sometimes feels like being told the obvious or told to follow a system that seems unlikely to hold together in the &amp;ldquo;real world,&amp;rdquo; it is fun to see that other people enjoy taking notes on paper as much as I do. Worth a read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bulletjournal.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/10/bullet-journal-300x106.png&#34; alt=&#34;bullet-journal&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;106&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3281&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_4&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an embarrassment of riches to choose from when it comes to journals and notebooks, and my bookshelf is stockpiled with a couple of years&amp;rsquo; worth now that I&amp;rsquo;ve done this epic series. But in today&amp;rsquo;s digital world, can you ever get too much of good old paper and pen? Enjoy the simpler pleasures&amp;hellip; I hope this blog has helped with that a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using encryption? You&#39;re suspicious</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/08/01/using-encryption-youre-suspicious/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/08/01/using-encryption-youre-suspicious/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday more details on the NSA&amp;rsquo;s secret and illegal monitoring activities were &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/jul/31/nsa-top-secret-program-online-data&#34;&gt;revealed&lt;/a&gt;. (Yes, the NSA revealed some things themselves, but as far as I can tell, that was only a conciliatory effort and didn&amp;rsquo;t actually reveal more details &amp;ndash; just more talk.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember my recent series of blog posts, where I claimed that privacy in today&amp;rsquo;s world is impossible without &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/05/without-free-software-and-hardware-privacy-is-impossible/&#34; title=&#34;Without free software and hardware, privacy is impossible&#34;&gt;trustworthy hardware/software&lt;/a&gt;, privacy is impossible unless it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/06/privacy-is-impossible-unless-its-the-default/&#34; title=&#34;Privacy is impossible unless it’s the default&#34;&gt;default&lt;/a&gt;, and privacy is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/17/email-snooping-is-a-small-fraction-of-the-story/&#34; title=&#34;Email snooping is a small fraction of the story&#34;&gt;essentially unachievable&lt;/a&gt; because of the scope of the problem, and the way we&amp;rsquo;ve built our society and technologies?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also said that those who use privacy, which is non-default, are making themselves targets for surveillance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you and I use this technology right now to encrypt our communications, we’ll actually make ourselves more interesting targets. That’s partially because we’d be among the few people doing so. Have you ever noticed that nothing draws attention like whispering in a public place? I don’t know what proportion of ordinary email between everyday people is encrypted, but if pressed, I’d guess it’s fewer than one email in 50,000.** That’s an extraordinarily strong signal to authorities looking for needles in the haystack of Internet activity**. I wouldn’t be surprised if the NSA has large-scale brute-force encryption-cracking clusters dedicated to forcibly decrypting the few encrypted emails that wend their way around the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, yet another &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/world/interactive/2013/jul/31/nsa-xkeyscore-program-full-presentation&#34;&gt;ugly NSA slideshow&lt;/a&gt; was made public. Take a look at slide 15:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/08/nsa-finding-targets.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/08/nsa-finding-targets-300x219.png&#34; alt=&#34;nsa-finding-targets&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;219&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3242&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the following slides, too: they discuss decrypting people&amp;rsquo;s encrypted activities to inspect. Refer to the closing sentence of my quoted paragraph above. Read the full article, linked at the top of this blog post. The amount and specificity of surveillance being performed is stunning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Am I psychic? No, this stuff is pretty obvious. As I said previously, it&amp;rsquo;s inevitable. Nothing is going to stop these agencies from doing this stuff. If it&amp;rsquo;s resisted strongly enough, they&amp;rsquo;ll just knuckle down and do it more and more secretly. They won&amp;rsquo;t stop doing it; they will just try to stop being caught in the act.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Email snooping is a small fraction of the story</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/17/email-snooping-is-a-small-fraction-of-the-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/17/email-snooping-is-a-small-fraction-of-the-story/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I wrote previously about why privacy and security &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/05/without-free-software-and-hardware-privacy-is-impossible/&#34; title=&#34;Without free software and hardware, privacy is impossible&#34;&gt;require open-source, inspectable hardware and software&lt;/a&gt; to run on, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/06/privacy-is-impossible-unless-its-the-default/&#34; title=&#34;Privacy is impossible unless it’s the default&#34;&gt;software that makes encryption the default&lt;/a&gt; so everyone uses it. My example application was email, and I concluded that it&amp;rsquo;s currently impractical to think that we can block government snooping on a large scale even in the domain of email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, think what a small fraction of people&amp;rsquo;s Internet-connected activities we&amp;rsquo;re talking about: email. What about web browsing, social network use, chat clients, game playing, phone use, GPS use, credit card transactions, search engine activity, smartphone apps, online video streaming, television viewing, car driving, access to personal devices such as security systems and webcams, cable TV use, and on and on? How can all of this be made secure and intrusion-proof? And make no mistake, all of this data is intensely personal, private, and meaningful. Email is a tiny part of the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And day by day, our lives are becoming ever more electronic, ever more connected, and thus ever more trackable. Wearable computing and RFID chips are going to be reality for normal citizens in the next decade or less. In twenty years many people will probably have Internet-connected, GPS-enabled, RFID-broadcasting devices physically implanted in their bodies. (The rest of us already carry these in our pockets every day). This is not sci-fi, it&amp;rsquo;s the quite predictable and ordinary extension of current trends and developments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not to say that this is evil. All of these things have good and wholesome uses, and will become available for good reasons &amp;ndash; medical, business, convenience, entertainment, and so on. They&amp;rsquo;ll enhance us and our lives greatly. But their potential for abuse, and thus the virtual certainty that they will be abused, is stunning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as I&amp;rsquo;ve pointed out in my previous posts, it&amp;rsquo;s practically impossible to prevent such abuse, even for the mundane technologies such as email. Any workably-secure technology that I currently know of is unsuitable for mass use, and thus won&amp;rsquo;t be used. All of these devices and technologies will, in their convenience, expose us to intrusion on a scale I&amp;rsquo;m not sure I can imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put it this way: have you heard of bitcoin? It&amp;rsquo;s a radical departure from traditional currencies. Now imagine that &lt;em&gt;every kind of electronic activity you engage in needs to be similarly radically invented if there&amp;rsquo;s any hope of privacy and security.&lt;/em&gt; This might not be an exaggeration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can we do? I think that all devices, technologies, and services need to be designed to be surveillance-proof, but I think the very foundations of our technology platforms, such as the Internet itself and all of the components that make it work, might have to be redesigned. Perhaps there&amp;rsquo;s another way, such as building a secure &amp;ldquo;tunnel&amp;rdquo; or VPN-like environment inside and on top of existing technology. But I&amp;rsquo;m not the expert in such matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone can solve this, it could be a more significant technological advance than all of the technological advances in human history thus far, because rather than just enabling technical innovation, it could enable and guarantee freedom &amp;ndash; both freedom &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; and freedom &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt;. If so, this would truly be a first. However, I believe that freedom is never guaranteed and won universally and permanently; I believe there will always have to be a fight for freedom against those who seek to limit it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime I personally plan to carry on as usual, doing what I can and working to become successful within the system, so that I have more of an opportunity to counteract the potential and actual abuses. Because that&amp;rsquo;s what it seems to come down to: stopping governments from monitoring and thus (as I said previously) partially controlling us seems to be impossible or impractical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want to end on a positive note. I don&amp;rsquo;t worry about these things; I don&amp;rsquo;t make myself unhappy about them. And I hope you don&amp;rsquo;t, either. The future is &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; uncertain. If it&amp;rsquo;s not the race between technological good and evil, it&amp;rsquo;s something else. This is simply another challenge to be met with a clear, present, joyful head and heart.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ultimate notebook and journal face-off</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/10/ultimate-notebook-and-journal-face-off/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/10/ultimate-notebook-and-journal-face-off/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re like me, you spend so much time typing on a computer that a good notebook or journal is one of life&amp;rsquo;s finer pleasures. I&amp;rsquo;ve kept a diary of my personal life for close to 30 years now, and I have a shelf full of journals. I&amp;rsquo;ve found a great many that I enjoy writing in, and choosing a different one each time is part of the fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But thus far, my quest for a notepad has been unsatisfying. Many notepads have loved me, but I&amp;rsquo;m sorry to say their love has been unrequited. I&amp;rsquo;ve tried all the usual things: Moleskine, loose-leaf paper, binders, what have you. But I never found something that is practical, functional, a joy to write on, and a pleasure to look at and hold. I just can&amp;rsquo;t settle into a long-term relationship with my notebook, because I haven&amp;rsquo;t met The Right One yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, naturally, I decided to stage a giant contest amongst all the premium notebooks I could find by reading online reviews, searching the Internet, and visiting my local retailers. Read on, but I warn you, I&amp;rsquo;ve spent hundreds of dollars amassing a collection, and I&amp;rsquo;m not going to waste all that on a short blog post. And yes, there will be a winner at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/notepads.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/notepads-300x231.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;notepads&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;231&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3212&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I review any of the notebooks, let me explain what I&amp;rsquo;m looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;The Perfect Notebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My quest for the Holy Grail of notebooks began innocently enough when I happened to read that &lt;a href=&#34;http://katemats.com/&#34;&gt;Kate Matsudaira&lt;/a&gt; is a notebook connoisseur and will only write on Semikolon Il Creativo notebooks with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B004IMAQTG/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Uchida Le Pen pens&lt;/a&gt;. Intrigued, I included one of each in my next batch of &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo; from Amazon.com. I immediately fell in love with the pens, but the notebook was much larger than I expected it to be &amp;ndash; far too large to be practical as I travel and carry it hither and yon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what do I want?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The size. It needs to be large enough to write on easily, leaving readable margins, without wasting a high percentage of the paper. It needs to be small enough to slip into a bag or hold in a hand with several other things; it should be neither bulky nor so small that it gets lost and slides to the bottom and gets all crumpled by other things.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The proportions. Too tall and skinny is bad; too short and wide is bad. Something fairly standard is best, like the usual A* paper proportions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The thickness and number of pages. Enough to last a while. Not so many that it&amp;rsquo;s heavy or bulky in a messenger bag; not so many that if I lose it, a giant chunk of my life and professional notes is gone. There&amp;rsquo;s always some risk, but it needs to be balanced.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The type of cover. Rigid, thick covers waste space and add weight, as well as being difficult to pack in a carry-on bag. Something springy and thin, but substantial enough to help with writing, is best.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The binding. I write on both sides of the paper, and it needs to fold open easily and flat, be very durable, and not force me to write awkwardly when I&amp;rsquo;m writing in the center margin of the left-hand page. It should also not curl awkwardly when I&amp;rsquo;m near the first or the last page.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The closure. I&amp;rsquo;m not a big fan of elastic closures; they get in the way more than they help.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The paper quality. As I said, I write on both sides. It needs to resist bleed-through and be smooth and strong.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ruling. I like ruled notebooks, but can do all right with blank. If there&amp;rsquo;s ruling, it needs to be pretty narrow. Nothing wastes more paper and annoys me more than too-wide ruling. Any ruling also shouldn&amp;rsquo;t force or encourage me to leave too much of a margin.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The index, table of contents, helper charts, page numbers, and so on. Some of these things are wonderful in moderation; a table of contents and page numbers, for example, are a delight. I can quickly index a notebook after using it, and it becomes immensely more useful for reference. Do I need 12 pages of conversion tables and timezone maps? Not really.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The bookmarks or page markers. I prefer a silken ribbon for journals, but for notebooks I actually prefer none; my favorite is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1593593422/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;these magnetic owl page markers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The design. This is the most subjective and intangible thing of all. The design needs to be professional, a little bit creative, and inspiring. It should make me feel like an artist as well as an engineer. If I may stereotype for a moment, the Germans perhaps err on the side of being too mechanical, the Swiss can sometimes feel as if everything is meant to be a coffee-table conversation piece, and the Americans can be deathly boring. I want something that makes me feel light and nimble, practical, yet &amp;hellip; a craftsman, somehow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is that really so much to ask?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;The Categories&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After assessing a number of books, including some extras provided by my wonderful and resourceful wife, I&amp;rsquo;ve realized there are really three categories. Regardless of what a notebook or journal is designed for, in my mind it ends up in one of these, even if it&amp;rsquo;s supposed to be something else:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Journals. Journals tend to have a bit larger margins, may offer fold-over magnetic covers or other clasps, and are usually mid-sized. They often have beautiful designs on the covers, but are relatively plain inside. If notebooks were coffee, these would be a latte.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moleskines and imitations. These come in several sizes but generally have elastic loop clasps, minimal features such as a single pocket inside the back cover, and are generally boring and middle-of-the-road in nearly every way. As coffee, these are a cup of Americano at best.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The exceptional notebooks. These vary more widely and have a lot of personality and special features. These are espressos, macchiatos, and cappuccinos.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now, let&amp;rsquo;s get right down to brass tacks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;The Contenders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allow me to repeat the photo from before:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/notepads.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/notepads-300x231.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;notepads&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;231&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3212&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the left, and roughly in order of size, these are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An Italian leatherette journal by Markings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Semikolon Il Creativo, large&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Quo Vadis Habana&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An iPad for size perspective ;-)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A PaperBlanks journal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Peter Pauper Press journal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another PaperBlanks journal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Mead Cambridge notebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A deconstructed journal by Studio Oh!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Whitelines Squared notebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Clairefontaine notebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Barnes &amp;amp; Noble journal refill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Leuchtturm 1917 notebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Moleskine notebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Chameleon Like notebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Semikolon Il Creativo, small&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A (small) Chameleon Like notebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A teNues CoolNotes notebook &lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whew! That&amp;rsquo;s a lot of reviewing to do. I&amp;rsquo;ll go through them [mostly] in order. I&amp;rsquo;ve uploaded hi-resolution photos; click on thumbnails to see the bigger picture. In some cases I&amp;rsquo;ve linked through to Amazon, when a product is available there. Some others I never buy online, or can&amp;rsquo;t find online, although you may be able to find them if you search. You can see more photos of the notebooks there. I&amp;rsquo;ve focused mostly on the inside of the books, but there are good photos online of the exterior too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;Italian leatherette journal by Markings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/markings-italian-leatherette.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/markings-italian-leatherette-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;markings-italian-leatherette&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3214&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a wonderful journal that I&amp;rsquo;m going to enjoy filling up. Though the design is understated, and I tend to like some eye candy on my journals, the cover is supple and has a suede feel, and there are enough pages to be a good journal. (Unlike my notebooks, I like a diary to last a good while.) The paper is smooth and heavy, the ruling and margins are nice, and overall it feels great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a notebook, I can&amp;rsquo;t really use it. It&amp;rsquo;s too large, too thick, and too heavy to carry around. The teacup in the photo is a bit oversized, so it is actually a bit larger than it looks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;192 pages, 10.25 x 7.5 x .75 inches. Rule width: .3125 inches. Bought at Target for $12.99.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_4&#34;&gt;Semikolon Il Creativo, large&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/semikolon-creativo-large.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/semikolon-creativo-large-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;semikolon-creativo-large&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3215&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the notebook that started this whole quest. It&amp;rsquo;s perhaps the most &amp;ldquo;designed&amp;rdquo; of all of them, with an elaborate perpetual calendar on every page in German, French, and English. It also has several pages of table of contents and calendar overview at the front, and sheets of stickers and labels are included. I immediately wanted to label everything in sight. The notebook made me feel like putting my whole life in order, and I knew I&amp;rsquo;d feel great about it if I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main problem is that it&amp;rsquo;s way too big for me to carry around. I want something a lot slimmer, to start with. The cover is nice and flexible, and there are other nice features, but I can&amp;rsquo;t get past the bulk. I also have a gripe with the ruling, which is too wide. I&amp;rsquo;m forced to write way too spaced-out, or to write two lines per rule, which is annoying and cramped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper is a bit coarse, almost ridged, and I am pretty sure that this texture is intentional. It should be great for pencils, but is not as good for the pens that I use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This notebook is designed for notes, but I&amp;rsquo;ll use it as a journal. I wonder if I&amp;rsquo;ll write less about emotional things and dreams, and more about analytical things?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;304 pages, 10 x 7.75 x 1.0 inches. Rule width: .375 inches. Bought at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B005DVEUDO/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; for $14.97.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_5&#34;&gt;Quo Vadis Habana&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/quo-vadis-habana.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/quo-vadis-habana-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;quo-vadis-habana&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3216&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This notebook is a big step down in size and bulk from the previous two. It&amp;rsquo;s a much more practical size to carry around, and it has the best cover of all of them, in my opinion. The cover isn&amp;rsquo;t quite rigid; it&amp;rsquo;s flexible enough not to be annoying and uncomfortable in a thin bag with other things crammed in. The paper is top-notch quality &amp;ndash; silky smooth and creamy. The corners are rounded, which is always appreciated in a notebook. And, the notebook and the paper are made in the USA, from certified sustainable forests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ruling might extend a little too close to the margins, but although the book doesn&amp;rsquo;t open completely flat, it comes very close; close enough that there shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a problem with the margins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, a very nice notebook, and one of the top contenders for certain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;160 pages, 6.375 x 9.625 x .625 inches. Rule width: .222 inches. Bought at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0072WW8K4/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; for $20.99.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_6&#34;&gt;PaperBlanks journal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/paper-blanks.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/paper-blanks-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;paper-blanks&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3217&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are my favorite journals. They have a ribbon marker, a magnetic clasp cover, a huge variety of beautiful cover designs to choose from, and they&amp;rsquo;re easy to find at Barnes &amp;amp; Noble. I&amp;rsquo;ve probably bought over a dozen of these. It&amp;rsquo;s great when there&amp;rsquo;s a sale; I&amp;rsquo;ll buy several at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper isn&amp;rsquo;t quite as nice as I&amp;rsquo;d want in a notebook, but it&amp;rsquo;s great for journaling. It is slightly rough. The journals are plain inside, with no decorations, and a small note on the inside cover about the pattern reproduced on the outside. For example, I&amp;rsquo;m currently writing in the one shown closed, and this cover is inspired by a Persian Safavid-style design from centuries ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t use these for note-taking. They&amp;rsquo;re a little too bulky, the ruling is a little too wide, and the covers are too rigid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;288 pages, 9 x 7 x .875 inches. Rule width: .318 inches. Bought at Barnes &amp;#038; Noble for $18.95.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_7&#34;&gt;Peter Pauper Press journal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/peter-pauper.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/peter-pauper-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;peter-pauper&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3218&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This journal is certainly in the same class as the PaperBlanks journals. It&amp;rsquo;s about the same size, and also has beautiful art on the cover; in this case, a Van Gogh. The paper is a little heavier, and there&amp;rsquo;s no clasp to hold the cover shut. It has slightly fewer pages and is a little thinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;192 pages, 9 x 7.5 x .75 inches. Rule width: .318 inches. Bought at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Almond-Blossom-Journal-Notebook-Diary/dp/144130357X/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; for $13.49.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_8&#34;&gt;Mead Cambridge notebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/mead-cambridge.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/mead-cambridge-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;mead-cambridge&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3219&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This notebook is a great find, in my opinion. It&amp;rsquo;s a good size, is thin and flexible with a semi-rigid cover, has trimmed corners to avoid dog-earing, and has nice paper. It&amp;rsquo;s all business, but is just sophisticated enough to feel good, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen a variant that has an extra column on the right for notes to be set aside. I&amp;rsquo;m going to give this a try because I often find myself going back and cramming cross-references or additional information into the margins. There is a variant without this extra column, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ruling is a nice width &amp;ndash; just right for me. The color might be a little too dark, though. It could be lighter, or even use light dots, like a signature line, and it&amp;rsquo;d be nicer in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downsides: the binding doesn&amp;rsquo;t quite open flat, though it comes very close, and I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if it&amp;rsquo;s going to be all that durable, though the notepad is thin enough that it shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have a long heavy-duty life to wear it out. The ruling doesn&amp;rsquo;t have any margin in the center of the binding. This might seem like a nitpick, but without that guide I find myself cramming my pen into the crevice when writing on the left page, and having trouble with an even left-margin when writing on the right page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, one of the top choices for a notebook, due to its design, practical size, and low price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;160 pages, 8.625 x 6.75 x .4375 inches. Rule width: .220 inches. Bought at Target for $8.95.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_9&#34;&gt;Deconstructed journal by Studio Oh!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/studio-oh-deconstructed-clock.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/studio-oh-deconstructed-clock-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;studio-oh-deconstructed-clock&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3221&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This journal is perhaps the most versatile of the notebooks and journals I&amp;rsquo;ve shown here, because it could easily be a very respectable notebook as well. Its binding is the most attention-grabbing feature. Take a look:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/studio-oh-deconstructed-clock-edge.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/studio-oh-deconstructed-clock-edge-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;studio-oh-deconstructed-clock-edge&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3220&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journal opens absolutely flat, without a hint of resistance. This is the flattest-opening notebook I&amp;rsquo;ve ever seen. Will the binding hold up? On close inspection, it does seem pretty well-bound. I suspect it&amp;rsquo;ll last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cover is quite rigid, the corners are rounded, the paper is silky and smooth though perhaps a bit thin, and overall it feels really nice. The only points against it, as far as a notebook, are the ruling width and the stiff covers. It&amp;rsquo;s also a little heavy, now that I think about it. Still, it&amp;rsquo;ll easily be a great journal, and could be a very nice notebook too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;192 pages, 8.625 x 6.5 x .6875 inches. Rule width: .3125 inches. Bought at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Studio-Oh-Deconstructed-Journal-Epoque/dp/B005K03NHW/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; for $13.85; also available from Barnes &amp;amp; Noble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_10&#34;&gt;Whitelines Squared notebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/whitelines-squared.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/whitelines-squared-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;whitelines-squared&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3222&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This premium-quality notebook has a really unusual feature: instead of white paper with dark lines, it has slightly gray paper with white lines. The idea is that this is less distracting and will glare and contrast less, and that what you write will stand out, rather than conflicting with the lines. I chose a &amp;ldquo;graph paper&amp;rdquo; or grid, instead of a lined/ruled notebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a nice size (A5, perfect!), has really nice paper, and is made with a C02-neutral process. It&amp;rsquo;s sharply designed and utilitarian, with a black cover that has a single orange horizontal stripe. There&amp;rsquo;s no arguing that it&amp;rsquo;s not a high-end notebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downsides? The cover is rigid, and the corners are squared instead of rounded. The binding doesn&amp;rsquo;t open flat; in fact, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t really even come close, and this will be a nuisance. Although the white-lined feature seems nice, I wish it didn&amp;rsquo;t extend all the way to the edge of the paper. The grid feature does give some guidance for margins, but I foresee myself getting greedy in the margins accidentally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to have to say that a couple of the others are nicer, because of their binding and ruling with margins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;200 pages, 8.5 x 6 x .6875 inches. Rule width: .197 inches. Bought at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0052XQDUG/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; for $11.95.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_11&#34;&gt;Clairefontaine notebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/clairefontaine.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/clairefontaine-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;clairefontaine&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3223&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This notebook is practical and functional, with a plain black cover that&amp;rsquo;s flexible, and rounded corners. Inside there&amp;rsquo;s no decoration or jazz; just basic, plain ruled paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper, though, is a highlight. This is Clairefontaine&amp;rsquo;s famous high-quality paper, and I&amp;rsquo;ve used it before. It&amp;rsquo;s really nice quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The notebook is also a great size: not too thick, not too large (A5 again), easy to carry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Downside? There are no margins, and the ruling is wide for my taste. The binding doesn&amp;rsquo;t open as flat as I&amp;rsquo;d like. Still, a very good choice for a notebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;192 pages, 8.125 x 5.875 x .4375 inches. Rule width: .3125 inches. Bought at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B003JMZT98/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; for $10.99.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_12&#34;&gt;Barnes &amp;amp; Noble journal refill&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/barnes-noble-refill.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/barnes-noble-refill-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;barnes-noble-refill&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3224&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grabbed this journal refill from the shelves at B/N for one reason: it&amp;rsquo;s simple and inexpensive. It&amp;rsquo;s designed to replace the interior of some kind of journal, I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what exactly. The paper is a high-quality Italian ivory, and the cover is heavy card stock. The binding opens very flat, more so than many of the notebooks I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the downside, the corners are not rounded, and there is a decoration at the bottom of each page, which shouts out &amp;ldquo;journal!&amp;rdquo; and not &amp;ldquo;professional notes!&amp;rdquo; Still, it&amp;rsquo;s a better choice for notes than some of the notepads I&amp;rsquo;ve bought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;224 pages, 8.25 x 5.75 x .625 inches. Rule width: .26 inches. Bought at Barnes &amp;amp; Noble for $7.95.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_13&#34;&gt;Leuchtturm 1917 notebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/leuchtturm-1917.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/leuchtturm-1917-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;leuchtturm-1917&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3225&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Leuchtturm 1917 notebook has a very analytical, practical feel. It has some great standout features, too, such as page numbers on every page, and the paper is obviously good quality. It also has some nice additions, such as stickers for labeling and archiving, and the binding is very nice, although it doesn&amp;rsquo;t quite open flat easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than the added touches such as page numbers and high-quality paper, you could easily mistake it for a Moleskine if you weren&amp;rsquo;t a notebook snob. The cover is plain black, with a bit more flex than a Moleskine cover, rounded corners (and the pages are rounded too). As soon as you open it and examine it, though, you see why their motto is &amp;ldquo;details make all the difference.&amp;rdquo; It&amp;rsquo;s obviously a step up in quality from a Moleskine. For example, although the ruling is essentially the same in design and width, it&amp;rsquo;s much lighter than the Moleskine&amp;rsquo;s obtrusive, coarse rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;249 pages, 5.75 x 8.25 x .6875 inches. Rule width: .236 inches. Bought at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B002CVAU1Y/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; for $15.99.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_14&#34;&gt;Moleskine notebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/moleskine.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/moleskine-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;moleskine&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3226&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, Moleskine, how we love to love you and pay a premium for you. Yet you&amp;rsquo;re so&amp;hellip; boring. Your paper isn&amp;rsquo;t all that great, your cover is uninspiring, your heavy ruling goes all the way across the page with no margin, your elastic droops and sags. You are the girl next door, and goodness knows why you&amp;rsquo;ve gotten a reputation for being the beauty queen, because you&amp;rsquo;re not the best girl to take to the prom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Moleskine notebooks are perfectly functional, with a nice binding, and lots of adoring fans can&amp;rsquo;t all be all wrong, can they?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;240 pages, 8.25 x 5.25 x .625 inches. Rule width: .236 inches. Bought at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Moleskine-Classic-Cover-Large-Notebook/dp/8883701143/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; for $15.41.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_15&#34;&gt;Chameleon Like medium notebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/chameleon-like-large.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/chameleon-like-large-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;chameleon-like-large&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3227&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is essentially another Moleskine look-alike, although it&amp;rsquo;s a size smaller and has a tan cover instead of black. The binding is actually nicer, though the paper is not as nice. Overall, nothing remarkable to see here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s at this size and form factor that the notebooks definitely start to get too small for me. A small, rigid notebook like this isn&amp;rsquo;t the easiest thing to carry or write on, and you end up wasting a lot of space unless you cram your writing really close to the edges of the pages, which makes everything unpleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;192 pages, 7 x 5 x .625 inches. Rule width: .278 inches. Source: freebie at a conference, though apparently they can be had for about $4.99.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_16&#34;&gt;Semikolon Il Creativo notebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/semikolon-creativo-small.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/semikolon-creativo-small-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;semikolon-creativo-small&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3228&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the small version of the large Il Creativo mentioned above. When I saw that the large one was too big for me, I tried to buy a medium one, but it was unavailable from any sellers I could find, so I tried the small one. Unfortunately, like Goldilocks and the Three Bears, this one is Really Too Small. It&amp;rsquo;s cramped to write in. It&amp;rsquo;s just as thick and blocky as the large size. It has too many pages. And it has that annoyingly wide ruling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to like it. But I just can&amp;rsquo;t. I wish I&amp;rsquo;d been able to get a medium-sized one, but frankly I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have enjoyed it all that much either. Alas!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;304 pages, 5.625 x 4.375 x 1 inch. Rule width: .375 inches. Bought at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B005DVEU1G/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; for $8.37.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_17&#34;&gt;Small Chameleon Like notebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/chameleon-like-small.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/chameleon-like-small-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;chameleon-like-small&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3229&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just the smaller version of the above Chameleon Like notebook. Way too small for my taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_18&#34;&gt;teNues CoolNotes notebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ditto &amp;ndash; this notebook is another mini-Moleskine-lookalike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_19&#34;&gt;The Winners&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It depends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you want a journal? I think you can hardly go wrong with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Almond-Blossom-Journal-Notebook-Diary/dp/144130357X/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Peter Pauper&lt;/a&gt; or the PaperBlanks. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Studio-Oh-Deconstructed-Journal-Epoque/dp/B005K03NHW/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Studio Oh!&lt;/a&gt; is a great choice too, especially because it&amp;rsquo;s actually a nicer grade of book and is a little less pricey. It isn&amp;rsquo;t as beautiful, though. On the larger side, the Markings leatherette is a hefty journal that will last a long time, though it&amp;rsquo;s plain too. And if you want a journal that screams &amp;ldquo;Swiss watch designer&amp;rsquo;s journal!&amp;rdquo; then maybe you&amp;rsquo;d like the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B005DVEUDO/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Semikolon Il Creativo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you want a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Moleskine-Classic-Cover-Large-Notebook/dp/8883701143/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Moleskine&lt;/a&gt;? Then buy one. Do you want something like it but better quality? Then get the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B002CVAU1Y/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Leuchtturm&lt;/a&gt;, hands down. It&amp;rsquo;s easily the nicest thing in the Moleskine class. I also like the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B003JMZT98/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Clairefontaine&lt;/a&gt; a lot, and if you&amp;rsquo;re looking for something a little different, you might like the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0052XQDUG/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Whitelines&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you want a big, bulky, analytical notebook? That&amp;rsquo;s the Semikolon Il Creativo for you again. Organize thyself!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you&amp;rsquo;re like me and you really want a compact, flexible, practical notebook that slips easily into a messenger bag, opens flat, has nice paper, is slim and inexpensive &amp;ndash; then I&amp;rsquo;m leaning towards recommending the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0072WW8K4/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Quo Vadis Habana&lt;/a&gt; or the Mead Cambridge Premium Notebook, depending on your taste. Note that I can&amp;rsquo;t find the Cambridge online, but if you&amp;rsquo;re near a Target it&amp;rsquo;s probably easy to find. I might go back and buy a half dozen or so, just in case that turns out not to be true!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, the ultimate notebook for me is 80-100 sheets of paper or 160-200 pages (I&amp;rsquo;ve listed pages above, to make everything consistent), an A5 size, and has pretty minimal features &amp;ndash; no need for a ribbon or an elastic strap &amp;ndash; just nice-quality paper, a slim and flexible design, and the right ruling and margins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are my favorites in one photo. The rest is up to you. Happy writing, drawing, designing, sketching, scheduling, and organizing! &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/best-notebooks-journals.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/07/best-notebooks-journals-300x225.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;best-notebooks-journals&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3231&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy is impossible unless it&#39;s the default</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/06/privacy-is-impossible-unless-its-the-default/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/06/privacy-is-impossible-unless-its-the-default/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a follow-up to my last post, in which I asserted that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/05/without-free-software-and-hardware-privacy-is-impossible/&#34; title=&#34;without free software and hardware, privacy is impossible&#34;&gt;without free software and hardware, privacy is impossible&lt;/a&gt;. Suppose we have trustworthy, free hardware and software. What else is needed to thwart efforts to monitor our everyday behavior on a massive scale?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look only at one activity that&amp;rsquo;s currently being monitored: email. How can we make email less vulnerable to prying eyes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology to encrypt email between ordinary citizens (PGP, OpenPGP, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gnupg.org/&#34;&gt;GnuPG&lt;/a&gt;) has existed for years, and in a form strong enough to frustrate any known attempts at decryption. The encrypted emails can be decrypted, but it requires a brute-force effort of computing, which would take far too long with available computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you and I use this technology right now to encrypt our communications, we&amp;rsquo;ll actually make ourselves more interesting targets. That&amp;rsquo;s partially because we&amp;rsquo;d be among the few people doing so. Have you ever noticed that nothing draws attention like whispering in a public place? I don&amp;rsquo;t know what proportion of ordinary email between everyday people is encrypted, but if pressed, I&amp;rsquo;d guess it&amp;rsquo;s fewer than one email in 50,000. That&amp;rsquo;s an extraordinarily strong signal to authorities looking for needles in the haystack of Internet activity. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be surprised if the NSA has large-scale brute-force encryption-cracking clusters dedicated to forcibly decrypting the few encrypted emails that wend their way around the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; sent encrypted email? Then it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be remarkable. Those little &lt;em&gt;hi hon, do you need me to pick up groceries on the way home?&lt;/em&gt; emails I send would be as common as more weighty ones. Brute-forcing may be feasible on a small scale, but I doubt that even un-guessed-at techniques and availability of powerful computers could brute-force decryption on the scale of the whole of the Internet&amp;rsquo;s email. The NSA, unable to determine whose emails to decrypt, would have to settle for snooping on a smaller scale, or giving up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would it take for everyone to use encryption in their emails? It is practically impossible, and thus certainly won&amp;rsquo;t happen, unless all email software makes it &lt;em&gt;the default behavior&lt;/em&gt;. And since most people use email software from companies such as Apple, Microsoft, and Google, this will not happen. Even if these companies wanted to make such software encrypt-by-default, I am absolutely certain that they would be secretly barred from doing so. (Plus, as I&amp;rsquo;ve said in my earlier article, their software would not be trustworthy and we&amp;rsquo;d be spied upon in other ways. Why spy on email software when you can spy on the whole operating system?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Email encryption would also have to be a lot simpler and more automatic. Most computer users, in my opinion, can&amp;rsquo;t understand the concepts of public and private key pairs, how to generate them, how to exchange them, how to know if another person&amp;rsquo;s key should be trusted, and so on. Even HTTPS is baffling to most computer users &amp;ndash; and the only thing they&amp;rsquo;re exposed to is their browser&amp;rsquo;s address bar and the presence or absence of a lock icon, a much simpler thing to understand. Yet a majority of people still get it wrong and expose themselves to phishing attacks, viruses, and other scams. This is not a criticism of them; it&amp;rsquo;s a criticism of the technology. Security technology is way, way too hard for everyday people to use. Thus we&amp;rsquo;ll never have mass encryption unless something fundamentally changes in how we do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if we had mass adoption of encryption, there are a couple of things that would make it easier for the NSA to continue spying on us. Once they decrypt one message, they&amp;rsquo;d have the key to decrypt future emails to that same recipient. So over time they&amp;rsquo;d be able to snoop on more and more people. Encryption keys would have to be rotated regularly to frustrate this. For this, and other technological reasons, absolutely everything would have to &amp;ldquo;just work&amp;rdquo; without any need for manual configuration or intervention. If a human has to do something like rotate an encryption key, it won&amp;rsquo;t happen. Anyone experienced with backups knows what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other is that only the body of the email message is encrypted. The subject, sender, recipient, IP addresses, and a surprising variety of other data would be unprotected. This is too much for my comfort. It&amp;rsquo;s essentially equivalent to the so-called metadata they&amp;rsquo;ve been collecting from Verizon, for example (caller, callee, time of call, and so on).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line is that we are using technologies such as email that were never designed to be resistant to the snooping now occurring. Email encryption is a bolt-on afterthought. It&amp;rsquo;s not feasible society-wide, by default, for all users; and on a smaller scale, it helps identify interesting snoop-worthy targets. And thus there&amp;rsquo;s really nothing we can do that will make government monitoring of email impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a future post I&amp;rsquo;ll broaden this topic beyond email.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Without free software and hardware, privacy is impossible</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/05/without-free-software-and-hardware-privacy-is-impossible/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/05/without-free-software-and-hardware-privacy-is-impossible/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The recent revelations about the NSA&amp;rsquo;s wide-ranging surveillance of Americans and non-Americans alike has spurred a lot of outcry. Of course, some people are crying for legal solutions, but there&amp;rsquo;s absolutely no chance of any present or future elected official changing or stopping it (it&amp;rsquo;s already completely illegal and always has been, so more laws can do nothing but poke loopholes in existing laws forbidding surveillance).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re on a road that leads to only one place: total, absolute government monitoring of everything we do &amp;ndash; and thus, to some extent, control of everything we do. I&amp;rsquo;m not a conspiracy theorist or right-wing nutcase. It&amp;rsquo;s just a simple fact that any reasoning person should be able to deduce from a little objective examination of history and a smidgen of logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is really serious. We are (and have been for years) hovering on the brink of a sudden plunge towards a truly Orwellian society, with progress heading that direction pretty steadily. What are you going to do about it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to stop surveillance is to encrypt things and make surveillance impossible. Not just impossible for some people. It needs to be impossible for everyone, which means it has to be based on math that&amp;rsquo;s essentially unsolvable (this is how encryption works). If they can do it, they will do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to make decryption impossible is with encryption and decryption systems that are designed to have no possibility of central control. If there is any kind of central control or access to the system, your government will seize that and use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to trust those kinds of systems is for them to be made wholly of open-source, free software. No amount of proprietary-ness or obscurity brings security. This is because if there&amp;rsquo;s any type of hidden or secret knowledge about how to use or build the system, someone has an advantage, and that advantage will be held by those who shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to trust the software is if it&amp;rsquo;s running on trustworthy hardware. You can run the highest encryption you wish, but you can&amp;rsquo;t read what&amp;rsquo;s on your screen unless your computer&amp;rsquo;s hardware and software decrypt it to show it to you. That means that your computer&amp;rsquo;s software and hardware has access to the decrypted information. And if there&amp;rsquo;s any back door in the hardware, it&amp;rsquo;s untrustworthy and will be exploited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why I continue to be a Free Software Foundation member. Vote with your wallet and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fsf.org/&#34;&gt;join the FSF&lt;/a&gt; today. It&amp;rsquo;s a tiny organization with fewer than twenty staff who&amp;rsquo;ve made an incalculable difference in your freedom today. Without the FSF I have no doubt we&amp;rsquo;d already be significantly further down the road to the total monitoring and control of normal citizens&amp;rsquo; everyday lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll end this post with the Fourth Amendment of the United States Constitution:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The right of the people to be secure in their persons, houses, papers, and effects, against unreasonable searches and seizures, shall not be violated, and no Warrants shall issue, but upon probable cause, supported by Oath or affirmation, and particularly describing the place to be searched, and the persons or things to be seized. &amp;#8211; Fourth Amendment, US Constitution
That amendment was written for damn good reasons based on horrific abuses of power by governments through the ages. Think about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The moment I first held my newborn daughter in my arms</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/06/05/the-moment-i-first-held-my-newborn-daughter-in-my-arms/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/06/05/the-moment-i-first-held-my-newborn-daughter-in-my-arms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a personal post, not a technical one. We tell ourselves a lot of lies that are not okay. I want to out one of them. It is important to be real, to be true to oneself. This matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lie starts something like this: the moment I held my newborn child in my arms, I looked into her tiny face and felt an all-encompassing, pure love. I was breathless. I could not think, speak, or move. My life was complete, and I knew I was changed forever in that instant. I knew that I would do anything for this tiny creature, even give up my own life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This script is repeated ad nauseum in books, TV shows, movies, songs, and most of all, person-to-person. If you have children, ask yourself, is this honestly the experience you had? No? Well, you&amp;rsquo;re not alone, because this is by and large an absurd lie. Unsurprisingly, psychologists who study attachment can tell you that most people take time &amp;ndash; some of them a lot of time &amp;ndash; to become strongly attached to their children. If you don&amp;rsquo;t have this phony experience of mindblowing love at first sight, &lt;em&gt;nothing is wrong with you.&lt;/em&gt; You are perfectly normal and this is okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many men, in particular, don&amp;rsquo;t feel strong feelings for their children until many months or even years have passed. I know not only through my own experience, but also because I&amp;rsquo;ve asked literally dozens of fathers, and heard not one single story that matches what we&amp;rsquo;re told we should feel by popular media. Shockingly, some men &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; feel the feelings of fatherly attachment we&amp;rsquo;re taught we should feel. And that includes many of the best fathers that have ever lived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you aren&amp;rsquo;t a father, maybe you don&amp;rsquo;t know this, but infants do very little for a long time. They are helpless and confused, and they can&amp;rsquo;t move, they don&amp;rsquo;t recognize you, they don&amp;rsquo;t smile, they don&amp;rsquo;t laugh, they don&amp;rsquo;t express affection. They cry, poop, sleep, and eat, and they generally make you cry by interfering with your own pooping, sleeping, and eating. By the time children even begin to crack a smile, parents and grandparents have spent sleep-deprived months mistaking fart grimaces as smiles, out of a desperate desire to believe it&amp;rsquo;s a smile. Beyond smiles, it takes a long time until children return hugs or say &amp;ldquo;Daddy!&amp;rdquo; or snuggle or want to sit on your lap with a book and read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experience of being a father is very special, but let&amp;rsquo;s not lie to ourselves and give ourselves inferiority complexes if we don&amp;rsquo;t feel anything but exhausted and irritated for a long, long time after a child is born. Be patient and honest with yourself. It is more important to be honest than to conform to ridiculous expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we perpetuate this harmful and inappropriate lie about our blinding love for our children? Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s because we are confused about what love is. Love is not a feeling, it is the act of caring for another&amp;rsquo;s well-being, through conscious decision and a huge effort against internal resistance, because you know it is the right thing to do and for no other reason. Loving feelings are sometimes a result of loving action, and often don&amp;rsquo;t come soon or strongly, but real love is not conditioned upon the feelings, because they are an effect, not a cause. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in this line of thought, I recommend reading &amp;ldquo;The Road Less Traveled&amp;rdquo; by M. Scott Peck. Love is not a feeling. I know this is not what most cultures teach, but it&amp;rsquo;s true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you do have an amazing experience of overwhelming feelings in those first few moments, be a little reserved in how you share it with others, okay? It could be a great favor (an act of love, in fact) to a great many people.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why building a free service can be a disservice</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/05/18/why-building-a-free-service-can-be-a-disservice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/05/18/why-building-a-free-service-can-be-a-disservice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Like many others, I don&amp;rsquo;t think that RSS is dead. It&amp;rsquo;s my favorite way to keep up with highly valuable content on the Web. So I&amp;rsquo;m in the market for a replacement for Google Reader, along with millions of others. As I&amp;rsquo;ve evaluated options, I&amp;rsquo;ve had to eliminate some of them because I&amp;rsquo;m not sure they&amp;rsquo;re serious about what they&amp;rsquo;re doing. This post is about my thought process and why I think entrepreneurs should challenge themselves to get serious, and signal that intent, by not building free services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I&amp;rsquo;ve looked around, a number of replacement or alternative services exist. Some of them offer a subscription, but also a free (or freemium) model. Some are free-only. As I assess each of these, I am measuring them against some important questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, although the main thing I care about is the product and how it serves my use-case needs, one of my meta-needs is longevity. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to change things. I want to find things that work, and stick with them. I just don&amp;rsquo;t have the bandwidth to go through this process all the time. I&amp;rsquo;ll stick with something old-but-serviceable for a long time after my friends tell me that the new kid on the block is so much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I really want to know that the people behind the product are damn serious about building it into a lasting service, which means a lasting business. I want to know that they&amp;rsquo;re not in it for a quick flip-to-big-company-that&amp;rsquo;ll-kill-it, it&amp;rsquo;s not an acqui-hire-me strategy, it&amp;rsquo;s not a lifestyle project or a hobby, it&amp;rsquo;s not something they&amp;rsquo;ll tire of and go take a job with another company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember Delicious and Magnolia? A bunch of my friends switched from the former to the latter, and then there was a spectacular data loss incident, and they all lost all of their bookmarks. And the guy who ran Magnolia seemed to signal that he wasn&amp;rsquo;t willing to press on when the going got tough. When it became clear that it&amp;rsquo;d cost some money and time to recover the corrupt data he hadn&amp;rsquo;t backed up, even though his users were loyal and willing to help, he shut the service down. Something similar almost happened with Couchsurfing. In both cases, the users/customers felt (and were) set up to be betrayed because the service was never a mutual obligation; it was an offer of something free with no expectations in either direction. Ah, but expectations always exist, and to avoid acknowledging that is tantamount to dishonesty by omission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I look for a service or product that I&amp;rsquo;m going to rely on to do something for me &amp;ndash; such as aggregating my chosen Web content &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;m doing it because the value to me is real. It&amp;rsquo;s a huge time-saver. Time is worth money. I want to see signs that they understand this and insist that I give them money in return for the benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a service is free, one must speculate. There are a variety of reasons something is free, but usually, when a product is free, YOU are the product. This is the case with Facebook and Google. I&amp;rsquo;m OK with this when I understand it and I believe that the company knows how to take the product-of-me and build a business on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases, however, I want to pay. Not too much, but more than a little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paying an appropriate amount of money gives me a lot of assurances. First, it means the company has their act together on a much larger scale than just running the IT and technical stuff. It&amp;rsquo;s relatively easy to build a product &amp;ndash; much harder to build a company. The logistics of assembling the business around the product are pretty large. Second, it means I have a right to expect good service and to complain. Businesses that are trying to drive the cost down send the signal that they&amp;rsquo;re just paying attention to competitors, not customers. I had a lot of experience with Virtual PBX products a few years ago &amp;ndash; they were all charging pennies, and there was no one I could pay a decent chunk of money to. That meant that I was entitled to dropped and misrouted calls and horrible voice quality and poor customer service. It&amp;rsquo;s frustrating when there isn&amp;rsquo;t a solid alternative and you can tell that the market is just being gutted by a price race to the bottom. The elephants fighting means the ant gets trampled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently tried to use a service that integrates with Github and provides a really valuable add-on. It&amp;rsquo;s built up as a free open-source project that is now trying to commercialize. There are several products and companies in this space; I assume Github will eventually acquire one, and the others will become irrelevant. This is unfortunate, because you have to assume the teams behind the products understand this and are angling to be first in line for the acquisition. That sends a strong signal about their real motivations &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;not the customer.&amp;rdquo; I tried Product A, and was able to convince them to take me as a paying alpha user (they mostly offer the product for free.) But they were charging way too much &amp;ndash; many times what I pay for Github. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense to pay several multiples of Github, to add a feature to Github. I negotiated a long-term deal that was in my interests: not too much, not too little, 12-month deal &amp;ndash; should have been a no-brainer for them, because as a young company, if you have ambitions, this is what you&amp;rsquo;re dying to show investors. But after they agreed to the terms, they couldn&amp;rsquo;t get their invoicing process together. After a while I found another company doing something similar, who were totally on the ball. This other company offered a free trial period to assess the product, but after that you pay or you leave. They&amp;rsquo;ve done a great job for me and I haven&amp;rsquo;t had a second thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, back to the point &amp;ndash; as an entrepreneur, I think you should get serious, and signal your intention by charging an appropriate amount of money. Don&amp;rsquo;t copy giant companies who offer things for free. That free (or freemium) strategy only works in very special cases. You should understand what those cases are &amp;ndash; if you don&amp;rsquo;t, get someone business savvy to help with your strategy. The vast, vast majority of businesses are emphatically not right for free/freemium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charging also obligates you to what you&amp;rsquo;re offering. It gives you no easy out, mentally. I think a lot of people may be subconsciously more comfortable with leaving themselves that out: &lt;em&gt;if this gets tough, I don&amp;rsquo;t have to feel guilty, because it&amp;rsquo;s not like I owed the users anything&lt;/em&gt;. (If you&amp;rsquo;re thinking about &amp;ldquo;users&amp;rdquo; instead of &amp;ldquo;customers&amp;rdquo; you&amp;rsquo;re probably doing it wrong.) Man up and charge your customers, and accept the obligation that comes in return. Now when shit hits the fan, you damn well better stay up all night fixing it. You can&amp;rsquo;t just go &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m tired, and it&amp;rsquo;s Friday night. Screw it. I&amp;rsquo;ll get back to work on this Monday.&amp;rdquo; (If you&amp;rsquo;re scared of being obligated to work all weekend on a few hours of sleep, you&amp;rsquo;re also probably doing it wrong.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building something for free can be a way to avoid risk, avoid complexity, avoid boring/mundane/hard things that don&amp;rsquo;t feel rewarding. But those things are exactly what make you grow, and you do yourself and your customers (users) a huge disservice if you don&amp;rsquo;t challenge yourself to grow. Growth comes from risk, and creates risk. That&amp;rsquo;s what life is about. See, this is the difference between a nerd/coder and an entrepreneur. An entrepreneur puts his/her career on the line and takes the risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want a Google Reader replacement from an entrepreneur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to end by clarifying a few points. 1) This isn&amp;rsquo;t about Google Reader; it just provided the inspiration. 2) Google Reader is free in a manner of speaking, so it might seem odd that I&amp;rsquo;m insisting that its replacement be non-free. Google Reader is in a special category because it&amp;rsquo;s owned by a company that I believe is unlikely to close its doors soon. None of the replacements I&amp;rsquo;ve seen so far are in that position. 3) I&amp;rsquo;m not saying that none of the replacements I&amp;rsquo;m looking at is built by an entrepreneur who&amp;rsquo;s serious about making a business from it &amp;ndash; but some of them are not clearly identifiable as anything more than hobby projects.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s the lesson from daily deals sites?</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/05/09/whats-the-lesson-from-daily-deals-sites/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/05/09/whats-the-lesson-from-daily-deals-sites/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I found myself in a, ahem, lively discussion with someone recently. It started when I said &amp;ldquo;there was always something wrong about the daily deals businesses (i.e. Groupon), but I&amp;rsquo;m sure they&amp;rsquo;ll teach us what&amp;rsquo;s really needed.&amp;rdquo; Turns out this person ran a local daily-deals site. Oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My feeling is that anytime something doesn&amp;rsquo;t take root and grow into a lasting business, there&amp;rsquo;s a lesson to learn. Early social-networking sites weren&amp;rsquo;t quite a match with needs. More recent ones have gotten something right that the early ones missed. More than one thing needs to be gotten right. In particular, to achieve good user adoption, the value you deliver for the user, what you ask in return, and what the user perceives of both the value and the returned favor are all very delicate balances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always felt that these were out of balance in daily-deals businesses because they framed things wrong for the customer. If I get a daily-deals coupon to go try something out, I might be motivated to try it, but my core belief is that if I wasn&amp;rsquo;t already a customer, I&amp;rsquo;m not going to become one after my cheapo trial. I think one of the main reasons for that is that the daily-deal coupon sends the signal that the product isn&amp;rsquo;t worth the usual price. I firmly believe that most people live by &amp;ldquo;you get what you pay for,&amp;rdquo; and that this is a two-way street. If you don&amp;rsquo;t pay a lot, then you don&amp;rsquo;t think it&amp;rsquo;s worth a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I joined Percona, their consulting rate was $200 per hour. Complaints about this high rate were widespread, both externally and internally (consultants thought it was too high also). But something funny was going on: customers wouldn&amp;rsquo;t keep their appointments with consultants, and they didn&amp;rsquo;t seem to care. I made it a policy that missed appointments would be billed anyway, and that didn&amp;rsquo;t change anything. So I experimented with the rates. After trying out various rates for about a month, $300 per hour seemed to be a sweet spot. Serious customers were still willing to pay, we weeded out many bad customers who only caused trouble, and most importantly, a lot fewer appointments were missed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I experienced something similar in my individual consultancy. I worked on a pro bono basis for a local immigrant health clinic. I had a bad feeling that I was taken for granted, and one day when I was at the clinic early to finish up the project, I stood in the early morning cold for half an hour before I realized that nobody was coming to meet me and let me into the building. After that I stopped doing anything pro bono, and I always had a good feeling that my services were appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while arguing about the daily deals sites, I recalled the feeling I always had: that there was something wrong with the business model &amp;ndash; that it was undermining what it was supposed to promote. And that vague notion came back to me: the decline of daily deals should teach us what ought to be done instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, it came to me: A daily-deals offer is like a one-night stand, with no expectation of a long-term relationship. Without this agreement at the foundation of the relationship, the match between the ask and the offer is lopsided, and the &amp;ldquo;customer&amp;rdquo; becomes an exploiter, instead of a customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with that, I realized that I had it wrong. Far from being the leading indicator, the daily deals sites were actually behind the times. There have been businesses for many years doing what they should have done. I&amp;rsquo;ve supported some of them myself. I&amp;rsquo;m referring to BMG&amp;rsquo;s music subscription, Omaha Steaks, book-of-the-month clubs, gourmet coffee or wine subscriptions, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You begin these relationships with several subtly intertwined things, including a good introductory offer, an upfront agreement on the real value of what you&amp;rsquo;re getting in the trial, and an agreement to be a long-term customer. Oh, sure, you can change your mind and cancel after the introductory offer is up. But agreeing and then canceling is different from never agreeing. There&amp;rsquo;s probably a lot of psychological research related to what I&amp;rsquo;m claiming, and I&amp;rsquo;m sure that some of it contradicts me, but I believe that &amp;ldquo;buy 10 CDs at $1 each, then we&amp;rsquo;ll send one per month at full price thereafter, and if you buy X more within a year you get another batch at $1 each&amp;rdquo; is very different from &amp;ldquo;you can rip this merchant off by walking out of his store with $1 CDs and no actual or implied obligation.&amp;rdquo; With BMG&amp;rsquo;s music subscription service, you opt in and then you have to opt out again (either once-and-for-all, or once every month). And maybe your conscious brain says &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m going to just cancel after I get my cheap CDs,&amp;rdquo; but I&amp;rsquo;m an astute enough observer of myself to know that my subconscious feels differently about the matter. In the back of my mind, I feel like I&amp;rsquo;m cheating BMG if I cancel before I buy enough CDs at full price to be a profitable customer for them. The conscience gets involved. It never gets involved with a daily deal &amp;ndash; there&amp;rsquo;s no opt-in to opt-out of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps what the daily deals sites need to do is bring a platform for this kind of long-term relationship, and managing the logistics, to lots of companies so they don&amp;rsquo;t have to reinvent it on their own. Perhaps there is a &amp;ldquo;next time we&amp;rsquo;ll get this right&amp;rdquo; for daily deals after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On that note, it&amp;rsquo;s a good thing &lt;a href=&#34;http://gearhartschocolates.com/&#34;&gt;Gearhart&amp;rsquo;s Chocolates&lt;/a&gt; doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a BMG-like deal, because you&amp;rsquo;d have me at &amp;ldquo;chocolate.&amp;rdquo; (If you don&amp;rsquo;t know who they are, it&amp;rsquo;s a local Charlottesville chocolatier that is easily one of the best in the entire world, and priced to match. I send their variety pack as thank-yous fairly often. Just another perk of living in Charlottesville.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>