<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Hardware on Xaprb </title>
      <generator uri="https://hugo.spf13.com">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://www.xaprb.com/categories/hardware/index.xml/</link>
    
    
    
    <updated>Sat, 24 Jan 2015 00:00:00 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Ultimate Bargain Coffee Kit</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2015/01/24/ultimate-bargain-coffee-kit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2015 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2015/01/24/ultimate-bargain-coffee-kit/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve started drinking coffee over the last few years. Like most things I&amp;rsquo;ve
picked up relatively late in life, I am kind of a snob, in that I want good
coffee but I want it to be quick, easy, and cheap. This post is about the gear
I&amp;rsquo;ve settled on for making my morning cup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2015/01/coffee.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;coffee&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a wide range of gear you could build up, from super-cheap to really
nice, and in general the more expensive, the better coffee you&amp;rsquo;ll make. I am a
middle-of-the-road, Pareto Principle kind of guy. I want coffee that&amp;rsquo;s 80% or
more as good as the best coffee from experts, at a fraction of the cost and
effort. Here&amp;rsquo;s my list of &amp;ldquo;best value and balance&amp;rdquo; gear. As a bonus, some of my
gear items are things I already had (kettle, Brita pitcher) so
my coffee habit really didn&amp;rsquo;t entail adding much more equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Whole-Bean Coffee&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whole-bean coffee has to be ground before making it. You can read lots of
details online about why grinding just before brewing makes better coffee. I
notice a difference, and that&amp;rsquo;s enough for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My personal preference is to stick with something pretty simple and not all that
expensive, somewhere in the range of $6.00 to $8.00 for a bag or can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m currently enjoying several of the blends from Trader Joe&amp;rsquo;s. My wife likes
Central American beans, and I like those too; I once visited a coffee farm on
the slopes of a mountain in Costa Rica so it evokes fond memories. I also enjoy
Arabica. I like a medium or dark roast most of the time, but there&amp;rsquo;s an infinite
variety of beans, blends and roasts, and various combinations of them are better
or worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2015/01/gevalia.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;gevalia&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another decent middle-of-the-road brand is Gevalia, which tends towards the
better-quality range of not-too-expensive coffee. As a bonus, many of &lt;a href=&#34;www.amazon.com/Gevalia-French-Roast-Ground-Coffee/dp/B00MBEKH6U/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;their
roasts&lt;/a&gt;
come pre-ground. Sometimes the convenience of pre-ground is just what I need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Coffee Grinder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two kinds of grinders: conical burr, and ones that aren&amp;rsquo;t worth using.
The conical burr grinders produce a better, more uniform grind, without all
kinds of smashing and splattering of oils and other carnage and destruction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only problem is most conical burr grinders are several hundred bucks. There
is a bargain grinder, though, and it&amp;rsquo;s awesome. It&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Hario-Ceramic-Skerton-Storage-Capacity/dp/B001802PIQ/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Hario
Skerton&lt;/a&gt;, a Japanese hand-grinder
that fits on top of a little jar. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to use and produces a good quality
grind, it&amp;rsquo;s durable and doesn&amp;rsquo;t break, &lt;em&gt;and it is not expensive at all.&lt;/em&gt; The current price on Amazon is $32, and
there&amp;rsquo;s a rebranded version of it at a similar price. One or the other is
sometimes cheaper or more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2015/01/hario.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;hario&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The catch? If you set it to a very fine blend, it&amp;rsquo;ll take a while to grind.
Some people also complain about having to grind by hand. I honestly do not know
why. It is easy to grind, especially if you hold it in the air instead of trying
to hold it still on a counter-top, and enough coffee for a cup or two takes less
time to grind than the water takes to heat up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Water Kettle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heating water properly is a big part of a good cup of coffee. If you just boil
water on the stove, you&amp;rsquo;re going to get a nasty, bitter cup for sure. Your water
needs to be the right temperature; it varies by roast and personal taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can buy a simple thermometer, but in my opinion the easiest and cheapest way
to get water the right temperature is to use a programmable electric kettle. The
one I like, and have used several times a day for years (I drink one small cup
of coffee in the morning but many cups of tea all day long) is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Oster-BVST-EK5967-NP-Digital-Temperature-1-7-Liter/dp/B00BLR03I0/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Oster
BVST-EK5967-NP&lt;/a&gt;.
It&amp;rsquo;s $30 on Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2015/01/oster.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;oster&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you click through the link and look at the reviews, you&amp;rsquo;ll see everyone
complaining about it being cheap and failing after a short while. I don&amp;rsquo;t know
what the deal with that is. I had a friend who got scared off by the reviews,
bought a highly-rated one instead, and I&amp;rsquo;ve used it a ton. It is awful compared
to the Oster&amp;mdash;doesn&amp;rsquo;t turn off properly, doesn&amp;rsquo;t heat quickly, doesn&amp;rsquo;t alarm
when done, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a temperature control. The Oster has been great
for me. It&amp;rsquo;s possible that the Oster has changed since I got mine, though, and
it may indeed be lower quality now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heat the water to 190&amp;deg; F for most of my coffee. It&amp;rsquo;s easy with this
kettle: press twice on the minus button, press Start. About a minute later it&amp;rsquo;ll
be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a bonus, using an electric kettle like this is much faster than a pot on the
stove, and I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be surprised if it uses less electricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;Water Filter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tap water, with all of its nasty chemicals and minerals, definitely doesn&amp;rsquo;t make as good a
cup of coffee as filtered water. I use an ordinary
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Brita-10-Cup-Everyday-Filter-Pitcher/dp/B004GNGID0/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Brita&lt;/a&gt;
pitcher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2015/01/brita.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;brita&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to know how much difference this really makes, try the little Brita
test: make two cups of tea, one with tap water and one with Brita water, in
transparent glasses. Just any standard tea will do. If your tap water is
anything like mine, you&amp;rsquo;ll be shocked by the difference in appearance alone. The
only downside to using a Brita filter is that you need to remember to change it
every so often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_4&#34;&gt;Coffee Maker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are about as many ways to make coffee as there are people. If I could
drink my dream coffee every day, I&amp;rsquo;d drink traditional Espresso. However, making
Espresso takes a lot of equipment that&amp;rsquo;s usually &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; expensive, and it is
delicate and finicky. So many things have to be done &amp;ldquo;just right.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My compromise is
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Aeropress-Coffee-and-Espresso-Maker/dp/B0047BIWSK/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Aeropress&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s
not really a &amp;ldquo;compromise&amp;rdquo; since I think it&amp;rsquo;s great coffee by any standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2015/01/aeropress.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;aeropress&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aeropress coffee is about as close to an Espresso as
you can get without making real Espresso. The emphasis is on the coffee&amp;rsquo;s
flavors&amp;mdash;the oils, aromas, and organic compounds&amp;mdash;and not just bitterness,
which is all I taste with most &amp;ldquo;standard&amp;rdquo; American coffee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is more, too. A cup of Aeropress coffee is super-quick and simple to make!
I only use half of the parts that you see in the picture above: the press,
scoop, and mixer. I have no use for the funnel or the filter dispenser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, if you do like a larger serving and a more traditional American taste (less
strong), just add hot water to your Aeropress Espresso and you&amp;rsquo;re there.
Aeropress is also small enough to take with you when you travel. No more
disgusting coffee from the hotel lobby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of science behind why Aeropress coffee is not bitter and tastes
better. You can read about it on the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Aeropress-Coffee-and-Espresso-Maker/dp/B0047BIWSK/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Amazon page&lt;/a&gt;.
It also comes with good instructions that explain the correct temperature for
your roast, how long to mix and press, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s also very cheap. The Aeropress comes in at $25 or so, far less than any
other decent coffee maker I&amp;rsquo;ve found, and filters are super-cheap (and reusable
3-5 times too).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have tried drip, percolator, French Press, pour-over, and a bunch of other
coffee techniques. Like I said, Aeropress is easily the best coffee given the
ease and price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_5&#34;&gt;Optional: Nice Mugs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partially due to the Aeropress&amp;rsquo;s size, and partially because I like my mug to be
a little bit small and nicely decorated, I bought the following stack of 4 mugs
with a wire stand
from World Market. The Aeropress fits just right on top of them. They&amp;rsquo;re just a
bit smaller than most of the mugs I&amp;rsquo;m used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2015/01/mugs.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;mugs&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_6&#34;&gt;Bonus: Nespresso Milk Frother For Lattes and Mochas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like lattes and mochas and the like (which I do&amp;mdash;&lt;a href=&#34;https://vividcortex.com/blog/2014/11/05/make-your-own-pumpkin-spice-latte/&#34;&gt;see my pumpkin spice latte
recipe&lt;/a&gt;), then you might like the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Nespresso-Aeroccino-Plus-Milk-Frother/dp/B001UHZAYS/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Nespresso Aeroccino Plus Milk Frother&lt;/a&gt;.
Years ago I got one of these for my wife as part of a Nespresso kit, and I still use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2015/01/aeroccino.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;aeroccino&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With whole milk, or even 2% milk, it does a great job of producing a nice frothy
batch in no time. Drop in some chocolate syrup before foaming (Trader Joe&amp;rsquo;s and Whole Foods
both have good-quality organic chocolate syrup) and you&amp;rsquo;ve got a pretty decent
mocha. The frother is easy to use, fast, and easy to clean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On that subject, I do like Nespresso too. It makes a pretty good Espresso, all
things considered, though not as good as a &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; one by any stretch. My gripe
with it, and all similar capsule coffee makers such as Keurigs, is the cost. You
can drop a weekend getaway&amp;rsquo;s worth on an order of Nespresso without blinking,
and it will be gone before you know it! By contrast, my Aeropress with a single
scoop, hand-ground, is probably 20 times cheaper per cup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_7&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there you have it. My ideal coffee (which may not be yours) at the moment
turns out to go like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pour some water from the Brita into the kettle, adjust the temp, and heat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put one scoop of beans from the container into the Hario and grind it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set the Aeropress on top of the mug, pour, mix 10 seconds, press 10 seconds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wait a few moments for the coffee to cool enough to enjoy properly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sluuurrrrrp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the rest is gravy. I&amp;rsquo;ve included some decidedly non-essential items in this
post, because I enjoy them and they&amp;rsquo;re part of my overall experience, but you
can certainly get by with much less. For example, if I wanted to be really
minimalistic (as I am when traveling) I can make do with just the Aeropress and
a bag of Gevalia, pre-ground. Voila.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoy your coffee. Let me know your thoughts and ideas!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image credits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/zachinglis/5507648594/&#34;&gt;coffee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Installing CyanogenMod on the Barnes and Noble Nook HD&#43;</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2015/01/19/install-cyanogenmod-nook-hdplus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2015 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2015/01/19/install-cyanogenmod-nook-hdplus/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2014/03/01/barnes-noble-nook-hd/&#34;&gt;wrote previously&lt;/a&gt; about how much I
was using and enjoying my 9-inch Barnes and Noble Nook HD+. I&amp;rsquo;m still using and
enjoying it, but a few of the things I mentioned in that article&amp;mdash;the useless home
screen, the schizophrenic updates from two app stores at once, and so
on&amp;mdash;started to annoy me. I started to fantasize about installing a clean,
uncluttered Android operating system on it instead of using the Nook operating
system. The best-known general-purpose Android OS is CyanogenMod, and that&amp;rsquo;s
what I was thinking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2015/01/cyanogenmod.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;cyanogenmod&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last time I did this, I didn&amp;rsquo;t like the result. I&amp;rsquo;ll explain why, then move on
to show you how to install CyanogenMod easily on the Nook HD+ and talk about the
results. (I&amp;rsquo;m very happy thus far).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;It Didn&amp;rsquo;t End Well Last Time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never wrote about this, but when I &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2011/06/04/using-the-nook-color-as-a-full-featured-android-tablet/&#34;&gt;previously had a 7-inch Nook
Color&lt;/a&gt;,
and installed CyanogenMod on it, I was happy at first but after a while it
wasn&amp;rsquo;t what I wanted anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a number of issues with things like Netflix not working, exiting with an
error about being unsupported on this device (though clearly it wasn&amp;rsquo;t the
device, since the stock Nook OS had Netflix), various apps not working well, and
so on. The base OS seemed to work well enough, but after trying to install some
more apps, I found some problems. Combine that with the not-large-enough size
and the short battery life, and I just eventually sold it on eBay. I tried
wiping it and reinstalling stock Nook OS, but for some reason I must have not
backed up the stock ROM correctly, and it didn&amp;rsquo;t really function right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I was very hesitant to go through the same experience again with my new Nook.
I like the hardware and user experience of the new one. It&amp;rsquo;s light, it&amp;rsquo;s a good
size, it has great battery life, and it&amp;rsquo;s powerful enough (mostly). What if I
ended up with a glitchy OS again, or problems with apps?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Trying Less Drastic Measures&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To mitigate this risk, first I tried a couple of alternatives. One was to
install a custom home screen via the Nova Launcher app, instead of the Nook home
screen. This let me get rid of the large, ugly area where Nook wanted to show me
things I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to buy. Combined with a nice sharp Zen-rocks-and-a-flower
wallpaper, it felt like a much nicer user experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lock screen was still ugly, though. I tried disabling that and replacing it
with another one from the app store, but that never worked very well; I was
unable to really disable the Nook&amp;rsquo;s lock screen, and the new lock screen didn&amp;rsquo;t
work right. The default Nook lock screen is really pretty embarrassing. There&amp;rsquo;s
a high-resolution screen on the device and the lock screen looks like it was
made for a low-res device. I&amp;rsquo;m nitpicking, but my point is you can skin some of
the Nook, but not all of it, so the user interface still feels cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were other minor problems&amp;mdash;clearly the Nook OS is based on an old version
of Android. Fast task switching (and task killing) aren&amp;rsquo;t possible.  There&amp;rsquo;s
also lots of little annoyances like having apps pop up messages &amp;ldquo;Syncing Your
Library&amp;rdquo; while watching a movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two major problems remained. One was the bloatware installed on the Nook,
including the Nook app store that irritatingly kept overwriting versions of apps
installed from the Google Play store. More serious, though, was the app
instability. Gmail was unusable for a couple of weeks while some bug worked its
way through the release process. Gmail is a big part of why I have the tablet to
begin with. And even after it became usable again, it would crash at random
times. I&amp;rsquo;d be watching a movie and see a pop-up, &amp;ldquo;Unfortunately, Gmail has
stopped.&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;d open the Chrome browser and it would lock up the tablet for 30
seconds and then kill itself. I am not sure if I&amp;rsquo;m right, but I blame this on
the Nook app store and/or the ancient Nook OS, not on Gmail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem was performance. I installed &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.monumentvalleygame.com/&#34;&gt;Monument
Valley&lt;/a&gt; and I love, love, &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; it. It&amp;rsquo;s
just amazing. But the Nook didn&amp;rsquo;t seem quite fast enough. Graphics
stuttered, and there were visual glitches and other artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were some other things&amp;mdash;inability to encrypt the whole device, for
example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So although the skinned device was a lot nicer, it was still starting to wear on
me. And I read online that CyanogenMod solved these problems: clean,
uncluttered; latest version of Android; lots of performance improvements; safety
and privacy improvements over and above even Google&amp;rsquo;s open-source Android
releases; ability to encrypt the whole device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I decided to go for it and install CyanogenMod! But not on &lt;strong&gt;my&lt;/strong&gt; device. I
didn&amp;rsquo;t want to take the chance of wiping it and ending up wishing I hadn&amp;rsquo;t.
When I bought my first Nook HD+ 9-inch tablet, they were selling for $175 or so,
and $100 or so refurbished on eBay. Now they&amp;rsquo;re discontinued, and eBay is the
best place to buy one. I got a practically brand-new one for $109 including
shipping. &lt;strong&gt;This&lt;/strong&gt; device would be my sandbox. And if I liked it, well, I have a
gift idea for what to do with the extra one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Installing CyanogenMod On The Nook HD+ 9-Inch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Installing CyanogenMod is really quite easy. The online forums are
super-confusing, though. That&amp;rsquo;s the hard part. All the instructions seem to
cater to someone who already knows what they&amp;rsquo;re doing, or they&amp;rsquo;re written in a
spastic style that is impossible to understand. In many cases they just plain
don&amp;rsquo;t work; they are written by people who are speculating/extrapolating and
haven&amp;rsquo;t done it themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;m going to walk you through it plain and simple. I&amp;rsquo;ll follow the
instructions on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.cyanogenmod.org/w/Ovation_Info&#34;&gt;CyanogenMod Wiki for the Nook
HD+&lt;/a&gt; and the corresponding
&lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.cyanogenmod.org/w/Install_CM_for_ovation&#34;&gt;installation
instructions&lt;/a&gt; with some
clarifications and extra details. A lot is missing or assumed there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What To Know&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some terminology, in case you encounter it on the Internet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CM = CyanogenMod, the operating system you&amp;rsquo;ll install on the tablet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CWM = ClockworkMod, a &amp;ldquo;recovery&amp;rdquo; system for installing new software&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gapps = Google Apps, the Google-branded Android ecosystem apps including the Google Play store (not at all related to Google&amp;rsquo;s office and productivity suite for businesses)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;adb = the Android debug bridge, software you&amp;rsquo;ll use to communicate with the Nook when it is booted into recovery mode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What You&amp;rsquo;ll Do&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re going to follow these steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download CyanogenMod, Google Apps, and adb&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download ClockworkMod and make a bootable SD card with it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boot the Nook to the ClockworkMod recovery operating system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the Android Debugger to transfer CyanogenMod and Google Apps to the Nook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use ClockworkMod to install these two onto the Nook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What You&amp;rsquo;ll Need&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A computer with USB and an SD card reader&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A micro-SD card and an adapter for using it in a full-size SD card reader. Mine is 2GB, but you won&amp;rsquo;t go wrong if you use a larger one&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A fully charged Nook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What To Download&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to download some things before you start. Don&amp;rsquo;t unzip these files, just
download them. Don&amp;rsquo;t put them onto the SD card. Just keep them on your computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CyanogenMod: the Nook HD+ is code-named &amp;ldquo;ovation&amp;rdquo;. Get the &lt;a href=&#34;http://download.cyanogenmod.org/?type=snapshot&amp;amp;device=ovation&#34;&gt;latest ovation
snapshot build&lt;/a&gt;
and download it to your computer. Make a note of the CyanogenMod version you
download. I downloaded the following file just now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cm-11-20141112-SNAPSHOT-M12-ovation.zip
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is CyanogenMod version 11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Apps: you&amp;rsquo;ll want the proprietary Google Apps, which will give you access
to the Google Play store and so on. Download them from this link:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.cyanogenmod.org/w/Gapps&#34;&gt;http://wiki.cyanogenmod.org/w/Gapps&lt;/a&gt; Choose the correct version of them for your
OS, in my case for CyanogenMod (CM) version 11. I downloaded this file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;gapps-kk-20140606-signed.zip
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ClockworkMod: any version that is built for the Nook HD+. This is the sketchiest
part of the process, because you typically have to hunt around for something
built by someone and just linked into a forum thread. You don&amp;rsquo;t need the latest
and greatest, you just need something that&amp;rsquo;ll boot up from a micro SD card. I
downloaded &lt;code&gt;NookHDplus-CWM-6046-for-internal-memory-rev0-(07-13-14).zip&lt;/code&gt; from
&lt;a href=&#34;http://forum.xda-developers.com/showpost.php?p=42406126&amp;amp;postcount=7&#34;&gt;this XDA
thread&lt;/a&gt; and
found it to work fine. Download this to your computer as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Making A Bootable Micro SD Card&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason, the online instructions all do this simple task in bizarre
ways. I think a part of that may be due to people using Windows, which doesn&amp;rsquo;t
have the &lt;code&gt;dd&lt;/code&gt; command. If you use Windows, you may need to download a bunch of
stuff as instructed on the XDA thread I just linked to. But if you use a
Unix-based OS, you can just put your SD card into your computer and copy the
recovery image onto it with &lt;code&gt;dd&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll need to make sure the SD card device is unmounted, and figure out what the
device&amp;rsquo;s Unix path is. I assume you can do that without my help. On my Mac, the
device was &lt;code&gt;/dev/disk2&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, unzip the ClockworkMod file, and &lt;code&gt;dd&lt;/code&gt; the &lt;code&gt;recovery.img&lt;/code&gt; onto the device, e.g.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo dd bs=4m if=recovery.img of=/dev/your/device/here
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will take a few minutes to complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you have a card that you can put into the Nook&amp;rsquo;s card reader and boot it up.
Instead of booting up to the Nook OS, it will boot up to the &amp;ldquo;recovery mode&amp;rdquo;
operating system on the card. Try it. You should see the Nook splash screen for
a second or two, then a Cyanoboot logo will appear:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2015/01/cyanoboot.png&#34; alt=&#34;cyanoboot&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A moment later you should see a menu with options to do some basic operations&amp;mdash;reboot,
install, backup, and so on. If this doesn&amp;rsquo;t work, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to
re-read, perhaps read online info&amp;hellip; keep working until you get it. It worked
the first time for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use the volume keys to highlight the desired menu item, the Nook&amp;rsquo;s home button (the
N button) to select/OK the highlighted item, and the power button to go back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that, instead of following the confused and contradictory instructions
online about copying various files to this bootable SD card, and whether that
will or won&amp;rsquo;t work and in what order you have to do it, we are only putting the
&lt;code&gt;recovery.img&lt;/code&gt; file onto it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make A Backup&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have the Nook booted into recovery mode on the SD card, you need to
make a backup. Use the volume keys to go to &amp;ldquo;backup and restore&amp;rdquo; and choose
&amp;ldquo;backup to /sdcard&amp;rdquo; and let this run. It may take a while. This will be your
backup in case you want to restore the stock Nook OS and all your data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this is working, move on to the next step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Install the Android Debug Bridge&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Android debug bridge (adb) software lets you connect your computer to the Nook
when it&amp;rsquo;s booted into recovery mode. We&amp;rsquo;ll use it to copy the necessary files to
the Nook&amp;rsquo;s internal storage and then to install these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow the instructions on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.cyanogenmod.org/w/Adb&#34;&gt;CyanogenMod
Wiki&lt;/a&gt; to install adb. Please read the
instructions carefully. You basically need to download some software, unzip it,
execute it, and in the menu that appears, select a fairly minimal set of tools
to install. The initial install isn&amp;rsquo;t the full suite of software, it&amp;rsquo;s just an
installer you use to get the stuff you really need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t need to really &amp;ldquo;install&amp;rdquo; the software on your computer, it&amp;rsquo;s more a
matter of downloading. For example,
I did not modify my computer&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;$PATH&lt;/code&gt; variable to put &lt;code&gt;adb&lt;/code&gt; into my path. I
just opened a terminal and executed &lt;code&gt;./platform-tools/adb &amp;lt;options&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; to do what
I needed. Afterwards I deleted the directory from my downloads folder and my
computer is clean and unaltered, with nothing &amp;ldquo;installed.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wipe The Nook&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presumably your Nook&amp;rsquo;s backup has finished now. Next,
you have to completely reset the Nook. You can&amp;rsquo;t install CyanogenMod onto a Nook
that hasn&amp;rsquo;t been reset. I don&amp;rsquo;t quite understand why, but the installation
process failed for me (and others online) until a factory reset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t use the factory reset in the Nook itself. Use the reset function built
into your bootable ClockworkMod disk. Select &lt;strong&gt;wipe data/factory reset&lt;/strong&gt; and let
it run. It should only take a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mount The Nook&amp;rsquo;s Internal Storage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to mount the Nook&amp;rsquo;s internal storage (often referred to as &amp;ldquo;sdcard&amp;rdquo;
although it is not really a card) so you can copy the files you&amp;rsquo;re going to
install. Navigate back to the main menu and select &lt;strong&gt;mounts and storage&lt;/strong&gt;, then
&lt;strong&gt;mount /data&lt;/strong&gt;. For some reason ClockworkMod refers to it under different
names, but this is the correct thing to mount on the Nook HD+.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Copy CyanogenMod and Google Apps to the Nook&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a couple ways to install software onto the Nook. I tried the
&amp;ldquo;sideload&amp;rdquo; method mentioned in the CyanogenMod wiki&amp;rsquo;s instructions, but it
didn&amp;rsquo;t work. The &amp;ldquo;push and install&amp;rdquo; method worked, so that&amp;rsquo;s what I&amp;rsquo;ll document
here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remove the USB cable from the Nook power charger and plug it into your computer.
Your computer is now connected via USB to the Nook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you can use the &lt;code&gt;adb push&lt;/code&gt; tool to copy the downloaded software from your
computer to the Nook, and tell the Nook to store the zip files in &lt;code&gt;/sdcard&lt;/code&gt;/,
which is the storage you just mounted on the Nook. In my case, it looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~/Downloads/android-sdk-macosx/platform-tools/adb push ~/Downloads/cm-11-20141112-SNAPSHOT-M12-ovation.zip /sdcard/
~/Downloads/android-sdk-macosx/platform-tools/adb push ~/Downloads/gapps-kk-20140606-signed.zip /sdcard/
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These take a few moments to transfer. When I did it, they took about 55 and 40 seconds,
respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Install The New Software&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you&amp;rsquo;re ready to take the plunge! On the Nook, use the power button to return
to the main menu, and select &lt;strong&gt;install zip&lt;/strong&gt;, then &lt;strong&gt;install zip from /sdcard&lt;/strong&gt;.
Select the CyanogenMod zip file and install it, then the Google Apps (gapps) zip
file and install that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t see the files: reboot the Nook and try the transfer again. I have
gone through this process a couple of times and had the transfer appear to
succeed (but the files never appeared in the ClockworkMod menu), then when I
rebooted the Nook and tried again, it worked fine. I believe it was a problem
mounting the &lt;code&gt;/sdcard&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After installing: Reboot. You&amp;rsquo;re done. First boot will take a minute or two;
you&amp;rsquo;ll be presented with a setup menu after that. Subsequent boots will take about 20 seconds in my experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of installing CyanogenMod onto an Android device is a bit like
buying a computer with Windows and replacing it with Linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus far, I have noticed the following results from using my freshly installed
CyanogenMod operating system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is faster and graphics are noticeably better. No glitches or visual
artifacts in Monument Valley, for example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All the Nook-specific annoyances are gone, naturally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hulu&amp;rsquo;s app wouldn&amp;rsquo;t install, saying &amp;ldquo;Your device isn&amp;rsquo;t compatible with this
version.&amp;rdquo; Too bad; with the stock Nook OS, it installed OK. Not that I ever
used it, but it installed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No problems with Netflix, Spotify, Pandora, and lots and lots of other apps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I discovered things I didn&amp;rsquo;t even know about my Nook&amp;rsquo;s hardware. For example,
I thought it didn&amp;rsquo;t have a microphone. With the newer version of Android
that&amp;rsquo;s installed now, the Google Now &amp;ldquo;OK Google&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; instructions work fine.
It hears and recognizes my voice! Mind blown!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having a clean, uncluttered tablet OS is so nice!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Full-device encryption doesn&amp;rsquo;t do anything. It shows an Android logo, but no
progress bar or other feedback. I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize it was stuck until I got
suspicious after 10 hours or so, checked online, and found that this is
apparently a known problem. Alas, I still cannot take this device out of my
house or put any sensitive data on it, because &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/12/18/secure-your-accounts-and-devices/&#34;&gt;it is not secure
enough&lt;/a&gt; for me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, I&amp;rsquo;m loving it as a tablet to use around the home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I leave you with this precious gift from Ida, the protagonist in Monument Valley. You&amp;rsquo;re welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2015/01/ida-flower.png&#34; alt=&#34;Ida and the Flower&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Barnes and Noble Nook HD&#43;</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/03/01/barnes-noble-nook-hd/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Mar 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/03/01/barnes-noble-nook-hd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I consider myself a very slow adopter with regard to tablets. I&amp;rsquo;m too picky. I
think the iPad is inconveniently large, and there are a lot of devices that have
the same screen size, which eliminated many of the popular ones from my
consideration. Many of the devices out there are 7-inch screens, and that&amp;rsquo;s too
&lt;em&gt;small&lt;/em&gt;.  A while ago I &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2011/06/04/using-the-nook-color-as-a-full-featured-android-tablet/&#34;&gt;tried&lt;/a&gt; using a 7-inch device but after a while I
stopped using it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After seeing and holding a lot of tablets, I decided that somewhere between 8
and 9 inches is the right size. It may seem like nitpicking, but the screen size
is diagonal. That means that there is a big difference between 8-inch tablets
and 9-inch tablets. There&amp;rsquo;s even more difference when you get out of this range.
The area of a 10-inch device&amp;rsquo;s screen is twice as large as a 7-inch, for
example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t want an iPad Mini even though hardware-wise it seems like the pinnacle
of tablet design and is just the right size in my opinion. I think the Apple app
ecosystem is too closed and there&amp;rsquo;s more interesting stuff going on in the
Android world. I also think the price is ridiculous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other potential contenders in the size range I wanted were also mostly very
expensive, such as some of the Samsung devices. I&amp;rsquo;d love a Google Nexus tablet if it were offered in a size I want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been using a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.barnesandnoble.com/p/nook-hd-plus-barnes-noble/1110060512&#34;&gt;Nook Color HD+&lt;/a&gt; for many months now, and unlike my 7-inch
Nook, I &lt;em&gt;actually use it&lt;/em&gt; on a regular basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2014/03/nook.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Nook&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought the Nook HD+ because it seemed like the best deal in midsize tablets.
I got it refurbished for just over $100, via the official refurbished reseller
on eBay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have left the stock operating system on it. I don&amp;rsquo;t really care enough to
customize it. It&amp;rsquo;s fine as it is. Okay, the home screen is not really laid out
the way I would do it, but that&amp;rsquo;s fine, I don&amp;rsquo;t mind. It also comes with some
Nook versions of some apps. These are fine too. Some of the games are even fun.
Some of the apps have upgraded themselves with newer versions from the Google
Play store, and it always notifies me about this.  I would also like to be able
to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/12/18/secure-your-accounts-and-devices/&#34;&gt;enable full-device encryption&lt;/a&gt;, but I can&amp;rsquo;t (so I don&amp;rsquo;t take it out of
the house). Whatever &amp;ndash; these are minor things. Mostly, it&amp;rsquo;s just fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size, weight, and battery life are excellent. It is on the large end of the
scale but it&amp;rsquo;s nice and light, and lasts a long time on battery power. I
remember one of the reasons I didn&amp;rsquo;t end up &lt;em&gt;using&lt;/em&gt; my smaller Nook previously
was battery life. It seemed like everytime I wanted to pick it up and use it,
the battery was dead, so I never &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; use it. That&amp;rsquo;s not the case with this
newer device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The screen is not as gorgeous as the reviews claim. Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s because mine is
refurbished, but there&amp;rsquo;s a noticeable brightness gradient at one edge. I don&amp;rsquo;t
care, but you might. Otherwise, I agree, it&amp;rsquo;s a nice screen. Very high-res, good
refresh rate. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t flicker like the older one I had. This is important if
you&amp;rsquo;ll read on the device. Even if you don&amp;rsquo;t notice micro-flickering, your eyes
will be strained as they move back and forth across the device. Quick test: move
your hand between your eyes and the screen while you keep your eyes still. Does
the edge of your hand look jagged, with a strobing effect? Don&amp;rsquo;t buy devices
that do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The device is also not overly powerful. But I don&amp;rsquo;t need a lot of power. I don&amp;rsquo;t
care that it takes a second to load an app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve had my Nook HD+ 9-inch tablet for 4 months today and I&amp;rsquo;m still enjoying and
using it regularly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A review of Bose, Sony, and Sennheiser noise-cancelling headphones</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/01/16/bose-sennheiser-sony-noise-cancelling-headphones/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/01/16/bose-sennheiser-sony-noise-cancelling-headphones/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve used active noise-cancelling headphones for over ten years now, and have owned several pairs of Bose, one of Sony, and most recently a pair of Sennheiser headphones. The Sennheisers are my favorites. I thought I&amp;rsquo;d write down why I&amp;rsquo;ve gone through so many sets of cans and what I like and dislike about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Bose-QuietComfort-Acoustic-Cancelling-Headphones/dp/B0054JJ0QW/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Bose QuietComfort 15 Acoustic Noise Cancelling Headphones&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2014/01/bose-quiet-comfort.png&#34; alt=&#34;Bose QuietComfort 15 Acoustic Noise Cancelling Headphones&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sure you&amp;rsquo;re familiar with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Bose-QuietComfort-Acoustic-Cancelling-Headphones/dp/B0054JJ0QW/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Bose QuietComfort&lt;/a&gt; headphones. They&amp;rsquo;re the iconic &amp;ldquo;best-in-class&amp;rdquo; noise-cancelling headphones, the ones you see everywhere. Yet, after owning several pairs (beginning with Quiet Comfort II in 2003), I decided I&amp;rsquo;m not happy with them and won&amp;rsquo;t buy them anymore. Why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re not very good quality. I&amp;rsquo;ve worn out two pairs and opted to sell the third pair that Bose sent me as a replacement. Various problems occurred, including torn speakers that buzzed and grated. I just got tired of sending them back to Bose for servicing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re more expensive than I think they&amp;rsquo;re worth, especially given the cheap components used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They don&amp;rsquo;t sound bad &amp;ndash; but to my ears they still have the classic Bose fairy-dust processing, which sounds rich and pleasant at first but then fatigues me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They produce a sensation of suction on the eardrums that becomes uncomfortable over long periods of time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They can&amp;rsquo;t be used in non-cancelling mode. In other words, if the battery is dead, they&amp;rsquo;re unusable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On a purely personal note, I think Bose crosses the line into greed and jealousy. I know this in part because I used to work at Crutchfield, and saw quite a bit of interactions with Bose. As an individual &amp;ndash; well, try selling a pair of these on eBay, and you&amp;rsquo;ll see what I mean. I had to jump through all kinds of hoops after my first listing was cancelled for using a stock photo that eBay themselves suggested and provided in the listing wizard. &lt;a href=&#34;http://cgi3.ebay.com/ws/eBayISAPI.dll?ViewUserPage&amp;amp;userid=Bosetracker&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is the information the take-down notice directed me to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, the fit is very comfortable physically, they cancel noise very well, and they&amp;rsquo;re smaller than some other noise-cancelling headphones. Also on the plus side, every time I&amp;rsquo;ve sent a pair in for servicing, Bose has just charged me $100 and sent me a new pair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Sony-Canceling-Stereo-Headphones-MDR-NC200D/dp/B005LA53BK/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Sony MDR-NC200D&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2014/01/sony-mdr-nc200d.png&#34; alt=&#34;Sony MDR-NC200D&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I sent my last pair of Bose in for servicing, they replaced them with a factory-sealed pair of new ones in the box, and I decided to sell them on eBay and buy a set of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Sony-Canceling-Stereo-Headphones-MDR-NC200D/dp/B005LA53BK/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Sony MDR-NC200D&lt;/a&gt; headphones, which were about $100 less money than new Bose headphones at the time. I read online reviews and thought it was worth a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the good points. The Sonys are more compact even than the Bose, although as I recall they&amp;rsquo;re a little heavier. And the noise cancellation works quite well. The passive noise blocking (muffling) is in itself quite good. You can just put them on without even turning on the switch, and block a lot of ambient noise. The sound quality is also quite good, although there is a slight hiss when noise cancellation is enabled. Active cancellation is good, but not as good as the Bose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t long before I realized I couldn&amp;rsquo;t keep them. The Sonys sit on the ear, and don&amp;rsquo;t enclose the ear and sit against the skull as the Bose do. They&amp;rsquo;re on-the-ear, not over-the-ear. Although this doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel bad at first, in about 20 minutes it starts to hurt. After half an hour it&amp;rsquo;s genuinely painful. This may not be your experience, but my ears just start to hurt after being pressed against my head for a little while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to sell the Sonys on eBay too. My last stop was the Sennheisers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Sennheiser-PXC-450-Noise-Canceling-Headphones/dp/B000R2PC2M/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Sennheiser PXC 450 NoiseGard Active Noise-Canceling Headphones&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2014/01/sennheiser-pxc-450.png&#34; alt=&#34;Sennheiser PXC 450 NoiseGard Active Noise-Canceling Headphones&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Sennheiser-PXC-450-Noise-Canceling-Headphones/dp/B000R2PC2M/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Sennheiser PXC 450&lt;/a&gt; headphones are midway in price between the Bose and the Sony: a little less expensive than the Bose. I&amp;rsquo;ve had them a week or so and I&amp;rsquo;m very happy with them so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not the first pair of Sennheisers I&amp;rsquo;ve owned. I&amp;rsquo;ve had a pair of open-air higher-end Sennheisers for over a decade. I absolutely love them, so you can consider me a Sennheiser snob to some extent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m pleased to report that the PXC 450s are Sennheisers through and through. They have amazing sound, and the big cups fit comfortably around my ears. They are a little heavier than my other Sennheisers, but still a pleasure to wear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nice thing is that not only does noise cancellation work very well (on par with Bose&amp;rsquo;s, I&amp;rsquo;d say), but there is no sensation of being underwater with pressure or suction on the eardrums. Turn on the noise cancellation switch and the noise just vanishes, but there&amp;rsquo;s no strange feeling as a result. Also, these headphones can work in passive mode, with noise cancellation off, and don&amp;rsquo;t need a battery to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the downside, if you want to travel with them, they&amp;rsquo;re a little bigger than the Bose. However I&amp;rsquo;ve travelled with the Bose headphones several times and honestly I find even them too large to be convenient. I don&amp;rsquo;t use noise-cancelling headphones for travel, as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another slight downside is that the earcups aren&amp;rsquo;t completely &amp;ldquo;empty&amp;rdquo; inside. There are some caged-over protrusions with the machinery inside. Depending on the shape of your ears, these might brush your ears if you move your head. I find that if I don&amp;rsquo;t place the headphones in the right spot on my head, they do touch my ears every now and then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After owning several pairs of top-rated noise-cancelling headphones, I think the Sennheisers are the clear winners in price, quality, comfort, and sound. Your mileage may vary.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More Notebooks and Journals!</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/10/13/more-notebooks-and-journals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/10/13/more-notebooks-and-journals/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Something interesting happened after I published my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/10/ultimate-notebook-and-journal-face-off/&#34; title=&#34;Ultimate notebook and journal face-off&#34;&gt;ultimate notebook and journal face-off&lt;/a&gt; blog post a couple of months ago. I received an email from a company called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grandluxe.com/online-store.html&#34;&gt;Grandluxe&lt;/a&gt;, asking if I&amp;rsquo;d like to receive some stationery products in hopes that if I liked them, I&amp;rsquo;d write a review on them. I had never heard of them before, but they&amp;rsquo;ve been making paper products for 68 years, and apparently are trying to break out of the Asian market into international territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agreed, and they sent me quite a large box of notebooks. They also sent me their full product line catalog. So you could say that, as a notebook nerd, I&amp;rsquo;m in heaven!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like the products. (I&amp;rsquo;ve already disclosed my bias. But I&amp;rsquo;ll do it again. I was given these free of charge.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Monologue Ruled Notebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They sent me an entire set of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grandluxe.com/index.php/online-store/monologue-ruled-note-book-a5.html&#34;&gt;Monologue&lt;/a&gt; ruled notebook in A5 size, assorted attractive colors. It is very similar to a Moleskine-class notebook. It has a slightly softer and more &amp;ldquo;grippy&amp;rdquo; cover, but otherwise there&amp;rsquo;s little difference. I had enough to give one to my wife, to each of my coworkers, and keep the prettiest color for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/10/ruled-note-book.png&#34; alt=&#34;ruled-note-book&#34; width=&#34;587&#34; height=&#34;279&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-3277&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Mythology Notebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I received three small (A6) and one A5 in this product line. The paper is a little smoother and the edges are gilded in gold and silver colors. The covers are charcoal black with silvery/goldish undertones. They are hard and stiff, not soft and flexible like the Monologue, and have a knurled or bumpy feel. The spine is embossed with the product name in gilding to match the edge of the sheets. The A5 has a pseudo-reptile-skin pattern on the binding. These would make a great gift or promotional item, because they look really sophisticated. Note that the colors in the image below are a little exaggerated; in reality the gold/silver tones are more subtle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/10/mythology.png&#34; alt=&#34;mythology&#34; width=&#34;425&#34; height=&#34;425&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-3278&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This item doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to be available on their online store yet, but you can find more details and images &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grandluxe.com/notebooks-journals.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Monolette Notebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a slim notebook with a flexible cover (thick paper, not rigid at all) that comes in combination packs. Each pack has one ruled notebook and one blank notebook with perforated pages for easy tear-out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/10/monolette.png&#34; alt=&#34;monolette&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; height=&#34;600&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-3279&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This item doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to be available on their online store yet, but you can find more details and images &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grandluxe.com/notebooks-journals.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;Bullet Journaling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently stumbled on an interesting system of journaling / note-taking called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bulletjournal.com/&#34;&gt;Bullet Journal&lt;/a&gt;. Although it&amp;rsquo;s a little bit over-the-top in some ways, and sometimes feels like being told the obvious or told to follow a system that seems unlikely to hold together in the &amp;ldquo;real world,&amp;rdquo; it is fun to see that other people enjoy taking notes on paper as much as I do. Worth a read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bulletjournal.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/10/bullet-journal-300x106.png&#34; alt=&#34;bullet-journal&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;106&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3281&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_4&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an embarrassment of riches to choose from when it comes to journals and notebooks, and my bookshelf is stockpiled with a couple of years&amp;rsquo; worth now that I&amp;rsquo;ve done this epic series. But in today&amp;rsquo;s digital world, can you ever get too much of good old paper and pen? Enjoy the simpler pleasures&amp;hellip; I hope this blog has helped with that a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using the Nook Color as a full-featured Android tablet</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2011/06/04/using-the-nook-color-as-a-full-featured-android-tablet/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2011 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2011/06/04/using-the-nook-color-as-a-full-featured-android-tablet/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I bought a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Barnes-Noble-Color-eBook-Tablet/dp/1400532655/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Barnes and Noble Nook Color&lt;/a&gt; e-book reader and ripped out the Nook software, replacing it with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cyanogenmod.com/&#34;&gt;CyanogenMod&lt;/a&gt; distribution of the Android OS. It&amp;rsquo;s really, really nice hardware, and CyanogenMod (CM) is really, really nice software. I love them both, and my regular readers will remember that I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;em&gt;not a gadget guy&lt;/em&gt;. Read on for more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never thought I&amp;rsquo;d get a tablet, until my phone died and I got a Droid 2 as a replacement. With all those gadgets, I just started to find myself using my phone for reading my RSS feeds and so on &amp;ndash; but hating how small the screen was. I started to think again about a tablet after experiencing how handy the smartphone&amp;rsquo;s extra features are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;The Nook Color Hardware&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Nook Color is a medium-sized Android tablet with a screen that&amp;rsquo;s the same size as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Samsung-Galaxy-Tab-AT-T/dp/B004CYEQF0/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Samsung Galaxy Tab&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s a perfect size for carrying around &amp;ndash; much better than iPads and Xooms and so on, which are just too big for my taste. This device literally fits in the pocket of my jeans (&lt;a href=&#34;https://nookdeveloper.barnesandnoble.com/product/nook-color-specs.html&#34;&gt;specs&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The screen is amazing. It&amp;rsquo;s super sharp. But the Nook Color doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a microphone or a camera, and it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have any phone service. This is fine. I don&amp;rsquo;t want these items. I want a tablet to use primarily at home for consuming content such as blogs, books, newspapers, music, movies, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best parts: 1) it&amp;rsquo;s way cheaper than a Galaxy Tab or similar tablets. It&amp;rsquo;s $250 at the store. And 2) it&amp;rsquo;s really easy to take off the stripped-down version of Android that comes with it, and put something better on it. Which brings me to my next point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;The Software&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you unpack the box, the Nook has a pretty nice little e-reader installed, with a simplified Android interface. It has limited functionality, which is fine. It does have a web browser and a couple other things, and BN recently added their own application store. But it&amp;rsquo;s really kind of lame. You can only get a small fraction of the apps that you could get through the Android Market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I updated to CyanogenMod in two stages. First, I simply rooted the device and made it possible to install arbitrary apps from the Android Market. There&amp;rsquo;s a nice, easy process to do this. It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;a href=&#34;http://forum.xda-developers.com/showpost.php?p=13270739&amp;amp;#038;postcount=1&#34;&gt;Manual Nooter&lt;/a&gt;. I tried this first instead of just going to CyanogenMod because I wanted to see what it was like. It was okay, but it was really obvious that it was a sort of layer on top of the underlying Nook. Pressing the Home button, for example, brought up a prompt to use the Nook home screen or the hijacked home screen for the new software. I tinkered around with this for a while, enough to determine that I didn&amp;rsquo;t like the patched look and feel. At the same time, I learned that the applications I wanted would work just fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I moved on to CyanogenMod. Early reviews I&amp;rsquo;d read of this said it wasn&amp;rsquo;t ready for prime time on the Nook, but the newer updates seemed to be well received. So I backed up everything and took the plunge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s really ridiculously easy to install CyanogenMod on the Nook, even easier if you don&amp;rsquo;t first update your Nook operating system. It took me longer to burn a bootable ROM on a MicroSD card than anything else. Full instructions can be found beginning at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cyanogenmod.com/devices/nook-color&#34;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is just brilliant. I&amp;rsquo;ve now installed my preferred apps, stripped down the interface by removing some stuff I don&amp;rsquo;t want, such as multiple desktops (CyanogenMod is jammed with features), and I have a simple, elegant, perfectly functioning Android tablet. And I really mean it &amp;ndash; there are no rough edges or crashes or anything you might expect from a third-party OS on your tablet. In fact, one of the things I like the most is that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t come with pre-installed adware, as my Droid did (and the stuff on the Droid can&amp;rsquo;t be uninstalled without rooting it and voiding the warranty, which is not something I&amp;rsquo;m going to do on my work phone).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want a small, light, thin tablet with WiFi that you can hold in one hand for reading books and newspapers and so on, which is easy to put in a pocket or purse and carry with you, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t cost much, then consider the Nook Color. If you want to turn it into something much more full-featured, then consider ripping out the Nook software and replacing it with CyanogenMod. The result is really superb.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I hacked the HP Media Vault to support OGG and FLAC files</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/08/02/how-i-hacked-the-hp-media-vault-to-support-ogg-and-flac-files/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2008 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2008/08/02/how-i-hacked-the-hp-media-vault-to-support-ogg-and-flac-files/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Let me begin by saying &amp;ldquo;I am so not a gadget guy.&amp;rdquo; I don&amp;rsquo;t have an iPhone. Heck, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a cellphone at all until April when I joined Percona as a consultant. I don&amp;rsquo;t ooh and aah over other people&amp;rsquo;s gadgets most of the time. I don&amp;rsquo;t have, you know, that kind of envy. I&amp;rsquo;m sure you see where this is going: I got a gadget and I think it&amp;rsquo;s really cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, my wife and I have a bunch of computers (desktops and laptops) and we had been feeling the pain for a long time: the files were only on one computer, and we wanted them available. I built a file server and then realized that it was going to be really expensive in terms of power alone, so I went back to USB drives for backups, and kept thinking about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0015313O8?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;&lt;img border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2008/08/HPMediaVault.jpg&#34; width=&#34;160&#34; height=&#34;160&#34; alt=&#34;HP Media Vault&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a long time I decided to buy an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0015313O8?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;HP Media Vault&lt;/a&gt; and install ultra-low-power, oversized disks in it &amp;ndash; I did that, and will write about it elsewhere. And then I discovered that it has a media server in it. And not being a gadget guy, I had honestly never heard about these things before. Really. I read up on it a little bit and decided hell, sharing files is nice, but I have about a thousand CDs that could go on this thing, and my wife has hundreds too. That&amp;rsquo;s even better than file sharing! I copied the music from her iTunes library to the shared Music folder on the server and boom, Rhythmbox magically saw it all. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t believe I&amp;rsquo;d never heard about this before. Best thing since sliced bread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I even had all my music ripped already to my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2005/10/05/review-of-the-iriver-hd340/&#34;&gt;iRiver HD340&lt;/a&gt;. In OGG format. And then I found out the HP Media Vault doesn&amp;rsquo;t support OGG format. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0093779/&#34;&gt;Boo! Boo! Rubbish! Filth! Slime!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I fixed that. Now I&amp;rsquo;ll show you how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you try what&amp;rsquo;s on this page and something breaks, it is your fault, not mine. I make this information available without any warranties or representations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;The basics: log into the server&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The HP documentation for the Media Vault is totally incomplete and assumes you want to install their GUI program and control the thing from your Windows desktop. There&amp;rsquo;s a much better way. The Media Vault has a full-featured web interface. Log into the web console. I&amp;rsquo;m going to assume that your HP Media Vault&amp;rsquo;s DNS name is hpmediavault, so you can &lt;a href=&#34;http://hpmediavault/&#34;&gt;log into it with this URL&lt;/a&gt;. Once you do, set the admin password to secure the server. Remember it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next fun thing: the server runs GNU/Linux and has SSH enabled by default. Yes, that&amp;rsquo;s right: you can just SSH into the thing! The password you set in the previous step is now your SSH password. Your SSH username is root, no matter what you set the admin username to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, open up a terminal and SSH right in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;ssh root@hpmediavault&lt;/pre&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;Type the password you chose in the previous step. You should see the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;baron@kanga:~$ ssh root@hpmediavault
root@hpmediavault&#39;s password: 


BusyBox v1.01 (2008.02.08-22:41+0000) Built-in shell (ash)
Enter &#39;help&#39; for a list of built-in commands.

-sh: can&#39;t access tty; job control turned off
# 
&lt;/pre&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the server runs with a stripped-down set of command-line tools called BusyBox. You&amp;rsquo;re golden. Let&amp;rsquo;s get working on installing OGG and FLAC support. This will not be hard at all if you can use a command-line editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Step 1: install ipkg&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behind the scenes, the Media Vault&amp;rsquo;s media streaming is provided by &lt;a href=&#34;http://fireflymediaserver.org/&#34;&gt;Firefly&lt;/a&gt;, formerly known as mt-daapd (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_Audio_Access_Protocol&#34;&gt;DAAP&lt;/a&gt; is the iTunes server protocol). This is a Free Software media server, and it&amp;rsquo;s highly capable. But the version that ships on the device is old and doesn&amp;rsquo;t support OGG. You&amp;rsquo;re going to fix that by installing a newer version. But first, you have to install a package management system that will install the newest Firefly software for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The package management system is &lt;a href=&#34;http://handhelds.org/moin/moin.cgi/Ipkg&#34;&gt;ipkg, the Itsy Package Management System&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s really easy to install. First, let&amp;rsquo;s see where your hard drives are mounted:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;# mount
/dev/md6 on /share/1000 type ext3 (data=writeback)
&lt;/pre&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;If yours isn&amp;rsquo;t /share/1000, use a different value in the following commands. Now you want to make an installation directory and change to that directory:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;# mkdir -p /share/1000/tmp &amp;#038;&amp;#038; cd /share/1000/tmp&lt;/pre&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;rsquo;s find the installation image to download. Go look here for the latest version of the image:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ipkg.nslu2-linux.org/feeds/optware/cs05q3armel/cross/unstable/&#34;&gt;http://ipkg.nslu2-linux.org/feeds/optware/cs05q3armel/cross/unstable/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Search for &amp;ldquo;hpmv2-bootstrap&amp;rdquo; on that page. You should find a file something like this: hpmv2-bootstrap_1.2-4_arm.xsh. Copy the link location for that, and go back to your command prompt. Now download the file to the Media Vault, substituting the correct URL into the command below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
# wget http://ipkg.nslu2-linux.org/feeds/optware/cs05q3armel/cross/unstable/hpmv2-bootstrap_1.2-4_arm.xsh
&lt;/pre&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;And now, just execute it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;# sh ./hpmv2-bootstrap_1.2-4_arm.xsh&lt;/pre&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;You should see &amp;ldquo;Setup complete&amp;rdquo; when it&amp;rsquo;s done. That&amp;rsquo;s it. It installs itself and mounts the installation directory as /opt, which is where all your software will appear in the future. This will persist after a reboot. You can see the changes with the mount command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;# mount
/dev/md6 on /share/1000 type ext3 (data=writeback)
/share/1000/.optware on /opt type ext3 (rw)
&lt;/pre&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;Before you move on, update its cache of available software:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;# ipkg update&lt;/pre&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;I got this installation procedure from &lt;a href=&#34;http://tech.groups.yahoo.com/group/hackingthemediavault/message/259&#34;&gt;the Yahoo group on hacking the Media Vault&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;Step 2: Install Firefly Nightly&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to determine whether the latest stable Firefly release has OGG streaming enabled, so I installed the latest nightly release. At some point in the future I&amp;rsquo;m sure a stable release will have it, but I breathed a prayer to Saint Hewlett and installed the nightly, following &lt;a href=&#34;http://tech.groups.yahoo.com/group/hackingthemediavault/message/338&#34;&gt;instructions I also found on Hacking the Media Vault&lt;/a&gt;. Fortunately it seems to work fine for me. Here&amp;rsquo;s how I did it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;# ipkg install mt-daapd-svn&lt;/pre&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;Pretty easy. After you do this, it will download a bunch of things and install them until it says &amp;ldquo;Successfully terminated.&amp;rdquo; Now you need to configure it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably noticed that the installation said &amp;ldquo;To complete this installation, make any necessary changes to the config file in /opt/etc/mt-daapd/mt-daapd.conf, and start the daemon by running /opt/etc/init.d/S60mt-daapd&amp;rdquo;. Here&amp;rsquo;s how to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;# vi /opt/etc/mt-daapd/mt-daapd.conf&lt;/pre&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;If you like a different editor, feel free to use it. I like vi. Here are the lines that you need to change:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
mp3_dir = /share/1000/Music                                            
servername = HPMediaVault                                              
extensions = .mp3,.m4a,.m4p,.ogg,.flac                                 
&lt;/pre&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m assuming you are keeping the defaults, as I did on mine. All my music is in the Music share, I want to keep the same server name (what shows up in iTunes/Rhythmbox), and I want to add .ogg and .flac to the extensions Firefly will index and stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_4&#34;&gt;Step 3: Stop the built-in server, start the new one&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next you need to stop the built-in media server and start the one you just installed. Here&amp;rsquo;s how to see what&amp;rsquo;s running:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;# ps -eaf | grep daap
32530 nobody     1096 S &amp;lt; /usr/sbin/mt-daapd 
32531 nobody     1984 S &amp;lt; /usr/sbin/mt-daapd 
32160 root        488 S   grep daap 
&lt;/pre&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;There are two processes running. This is normal. Let&amp;rsquo;s stop them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;# killall mt-daapd&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you now run the ps command above, you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t see anything running. You can start the new server:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;# /opt/etc/init.d/S60mt-daapd&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you should be able to see the daemon running:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;# ps -eaf | grep daap
32681 nobody     3796 S   /opt/sbin/mt-daapd -c /opt/etc/mt-daapd/mt-daapd.conf
32682 nobody     4512 D   /opt/sbin/mt-daapd -c /opt/etc/mt-daapd/mt-daapd.conf
32703 root        488 S   grep daap 
&lt;/pre&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;Notice that it&amp;rsquo;s a different binary running &amp;ndash; not the one in /usr/sbin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point you ought to be able to start up your favorite music player (iTunes, Rhythmbox) and stream OGG and FLAC files from the media server. Test that before you go on to the next little bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_5&#34;&gt;Step 4: Change which media server starts on boot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s one last little detail. If you shut down your Media Vault and restart it, the old media server will start instead of the new one. The GNU/Linux variant on the Media Vault doesn&amp;rsquo;t have any nice init scripts, so I had to hunt around to find out how to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a bit of poking, I found that the /etc/inc/func_daapd.inc script has the start and stop commands. The startup process for the Media Vault is written in PHP, oddly enough. Here are the relevant lines:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
   144         $ret=mwexec(&#34;/usr/sbin/mt-daapd -k&#34;);
   147         killbyname(&#34;mt-daapd&#34;,&#34;&#34;);
   162         $ret=mwexec(&#34;/usr/sbin/mt-daapd&#34;);
&lt;/pre&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;I commented them out and changed them to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
   143          $ret=mwexec(&#34;/opt/etc/init.d/S60mt-daapd -k&#34;);
   144  #       $ret=mwexec(&#34;/usr/sbin/mt-daapd -k&#34;);
   161          $ret=mwexec(&#34;/opt/etc/init.d/S60mt-daapd&#34;);
   162  #        $ret=mwexec(&#34;/usr/sbin/mt-daapd&#34;);
&lt;/pre&gt;
  

&lt;p&gt;Notice I didn&amp;rsquo;t change the killbyname command, since once it is started the binary has the same command name as the old one did. I tested restarting the Media Vault and after restart, it was working OK again. I do not know whether the built-in command to reset the media server will work with these changes; I suspect not. But if you want to do that, you can log in and do it from the command line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_6&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you followed the steps I listed above, your Media Vault ought to be serving FLAC and OGG files in WAV format to your music player (audiophiles, rejoice: your FLAC is not downconverted to MP3!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After doing this, I have to say I think this piece of equipment is pretty darned awesome, and I&amp;rsquo;m really happy I bought a low-power, quiet, small, fun gadget that I have full control over. And I haven&amp;rsquo;t even talked about sharing files yet! That&amp;rsquo;ll be another post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_7&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few miscellaneous things I&amp;rsquo;ve learned:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The default mt-daapd configuration file doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a defined rescan_interval. This means it&amp;rsquo;ll never notice when you add music to your filesystem. But you can poke it via the web interface (&lt;a href=&#34;http://hpmediavault:3689/index.html&#34;&gt;http://hpmediavault:3689/index.html&lt;/a&gt;; the username is empty, the password is defined in your config file) to make it update. Also, and I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how well this works, there&amp;rsquo;s an option to gzip the list of songs, which might make startup quite a bit faster when your iTunes/Rhythmbox connects and gets the song list. This is documented in the config file too. &lt;strong&gt;Update: I&amp;rsquo;ve been running my server this way for a while and it seems to run fine.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to set up Gentoo wireless networking on AMD64</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2006/02/11/gentoo-wireless-networking-on-amd64/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2006 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2006/02/11/gentoo-wireless-networking-on-amd64/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a quick note on wireless networking on Gentoo GNU/Linux with a dual-core AMD 64-bit processor. It&amp;rsquo;s not hard to do, but the choices for hardware are more limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, installing Gentoo is just as easy as a standard installation. There is a separate installation document for it. All I needed to do was follow the instructions. I&amp;rsquo;m not expert with Gentoo, but I&amp;rsquo;ve installed it a half-dozen times or so since 2002&amp;hellip; if it&amp;rsquo;s not easy for you, wait 4 years and try again ;-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my hardware:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ECS KV2 Extreme Socket 939 VIA K8T800 Pro ATX AMD Motherboard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ASUS V9520-X/TD/64 Geforce FX5200 64MB DDR AGP 4X/8X Low Profile Video Card&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sunbeam PSU-CGMI450-US-SV ATX 450W Silver Tri Mirrored X-Plug Modular Power Supply&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VANTEC Clear 18&amp;#8243; ATA &lt;sup&gt;66&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;100&lt;/sub&gt;/133 IDE Round Cable, 2-Connector Model CBL-100IDE18-CS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AMD Athlon 64 3700+ San Diego 1GHz FSB Socket 939 Processor Model ADA3700BNBOX (&lt;em&gt;dual core, 2.2GHz&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patriot Signature 2GB (2 x 1GB) 184-Pin DDR SDRAM DDR 400 (PC 3200) Unbuffered System Memory Model PSD2G400KH&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Western Digital Raptor WD360GD 36.7GB 10,000 RPM Serial ATA150 Hard Drive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seagate Barracuda 7200.8 ST3250823AS 250GB 7200 RPM Serial ATA150 Hard Drive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 Pioneer Beige IDE DVD Burners, Model DVR-110 D&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;COOLER MASTER Centurion 5 CAC-T05-UW Black Aluminum Bezel, SECC Chassis ATX Mid Tower Computer Case&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought it all from NewEgg for about $900 and paid my brother&amp;rsquo;s friend for his time helping me choose the hardware and install it (actually, that was my brother&amp;rsquo;s friend&amp;rsquo;s brother). If you want similar help, by the way, send me an email and I&amp;rsquo;ll hook you up with him. I&amp;rsquo;d have been lost without his guidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, I forgot a network card! Oops! So I went to a local store and bought something that looked pretty standard. I looked online for it first, but I should have spent more time figuring out compatibility, because as I found out, it&amp;rsquo;s not guaranteed on AMD64.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought a Linksys WRT54G, which has an RT2500 chipset. For those who don&amp;rsquo;t know, it is the chipset &amp;ndash; the guts of the card &amp;ndash; which really matters. Most cards have a chipset that may be found in any number of other cards, all of which use the same driver. And manufacturers often change the chipset, sometimes to something totally different, which may be completely unsupported and nothing at all like the original (from a device driver point of view). I thought this chipset was going to be a breeze because the manufacturer has open-sourced the drivers (thank you!). Unfortunately, I found out it&amp;rsquo;s not supported on more exotic platforms, including mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I searched around on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://forums.gentoo.org&#34;&gt;Gentoo forums&lt;/a&gt;, and found a lot of weird stories of things working sometimes and not working other times; and I even had the bizarre experience of the card working for me, for just a few minutes. But there are two things in the way of full support: a) 64-bit processor and b) two of them (dual core). The RT2500 chip can be coaxed to work, apparently completely sporadically, in non-SMP mode. In other words, if you build your kernel &lt;em&gt;without SMP support&lt;/em&gt; so it only uses one of the two cores, sometimes the drivers will compile. And, when that happens, sometimes the hardware will work and sometimes not. I paid too much for this machine to use half of my processor, so that wasn&amp;rsquo;t good enough for me even if I could have gotten it to work reliably without SMP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some banging of the head against the wall, I returned the card and got one with an Atheros chipset. The card is a D-Link DWL-G510, hardware version B1, firmware version 2.11. Again, you may buy exactly the same card and find a different chip in it, so there are no guarantees. But there is no problem getting the card to work if it has the Atheros chipset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I built the 2.6.15-gentoo-r4 kernel with SMP support and built in the encryption routines used by the card:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;Processor type and features ---&amp;gt;
    [*] Symmetric multi-processing support

Cryptographic options ---&amp;gt; (I enabled them all)&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;then did &lt;code&gt;emerge madwifi-driver&lt;/code&gt; (version 0.1443.20060207) and followed the instructions for setting up the &lt;code&gt;ath0&lt;/code&gt; interface via &lt;code&gt;udev&lt;/code&gt; (version 079-r1). These are well documented at many websites, including the Gentoo forums, but the output of &lt;code&gt;emerge&lt;/code&gt; is really all you need. I didn&amp;rsquo;t need to create the interface via a command as the instructions say; I was able to just let &lt;code&gt;udev&lt;/code&gt; create it at boot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then all I needed to do was &lt;code&gt;modprobe ath_pci&lt;/code&gt; and the interface appeared! Of course this module can be added to &lt;code&gt;/etc/modules.autoload.d/kernel-2.6&lt;/code&gt;. Finally, I configured the network&amp;rsquo;s settings for my access point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this bump in the road, it&amp;rsquo;s been smooth sailing. The network works great &amp;ndash; better than my DSL, that&amp;rsquo;s for sure. And I have to say, this machine absolutely flies. It probably has a lot to do with the large L1 cache (and everything else for that matter). Look at this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;tigger ~ # time emerge xorg-x11
[snip...]
real    24m59.155s
user    18m3.664s
sys     6m27.860s&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, there are no &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2006/01/23/firefox-or-opera-on-slow-hardware/&#34;&gt;problems running Firefox&lt;/a&gt; on this machine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Firefox vs. Opera on slow hardware</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2006/01/23/firefox-or-opera-on-slow-hardware/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2006 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2006/01/23/firefox-or-opera-on-slow-hardware/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;My main computer is a medieval laptop running &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ubuntulinux.org&#34;&gt;Ubuntu&lt;/a&gt; GNU/Linux. I used to run Gentoo but tried Ubuntu on a lark, and haven&amp;rsquo;t been motivated enough to change back to Gentoo (or even decide whether I want to, since Ubuntu works fine too). There is one problem, though: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mozilla.com/firefox/&#34;&gt;Firefox&lt;/a&gt; is running more slowly with each release. What to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;The background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been running Firefox since way back when the project got started. When it was Phoenix 0.4, I was on board. I was buying t-shirts, displaying buttons and logos on my websites, and telling my friends. At 0.5 or so, my brother got hooked too. I was there for the name changes, to Firebird and then Firefox. I&amp;rsquo;ve submitted, discussed, and voted for bugs and patches. I&amp;rsquo;ve donated to the Mozilla project. In short, I feel attached to this piece of software. For me, Firefox is not just a good web browser. It represents freedom, adherence to standards, respect for privacy, cooperation, and so much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of all, Firefox demonstrates to the world that you don&amp;rsquo;t have to sell your soul to Them. I love &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fsf.org/&#34;&gt;Free Software&lt;/a&gt; as a philosophy. I love the ethics. It speaks clearly to me of That Which Is Right. I&amp;rsquo;m serious about that. I have a lot of problems with non-Free software, and I really see it as the root of or enabler to many of our current evils (loss of privacy, rootkits, credit card thefts, election fraud). But all through my career with computing, anytime I run into someone who says &amp;ldquo;screw the ethics, show me practical reasons why I should stop using Excel or SQL Server or IE&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;ve come up against a wall: for every reason I can give, someone else&amp;rsquo;s marketing department has created a counter-argument. Just to name one example, Microsoft has commissioned lots of studies &amp;ldquo;showing&amp;rdquo; the equality or superiority of their products (they call it getting the &amp;ldquo;facts&amp;rdquo;). On the other hand, there are tons of studies and benchmarks and whitepapers showing the opposite, too &amp;ndash; measurably higher code quality, fewer security incidents, lower total cost of ownership, and on and on. If you&amp;rsquo;re not an expert, you don&amp;rsquo;t know who to believe. It&amp;rsquo;s my word against theirs, and statistics are worse than lies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I view Firefox as the tipping point. Finally, we who believe don&amp;rsquo;t have to sway people with words alone. It&amp;rsquo;s blatantly obvious to many people at this point that Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s offering is categorically inferior &lt;em&gt;in ways that matter to everyone&lt;/em&gt;. Since Firefox has caught hold, I no longer try to convince people. They ask me when they see my t-shirt, and I just say &amp;ldquo;you might consider giving it a try. Read their website and see if you think it&amp;rsquo;s worth looking into.&amp;rdquo; Things just seem to progress after that. A week later they tell me they&amp;rsquo;re really excited about it, too. That&amp;rsquo;s when I try to let them know it&amp;rsquo;s part of a much larger picture; I tell them about the GNU project, about the ethics and philosophy behind it all. I try to give a bit of context. I hope the snowball picks up speed &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;m trying to push it faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Practical concerns&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As time goes on my old, slow hardware has a harder and harder time with newer software (whose features I love and don&amp;rsquo;t want to live without). It&amp;rsquo;s gotten to the point that my laptop doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel responsive when browing the web. I&amp;rsquo;m not griping about little things &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;m talking about the browser being unresponsive for many seconds while a new tab opens or something. I want to keep this old tanker around, though. First of all, it works just fine. There&amp;rsquo;s nothing wrong with it &amp;ndash; as long as I&amp;rsquo;m running &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xfce.org/&#34;&gt;XFCE&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://fluxbox.sourceforge.net/&#34;&gt;Fluxbox&lt;/a&gt; (or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nongnu.org/ratpoison/&#34;&gt;ratpoison&lt;/a&gt;, better yet!) and lynx. Second, it is also proof that Linux can run just fine on old hardware &amp;ndash; hell, Windows 98 had a hard time on this thing, so it&amp;rsquo;s pretty amazing to see it boot up in less time than XP takes to boot on my spankin&amp;rsquo; new laptop from work. (For those who don&amp;rsquo;t know &amp;ndash; every version of the Linux kernel gets &lt;em&gt;faster&lt;/em&gt;, not slower like Windows). It&amp;rsquo;s just this new breed of software that&amp;rsquo;s getting harder and harder to run on it. Finally, I detest the &amp;ldquo;consumer&amp;rdquo; culture that says &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo; is OK to make and throw into landfills when it becomes boring. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to contribute to that any more than I have to. I want to run this thing until it melts into an unrecognizable blob.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.opera.com&#34;&gt;Opera&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve also been a longtime fan of Opera. I bought a license for an early version on Windows, back in the bad old days when I used Windows. I have always liked Opera&amp;rsquo;s support for standards, small size and speed. I&amp;rsquo;ve had my share of gripes, but overall, it&amp;rsquo;s not all that bad to use. And there is one critical thing that makes it attractive on this old laptop: it&amp;rsquo;s much faster than Firefox. You folks with processors that go faster than 10 mph might not appreciate this fact, but use it on my old laptop and you will definitely see the difference. Opera 8.51 is fast and lightweight enough to browse the web in a reasonably usable way on my machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my list of Opera pros:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I like it OK&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s fast(er)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it has reasonably good privacy controls (a &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2005/11/06/protect-your-privacy-online/&#34;&gt;cookie whitelist&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the cons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s not extensible like Firefox&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;there&amp;rsquo;s no &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2005/10/26/adblock-patterns/&#34;&gt;adblocking&lt;/a&gt; capability (you can block ads with stylesheets, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t prevent the content from ever being loaded, which is really important for privacy in my opinion)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;there are limited JavaScript tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;overall I want my features &amp;ndash; I want &lt;a href=&#34;http://karmatics.com/aardvark/&#34;&gt;Aardvark&lt;/a&gt;, I want &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hacksrus.com/~ginda/venkman/&#34;&gt;Venkman&lt;/a&gt;, I want the &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrispederick.com/work/webdeveloper/&#34;&gt;Web Developer Toolbar&lt;/a&gt;, I want &lt;a href=&#34;http://adblock.mozdev.org/&#34;&gt;AdBlock&lt;/a&gt;. I feel starved for features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s not Free Software. I balk at the feeling of betraying my ideals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Solutions (or not) and fun&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel conflicted. I&amp;rsquo;m thinking I might just need to bite the bullet. I might use this laptop for a file and print server, to run LAMP as a development box, and so forth. It might be time for me to build myself another computer for use as a desktop machine. After all, I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten about 7 years out of this laptop, so if I build a decent desktop machine, maybe it&amp;rsquo;ll be good for 10 more or so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s more. My fianc&amp;eacute;e has a schmancy new dual-core Mac G5, which according to her can do &amp;ldquo;eighteen billion billion&amp;rdquo; of something or other. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure she knows what that means, but she told me I can quote her:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only need to know three words: Eighteen. Billion. Billion. Are you going to quote me on your blog? Quote me where?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hmmm, that sounds like a challenge. I might need to spend a little extra money and get the biggest and baddest now. And you thought I was all Mr. EgoDontMatter, did you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She tells me jealousy is a horrible thing, and I can touch her computer if I&amp;rsquo;m feeling envious. When I bring up how often it crashes and forces her to reboot (how is it that a computer with eighteen billion billion somethings can&amp;rsquo;t run a few programs without crashing?) she says&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It only crashes when you&amp;rsquo;re around. I&amp;rsquo;ve had 20 years of using a Mac and it never used to crash. Now you&amp;rsquo;re around, and it&amp;rsquo;s crashing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the record, I never did anything to her computer to cause crashes. I did show her once how, since it&amp;rsquo;s built on UNIX, you can use &lt;code&gt;killall&lt;/code&gt; to kill programs when the point-and-click interface&amp;rsquo;s command to &amp;ldquo;forcibly kill&amp;rdquo; something gets laughed down by the offending app. Remember, Real Men Don&amp;rsquo;t Click.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will leave you with another quote from my younger brother, who recently built a computer himself. He&amp;rsquo;s talking about my computer, after my fianc&amp;eacute;e looked online to see &amp;ldquo;how many bits her computer has&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His computer probably only has twelve bits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose, whether it&amp;rsquo;s Opera or Firefox, the most important thing is to keep it fun. Next to Freedom, of course.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Review of the iRiver HD340</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2005/10/05/review-of-the-iriver-hd340/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2005 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2005/10/05/review-of-the-iriver-hd340/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The iRiver HD340 is a 40GB hard-drive-based multi-codec music player, radio, text reader, and image viewer. I have had mine for about 6 months now. I have found some strengths and weaknesses that do not seem to be common knowledge. As usual, I will try to avoid giving information available elsewhere on the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use my unit solely to listen to my CD collection and have not used its other functions much. My motivation for buying it was to be able to take my music with me conveniently, without risking loss or damage. In this respect I&amp;rsquo;m just like millions of others. But I don&amp;rsquo;t use non-Free Software compression formats (and I don&amp;rsquo;t want to have to encode at a high bitrate to get good sound quality, another reason not to use mp3), so just any old player won&amp;rsquo;t do. I need something that will play Ogg Vorbis files. That&amp;rsquo;s why I chose this unit over the others available on the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a lot of criticism below, but don&amp;rsquo;t be fooled: I really like this little gizmo and would definitely buy it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s good&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unit is compatible with Ogg Vorbis and other Free Software formats. The firmware is upgradable and iRiver has a good track record with updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unit itself is little more than a hard drive, a screen, and some software. It has a USB2.0 interface and when I plug it in, it shows up as an external hard drive like any other. The filesystem is FAT32. This means interfacing with my Gentoo GNU/Linux system is trivial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The player is well-built; it is very solid. It looks and feels like quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Filesystem layout is very simple: the unit simply browses the directory structure in a familiar tree view. There is a single four-way up/down/left/right button for navigation, which is very easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sound quality is &lt;strong&gt;excellent&lt;/strong&gt;. People often shrug off sound quality reviews and assume that every player will be great, but I can tell you from experience, some players can take a great file and make it sound like crap. Playback quality is very dependent on the software and hardware used. iRiver&amp;rsquo;s sounds great. I listen through a set of Sennheiser HD590s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Battery life is very good. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure exactly how long it lasts; I listen at low levels and it will play for a couple of work days, so maybe 16 to 20 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Room for improvement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interface is fairly geeky. Buttons do unintuitive things in different modes. After a little practice it&amp;rsquo;s not hard to use, but it is not straightforward. A person who isn&amp;rsquo;t used to it can easily choose the wrong song or album by accident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The instructions are unclear, in part because everything has a different function in different modes. For example, I tried and tried to get .m3u playlists to work, and concluded that the unit didn&amp;rsquo;t work right, but finally found something on the iRiver support website that explained how to do it. You have to press (and hold?) a certain button in a certain mode. I&amp;rsquo;ve forgotten how to do it now, and I usually don&amp;rsquo;t forget these types of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Navigating through the list of artists is slow. I have a lot of music and it would be nice to have a page-up/page-down function instead of clicking through them one at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is about a half-second gap between tracks. Gapless playback would be really nice, especially for my many albums that have no space between tracks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The display doesn&amp;rsquo;t really show all the information in a good way. Most song titles are too long to fit on the display. Instead of wrapping, they are scrolled. I have to wait for the text to scroll into view. In general, there is a lot of display real estate that&amp;rsquo;s poorly used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unit takes about 20 seconds to start. I understand that if I used Windows to transfer files to it, an internal database would be maintained and boot-up would be faster. I don&amp;rsquo;t think this is the reason for slow boot-up though. The system just takes a while to boot, period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is both a headphone and line-level output. The line output seems to be the same as the headphone though, and its level is controlled by the volume setting. A line output ought to be a certain voltage and impedance range. This isn&amp;rsquo;t a true line output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the battery goes low, playback is interrupted by a beep every few minutes as a warning. This is annoying and can&amp;rsquo;t be turned off. Worse, the battery really isn&amp;rsquo;t that close to dying. I&amp;rsquo;ve found there are typically two to three hours left in the battery when it starts beeping. To make the battery last as long as possible, it really needs to be drained every time before recharging, so there&amp;rsquo;s no way around it except to put it aside and not listen to it while it plays itself out of battery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unit is bigger than an iPod. It&amp;rsquo;s small, just not &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; small. It&amp;rsquo;s about the length and thickness of a deck of cards, and slightly narrower. When it is in its leather case it&amp;rsquo;s bulkier. The case has a small nub for attaching to a belt or other means of carrying, and the nub is not removable, which is a poor design choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing the settings is confusing. Many settings are unclear. Once the settings are saved it&amp;rsquo;s hard to get back to playback mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible to charge the unit by plugging it into a USB cable. Sometimes it started to charge when I really wanted it to connect for data transfer or vice versa. There is a setting to change this, but it&amp;rsquo;s hard to find, and unclear what really does what I want. It took some experimentation, but I was able to just disable USB charging, and I&amp;rsquo;m happy with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I have my settings the way I want, I really enjoy using this unit. I just turn it on and let it play, and that&amp;rsquo;s really all I want out of it. I&amp;rsquo;m very satisfied. I do not expect it to be a very popular toy for the masses, though.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>