<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Health on Xaprb </title>
      <generator uri="https://hugo.spf13.com">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://www.xaprb.com/categories/health/index.xml/</link>
    
    
    
    <updated>Mon, 20 Jan 2014 00:00:00 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Crossfit and Safety</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/01/20/crossfit-safety/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2014/01/20/crossfit-safety/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been a happy CrossFiter for a few years now. I met my co-founder and many
friends in &lt;a href=&#34;http://crossfitcharlottesville.com/&#34;&gt;CrossFit Charlottesville&lt;/a&gt;, completely changed my level of fitness
and many key indicators of health such as my hemoglobin A1C and vitamin D
levels, am stronger than I&amp;rsquo;ve ever been, feel great, and now my wife does
CrossFit too. It&amp;rsquo;s fantastic. It&amp;rsquo;s community, fun, health, fitness. It&amp;rsquo;s the
antidote to the boring gyms I forced myself to go to for years and hated every
minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2014/01/9117226687_6e903b5c1b.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Kettlebells&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is a fringe element in CrossFit, which unfortunately looks mainstream
to some who don&amp;rsquo;t really have enough context to judge. From the outside,
CrossFit can look almost cult-like. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to get an impression of people
doing dangerous things with little caution or training. To hear people talk
about it, everyone in CrossFit works out insanely until they vomit, pushing
themselves until their muscles break down and vital organs go into failure
modes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s not what I&amp;rsquo;ve experienced. I&amp;rsquo;ve never seen anyone vomit, or even come
close to it as far as I know. I think that part of this dichotomy comes from
certain people trying to promote CrossFit as a really badass thing to do, so
they not only focus on extreme stories, they even exaggerate stories to sound
more extreme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week there was a tragic accident: Denver CrossFit coach Kevin Ogar &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2540945/Kevin-Ogar-injury-CrossFit-athlete-left-paralyzed-waist-having-spine-severed-dumbbell.html&#34;&gt;injured
himself badly&lt;/a&gt;. This has raised the issue of CrossFit safety again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be clear, I think there is something about CrossFit that deserves to be
looked at. It&amp;rsquo;s just not the mainstream elements, that&amp;rsquo;s all.  The things I see
about CrossFit, which I choose not to participate in personally, are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The hierarchy and structure above the local gyms. If you look at local gyms
and local events, things look good. Everyone&amp;rsquo;s friends and nobody does stupid
things. But when you get into competitions, people are automatically elevated
into the realms of the extreme. This reaches its peak at the top levels of
the competitions. Why? Because there&amp;rsquo;s something to gain besides just
fitness. When someone has motivations (fame, endorsements and sponsorship,
financial rewards) beyond just being healthy, bad things are going to happen.
There&amp;rsquo;s talk now about cheating and performance-enhancing drugs and all kinds
of &amp;ldquo;professional sports issues.&amp;rdquo; Those are clear signs that it&amp;rsquo;s not about
fitness and health.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some inconsistencies in the underlying philosophy from the founders of
CrossFit. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how much this gets discussed, but a few of the core
concepts (which I agree with, by the way) are that varied, functional
movements are good. The problem is, the workout movements aren&amp;rsquo;t all
functional. A few of them are rather hardcore and very technical movements
chosen from various mixtures of disciplines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Untempered enthusiasm about, and ignorant promotion of, things such as the
so-called &lt;a href=&#34;http://mumanu.wordpress.com/2013/11/06/archaeologists-officially-declare-collective-sigh-over-paleo-diet/&#34;&gt;Paleo Diet&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m biased about this by being married to an
archaeologist, but it isn&amp;rsquo;t the diet that is the issue. It&amp;rsquo;s the fanaticism
that some people have about it, which can be off-putting to newcomers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m perfectly fine when people disagree with me on these topics. Lots of people
are really enthusiastic about lots of things. I choose to take what I like about
CrossFit and leave the rest. I would point out, however, that the opinions of
those who don&amp;rsquo;t really know CrossFit first-hand tend to be colored by the
extremism that&amp;rsquo;s on display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, there is one issue I think that&amp;rsquo;s really important to talk about, and
that&amp;rsquo;s the safety of the movements. This comes back to point #2 in my list
above. I&amp;rsquo;d especially like to pick out one movement that is done in a lot of
CrossFit workouts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;The Snatch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re not familiar with the snatch, it&amp;rsquo;s an Olympic weightlifting movement
where the barbell is pulled from the floor as high as possible in one movement.
The athlete then jumps under the barbell, catching it in a deep squat with arms
overhead, and stands up to complete the movement with the bar high overhead.
Here&amp;rsquo;s an elite Olympic lifter just after catching the bar at the bottom of the
squat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2014/01/7797163562_73c1630aa5.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Snatch&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The snatch is extremely technical. It requires factors such as balance, timing,
strength, and flexibility to come together flawlessly. Many of these factors are
not just necessary in moderate quantities. For example, the flexibility required
is beyond what most people are capable of without a lot of training. If you
don&amp;rsquo;t have the mobility to pull off the snatch correctly, your form is
compromised and it&amp;rsquo;s dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The snatch is how Kevin Ogar got hurt. Keep in mind this guy is a CrossFit coach
himself. He&amp;rsquo;s not a novice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I challenge anyone to defend the snatch as a functional movement. Tell me one
time in your life when you needed to execute a snatch, and be serious about it.
I can see the clean-and-jerk&amp;rsquo;s utility. But not the snatch. It&amp;rsquo;s ridiculous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The snatch is also inherently very dangerous. You&amp;rsquo;re throwing a heavy weight
over your head and getting under it, fast. You&amp;rsquo;re catching it in an extremely
compromised position. And if you drop it, which is hard not to do, where&amp;rsquo;s it
going to go? It&amp;rsquo;s going to fall on you. Here&amp;rsquo;s another Olympic athlete catching
hundreds of pounds with his neck when a snatch went a little bit wrong. A split
second later this picture looked much worse, but I don&amp;rsquo;t want to gross you out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2014/01/steiner.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Steiner&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next issue is that the snatch features prominently in many CrossFit
workouts, &lt;em&gt;especially competition workouts.&lt;/em&gt; This is not a small problem. Think
about it: in competition, when these extreme athletes have raised the bar to
such an extent that weeding out the best of the best requires multi-day
performances few mortals could ever achieve, we&amp;rsquo;re throwing high-rep,
heavy-weight &lt;em&gt;snatches&lt;/em&gt; into the mix. What&amp;rsquo;s astonishing isn&amp;rsquo;t that Kevin Ogar got
seriously injured. What&amp;rsquo;s amazing is that we don&amp;rsquo;t have people severing their
spines on the snatch all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What on earth is &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; with these people? What do they expect?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might think this is an issue that&amp;rsquo;s only present in the competitions. But
that&amp;rsquo;s not true. I generally refuse to do snatches in workouts at the gym. I
will substitute them for other movements. Why? Take a look at one sample snatch
workout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AMRAP (as many rounds as possible) in 12 Minutes of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Snatch x 10&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Double Under x 50&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Box Jump x 10&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sprint&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s 12 minutes of highly challenging movements (to put it in perspective,
most non-CrossFitters, and even many CrossFitters, would not be able to do the
double-unders or box-jumps). You&amp;rsquo;re coming off a sprint and you&amp;rsquo;re going to
throw off 10 snatches in a row, and you&amp;rsquo;re going to do it with perfect form?
Unlikely. This is just &lt;em&gt;asking&lt;/em&gt; for injury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or we could look at the &amp;ldquo;named WODs&amp;rdquo; that are benchmarks for CrossFitters
everywhere. There&amp;rsquo;s Amanda, for example: 9, 7, and 5 reps of muscle-ups and
snatches, as fast as possible. Or Isabel: 30 reps of 135-pound snatches, as fast
as possible. To get a sense for how insane that actually is, take a look at
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TAZgiahlvjs&#34;&gt;Olympic weightlifting competitor Kendrick Farriss doing Isabel&lt;/a&gt;. The man is
a &lt;em&gt;beast&lt;/em&gt; and he &lt;em&gt;struggles&lt;/em&gt;. And &lt;em&gt;his form breaks down.&lt;/em&gt; I&amp;rsquo;m over-using
italics. I&amp;rsquo;m sorry, I&amp;rsquo;ll cool down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My point is that I think this extremely technical, very dangerous movement should have
limited or no place in CrossFit workouts. I think it does very little but put people
into a situation where they&amp;rsquo;re at very high risk of getting injured. I do not
think it makes people more fit more effectively than alternative movements. I think one can get
the same or better benefits from much safer movements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing the snatch is an expert stunt. I personally think that I&amp;rsquo;ll never be good
at snatches unless I do them twice a week, minimum. And one of the tenets of
CrossFit is that there should be a large variety of constantly varied movements.
This automatically rules out doing any one movement very often.
In my own CrossFit workouts, going to the gym 2 or 3 times a week, I typically go weeks at a time without being trained on snatches in
pre-workout skill work. That is nowhere
near enough to develop real skill at it. (This is why I do my skill-work
snatches with little more than an empty bar.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other movements in CrossFit that I think are riskier than they need to
be, but snatches are the quintessential example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know many people who are experts in these topics will disagree with me very
strongly, and I don&amp;rsquo;t mind that. This is just my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Bad Coaches, Bad Vibes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s one more problem that contributes, I think, to needless risk in CrossFit
gyms. This is the combination of inadequate coaching and a focus on &amp;ldquo;goal
completion&amp;rdquo; to the exclusion of safety and absolutely perfect form, especially
during workouts where you&amp;rsquo;re trying to finish a set amount of movements as fast
as possible, or do as much as possible in a fixed time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no getting around the fact that CrossFit coaches aren&amp;rsquo;t all giving the
same level of attention to their athletes, nor do all of them have the
qualifications they need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anecdotally, I&amp;rsquo;ll tell the story of traveling in California, where I visited a
gym and did one of my favorite workouts, Diane. In Diane, you deadlift 225
pounds 21 reps, do 21 handstand pushups, repeat both movements with 15 reps
each, and finish with 9 reps each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deadlifting consists of grasping the bar on the ground and standing up straight,
then lowering it again. It is not a dynamic or unstable movement. You do not
move through any out-of-control ranges of motion. If you drop the bar you won&amp;rsquo;t
drop it on yourself, it&amp;rsquo;ll just fall to the ground. Nevertheless, if done wrong,
it can injure you badly, just like anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/media/2014/01/deadlift.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Deadlift&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gym owner / coach didn&amp;rsquo;t coach. There&amp;rsquo;s no other way to say it. He set up a
bar and said &amp;ldquo;ok, everyone look at me.&amp;rdquo; He then deadlifted and said some things
that sounded really important about how to deadlift safely. Then he left us on
our own. A relative newcomer was next to me. His form and technique were bad,
and the coach didn&amp;rsquo;t say anything. He was standing at the end of the room,
ostensibly watching, but he either wasn&amp;rsquo;t really looking, or he was lazy, or he
didn&amp;rsquo;t know enough to see that the guy was doing the movement unsafely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The newcomer turned to me and asked me what weight I thought he should use. I
recommended that he scale the weights way down, but it wasn&amp;rsquo;t my gym and I
wasn&amp;rsquo;t the coach. He lifted too heavy. I don&amp;rsquo;t think he hurt himself, but he was
rounding his back horribly and I&amp;rsquo;m sure he found it hard to move for a week
afterward.  The coach just watched from the end of the gym, all the way through
the workout.  All he did was start and stop the music. What a jerk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an element of responsibility to put on the athletes. You need to know
whether you&amp;rsquo;re doing things safely or not. If you don&amp;rsquo;t know, you should ask
your coach. For me, rule #1 is to find out how much I don&amp;rsquo;t know, and not to
attempt something unless I know how much I know about it. This athlete should
have taken the matter into his own hands and asked for more active coaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that doesn&amp;rsquo;t excuse the coach either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gym I go to &amp;mdash; that nonsense does not happen. And I&amp;rsquo;ve been to a few gyms
over the years and found them to be good. I&amp;rsquo;m glad I learned in a safe
environment, but not all gyms and coaches are that good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Precedent and Direction-Setting, and Lack of Reporting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What worries me the most is that the type of tragedy that happened to Kevin Ogar
is going to happen close to home and impact my friends or my gym. The problem is
complex to untangle, but in brief,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once annually there&amp;rsquo;s a series of quasi-competitions called the CrossFit
Open. These are scored workouts over a span of weeks. They are set by the
national CrossFit organization, not the local gyms. The scores are used to
filter who is the first rank of competitors to go to regional competitions,
and then eventually on to the annual CrossFit Games.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The CrossFit Open workouts will certainly include snatches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If local gyms don&amp;rsquo;t program snatches regularly, their members won&amp;rsquo;t be
prepared at all for the Open.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Local gyms don&amp;rsquo;t have to participate in the Open, and don&amp;rsquo;t have to encourage
their members to, but that&amp;rsquo;s easier said than done due to the community
aspects of CrossFit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result, in my opinion, is that there&amp;rsquo;s systemic pressure for gyms and
members to do things that carry a higher risk-to-reward ratio than many members
would prefer. Anecdotally, many members I&amp;rsquo;ve spoken to share my concerns about
the snatch. They love CrossFit, but they don&amp;rsquo;t like the pressure to do this
awkward and frightening movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it&amp;rsquo;s very difficult to understand how serious the problem really is. Is
there a high risk of injury from a snatch, or does it just seem that way because
of high-profile incidents? Are we right to be afraid of the snatch, or is it
just a movement that makes you feel really vulnerable? The problem here is that
there&amp;rsquo;s no culture of reporting incidents in CrossFit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can point to another sport where that culture does exist: caving. The National
Speleological Society publishes accident reports, and conscientious cavers share
a culture that every incident, even trivial ones, must be reported. As a result,
you can browse the NSS accident reports &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.caves.org/pub/aca/&#34;&gt;(summarized here)&lt;/a&gt; and see some
things clearly (you have to be a member to access the full reports, which are
often excruciatingly detailed). One of the most obvious conclusions you&amp;rsquo;ll draw
right away is that cave diving (scuba diving in underwater caves) is incredibly
dangerous and kills a lot of people, despite it being a small portion of the
overall caving sport&amp;rsquo;s popularity. If you weren&amp;rsquo;t a caver and you didn&amp;rsquo;t know
about cave diving, would you think this was the case? I&amp;rsquo;m not sure I would.
After reading cave diving accident reports, I remember being shocked at how many
people are found dead underwater for no apparent reason, with air left in
their tanks. The accident reports help cavers assess the risks of what they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing similar exists for CrossFit, and I wish it did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;Negative Press About CrossFit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the topic of what gets attention and exposure, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen a bunch of attention-seeking blog posts from
people who &amp;ldquo;told the dirty truth&amp;rdquo; about how CrossFit injured them and there&amp;rsquo;s a
culture of silencing dissenters and so on. I&amp;rsquo;m sure some of that happens, but
the stuff I&amp;rsquo;ve read has been from people who have an axe to grind. And frankly,
most of those people were indisputably idiots. They were blaming their problems
and injuries on CrossFit when the real problem was between their ears. I won&amp;rsquo;t
link to them, because they don&amp;rsquo;t deserve the attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t believe most of what you read online about CrossFit. Many of the people
telling their personal stories about their experiences in CrossFit are drama
queens blowing things completely out of proportion. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of legitimate
objective criticism too, most of it from neutral third-parties who have serious
credentials in physical fitness coaching, but this doesn&amp;rsquo;t get as much attention.
And there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of great writing about what&amp;rsquo;s good about CrossFit, much of it
from the good-hearted, honest, knowledgeable coaches and gym owners who soldier
on despite the ongoing soap operas and media hype wars. They&amp;rsquo;re bringing fitness
and health &amp;mdash; and fun &amp;mdash; to people who otherwise don&amp;rsquo;t get enough of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_4&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toss corporate sponsors, personal politics, competition, the lure of great gains
from winning, and a bunch of testosterone together and you&amp;rsquo;re going to get some
people hurt. Mix it in with snatches and it&amp;rsquo;s a miracle if nobody gets seriously
injured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you participate in CrossFit, which I highly recommend, take responsibility
for your own safety. If there is a rah-rah attitude of pushing too hard at all
costs in your gym, or if your coaches aren&amp;rsquo;t actually experts at what they do
(the CrossFit weekend-long certification seminars don&amp;rsquo;t count), or if it&amp;rsquo;s not
right for any other reason, go elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay healthy and have fun, and do constantly varied, functional movements at high
intensity in the company of your peers &amp;ndash; and do it safely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo credits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/stoermchen/9117226687/&#34;&gt;http://www.flickr.com/photos/stoermchen/9117226687/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/sumofmarc/7797163562/&#34;&gt;http://www.flickr.com/photos/sumofmarc/7797163562/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.abc.net.au/news/2012-08-08/matthias-steiner-is-struck-by-his-falling-weight/4184750&#34;&gt;http://www.abc.net.au/news/2012-08-08/matthias-steiner-is-struck-by-his-falling-weight/4184750&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/ario/8438758747/&#34;&gt;http://www.flickr.com/photos/ario/8438758747/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solving repetitive strain injury from typing</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/11/02/solving-repetitive-strain-injury-from-typing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/11/02/solving-repetitive-strain-injury-from-typing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the years I&amp;rsquo;ve had a lot of hand and arm problems from using a keyboard too much. For the last couple of years, though, I&amp;rsquo;ve been pain-free and twitch-free. (There was an extended time when my little fingers and thumbs spasmed annoyingly day and night.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of different kinds of keyboarding injuries, and lots of different solutions to them. I&amp;rsquo;ve changed my chair, my keyboard, my keyboard layout, my desk height, and so on. But one thing that&amp;rsquo;s made the most difference for me, and I suspect would help a lot of people, is strength training. The reason I believe it would be so helpful for a variety of different kinds of injuries is that low-force repetitive motions &amp;ndash; i.e. wiggling your fingers lightly in an awkward position &amp;ndash; is inherently weakening. That&amp;rsquo;s right, you use your fingers to type a lot, and you actually get really, really weak. Like, ridiculously weak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew up on a farm, milking cows by hand. I had some kind of deeply held assumption that I&amp;rsquo;d developed an iron grip for life. When I started using a computer a lot, I never would have believed anyone who told me I&amp;rsquo;d become a weakling in the space of six months or a year, yet looking back on it, that&amp;rsquo;s about how long it took for the problems to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost universally, when someone complains about RSI, or when I see someone flexing their hand or massaging their forearm painfully, a quick look at the person&amp;rsquo;s forearms reveals that the muscles are horribly atrophied. Sometimes these programmers look like strange insects; their arms are just bones and skin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Grip trainers&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; those little springloaded things you grab and squeeze &amp;ndash; are not the solution in my opinion, and may lead to more injuries. I am not a doctor, so take this with a grain of salt. But I believe that the muscles and connective tissues of the entire arm complex need to be developed, not only for strength, but for stability, and this applies to the nerve systems as well. (A lot of strength is neural, not muscular.) Coordination, flexibility, stamina, speed, and precision also need to be developed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than getting tunnel vision and looking at the grip muscles &amp;ndash; those muscles that curl your fingers toward your palm &amp;ndash; I believe that a lot of other muscles need to be involved, too. One example: hold something heavy, palm-down, and then raise the knuckles in a reverse wrist curl. Those muscles are vital, and they get as weak as any others, but they&amp;rsquo;re hard to imagine training with a spring in your palm. That&amp;rsquo;s why &amp;ldquo;grip trainers&amp;rdquo; aren&amp;rsquo;t the whole solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest wrapping your hands around something heavy, and doing hard things with it. Kettlebell training is an easy thing to recommend if you have proper coaching. Pullups, pushups, yoga, gymnastics, all kinds of weight training potentially including Olympic lifting, and jumping rope are all good workouts of various parts of the wrist/hand/arm complex. For a while now, I&amp;rsquo;ve carried a jump rope with me when I travel. Double-unders are a fantastic workout you can do anywhere, and they work pretty much your whole arm and everything attached (chest, back, shoulders, neck) as well as your legs, and if you haven&amp;rsquo;t done them, the cardio intensity is not to be underestimated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, there is a gadget that I love: the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Exercise-Fitness-Powerball-Blue-Exerciser/dp/B006LVJKGM/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Powerball&lt;/a&gt;. This little gizmo generates force through precession, and your job is to work back against it, adding energy to the ball and making it spin faster. You can hold it in a variety of grips and move it in several different patterns, including holding it as still as possible. It will exert an amazing amount of force back against you, if you have the skill, speed, and coordination to work against it. You can spend a few minutes a day with this and not only make your hands/wrists/arms burn like hell, but develop and harden all of the tissues involved. It takes a little while to get the hang of it, but it&amp;rsquo;s probably the best overall prevention of RSI I&amp;rsquo;ve ever used, given its combination of weight/price/size/go-anywhere-ness.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>