<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Web on Xaprb </title>
      <generator uri="https://hugo.spf13.com">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://www.xaprb.com/categories/web/index.xml/</link>
    
    
    
    <updated>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 00:00:00 UTC</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using encryption? You&#39;re suspicious</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/08/01/using-encryption-youre-suspicious/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/08/01/using-encryption-youre-suspicious/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday more details on the NSA&amp;rsquo;s secret and illegal monitoring activities were &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/jul/31/nsa-top-secret-program-online-data&#34;&gt;revealed&lt;/a&gt;. (Yes, the NSA revealed some things themselves, but as far as I can tell, that was only a conciliatory effort and didn&amp;rsquo;t actually reveal more details &amp;ndash; just more talk.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember my recent series of blog posts, where I claimed that privacy in today&amp;rsquo;s world is impossible without &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/05/without-free-software-and-hardware-privacy-is-impossible/&#34; title=&#34;Without free software and hardware, privacy is impossible&#34;&gt;trustworthy hardware/software&lt;/a&gt;, privacy is impossible unless it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/06/privacy-is-impossible-unless-its-the-default/&#34; title=&#34;Privacy is impossible unless it’s the default&#34;&gt;default&lt;/a&gt;, and privacy is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/07/17/email-snooping-is-a-small-fraction-of-the-story/&#34; title=&#34;Email snooping is a small fraction of the story&#34;&gt;essentially unachievable&lt;/a&gt; because of the scope of the problem, and the way we&amp;rsquo;ve built our society and technologies?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also said that those who use privacy, which is non-default, are making themselves targets for surveillance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you and I use this technology right now to encrypt our communications, we’ll actually make ourselves more interesting targets. That’s partially because we’d be among the few people doing so. Have you ever noticed that nothing draws attention like whispering in a public place? I don’t know what proportion of ordinary email between everyday people is encrypted, but if pressed, I’d guess it’s fewer than one email in 50,000.** That’s an extraordinarily strong signal to authorities looking for needles in the haystack of Internet activity**. I wouldn’t be surprised if the NSA has large-scale brute-force encryption-cracking clusters dedicated to forcibly decrypting the few encrypted emails that wend their way around the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, yet another &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/world/interactive/2013/jul/31/nsa-xkeyscore-program-full-presentation&#34;&gt;ugly NSA slideshow&lt;/a&gt; was made public. Take a look at slide 15:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/08/nsa-finding-targets.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/08/nsa-finding-targets-300x219.png&#34; alt=&#34;nsa-finding-targets&#34; width=&#34;300&#34; height=&#34;219&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3242&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the following slides, too: they discuss decrypting people&amp;rsquo;s encrypted activities to inspect. Refer to the closing sentence of my quoted paragraph above. Read the full article, linked at the top of this blog post. The amount and specificity of surveillance being performed is stunning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Am I psychic? No, this stuff is pretty obvious. As I said previously, it&amp;rsquo;s inevitable. Nothing is going to stop these agencies from doing this stuff. If it&amp;rsquo;s resisted strongly enough, they&amp;rsquo;ll just knuckle down and do it more and more secretly. They won&amp;rsquo;t stop doing it; they will just try to stop being caught in the act.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Model-view-controller considered harmful</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/04/17/model-view-controller-considered-harmful/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/04/17/model-view-controller-considered-harmful/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2001 I created a PHP 4 web application framework from scratch as the backbone of a sophisticated application. Back then frameworks weren&amp;rsquo;t cool. Smarty templates were the hotness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My framework had URL routing, templates with a capable templating syntax similar to mustache, loosely coupled and tightly cohesive object-oriented design, an elegant way to access the database without dumbing it down, and nicely separated business logic and presentation layers &amp;ndash; among many other nice things you find in good frameworks. As the application grew more and more complex, the framework continued to serve well with only occasional enhancements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mention this because it illustrates that I&amp;rsquo;ve been aware of how to design maintainable systems for a long time. But the so-called MVC paradigm (model, view, controller) has &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; made sense to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design goals make sense. See above. It&amp;rsquo;s just that I find MVC itself &amp;ndash; the abstraction and implementation of those goals &amp;ndash; to be unhelpful at best, on a day I&amp;rsquo;m being charitable. On a day I&amp;rsquo;m telling it like it is, I&amp;rsquo;ll just bluntly say MVC is the most confusing pile of acronym bulls**t I can think of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tell me, without knowing what MVC is, what would you guess the model represents? Controller? View? It would be bad enough if these were abstract terms like &amp;ldquo;node&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;resource,&amp;rdquo; but they&amp;rsquo;re not abstract. They hint at meaning, and then you discover that MVC doesn&amp;rsquo;t align with the hinted-at meaning. Instead, the M, V, and C represent concepts that are vague and hard to understand, and are kind of a stretch to mentally fit with the terms. This is worse than abstract, it&amp;rsquo;s misleading. It&amp;rsquo;s like bait-and-switch for someone who&amp;rsquo;s trying to grasp what it means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know where MVC came from and I&amp;rsquo;m sure I won&amp;rsquo;t change my mind if I find out. I have a hard time believing that I&amp;rsquo;m the only one who wishes someone had formed a committee[1] to discuss what kind of names to represent the concepts. Especially since there are so many frameworks that abstract things slightly differently, because MVC apparently doesn&amp;rsquo;t suit their designers either, and thus it&amp;rsquo;s necessary to explain the relationship between Framework X&amp;rsquo;s view of the world, and how that loosely maps to the MVC view of the world. It becomes a sloppy comparison to a sloppy analogy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even more fun: some folks try to invent an MVC framework, like the original ASP.NET, and &amp;ldquo;get it wrong,&amp;rdquo; to disdainful criticism. Then they have to reinvent it, sometimes several times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s kind of like the OSI 7-layer model, which everyone agrees doesn&amp;rsquo;t actually represent modern networking technology stacks cleanly, and yet everyone talks about the OSI layers. There&amp;rsquo;s a clean way to think about networking layers, but the OSI model ain&amp;rsquo;t it. Or NoSQL &amp;ndash; the most unhelpful, undescriptive name for an &amp;hellip; amorphous category of technologies or worldviews or design patterns or whatever&amp;hellip; ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lesson: great concepts that teach great truths, and could result in great advances in engineering due to a common mental model around which other things can be built, can be sidetracked by slapping an ill-fitting monicker or set of analogies on them. And sometimes we never seem to get another chance. NoSQL believers can&amp;rsquo;t seem to think of anything better than NoSQL as a name (and neither can I, as much as I deplore the NoSQL name). We&amp;rsquo;re stuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sure my strong opinions on this are a) somewhat ignorant and b) not shared by everyone. Discuss! :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] Yes, I&amp;rsquo;m aware that awful things come from committees, like SQL. But I have faith that it would have been better than MVC.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using AdBlock to clean up the UI on sites I use a lot</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/04/06/using-adblock-to-clean-up-the-ui-on-sites-i-use-a-lot/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/04/06/using-adblock-to-clean-up-the-ui-on-sites-i-use-a-lot/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I use LinkedIn a lot. I also use various Google properties a lot. Both of them have a bunch of distracting and annoying UI features that just get in my way. I know Google and LinkedIn have a vested interest in catching my attention and trying to get me to use their products in the ways that will make them the most money, but as a user, I don&amp;rsquo;t care what they want. I care what I want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;ve used AdBlock to clean up the elements I don&amp;rsquo;t want. Here&amp;rsquo;s how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m assuming you use one of the many excellent AdBlock extensions for whatever browser you use. If not, you need to do that &amp;ndash; reclaim your browser and view the web the way you want it. Every time I use someone else&amp;rsquo;s computer and they don&amp;rsquo;t have an AdBlock extension it blows my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;LinkedIn Endorsements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LinkedIn has a new endorsement feature. They show me a big banner at the top of the page every time I view a connection&amp;rsquo;s profile page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/04/linked-in-endorsements.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/04/linked-in-endorsements.png&#34; alt=&#34;linked-in-endorsements&#34; width=&#34;655&#34; height=&#34;207&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-3133&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t care. I don&amp;rsquo;t know enough about most of my connections to endorse them publicly, and I don&amp;rsquo;t want to see that nonsense. So I AdBlock it. This is easy to do &amp;ndash; just right-click and select the context menu item to block that whole banner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve also hidden the endorsements on my profile. It&amp;rsquo;s nice that people want to endorse me (although I think LinkedIn is almost bullying them into it by putting the obnoxious endorsement box in their faces), but most of the endorsements are for things I&amp;rsquo;m not actually expert in. Some of them I literally know nothing about. It&amp;rsquo;s interesting to see the difference between what people think I know and what I actually know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Google+ Notifications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhere I read that Google+ has quietly become a significantly large social network, with a large fraction of the number of users that Facebook has. I know why that is: it&amp;rsquo;s because Google has tied a Google+ account into nearly all of their services, and most people I know have multiple Google profiles. I have seven, and a couple months ago I had eight. Google can count me multiple times if they wish; that&amp;rsquo;s their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s my business is whether I let them annoy me with notifications. You know that irritating notification bar at the top of the page in all of the pages on Google&amp;rsquo;s domains? This one?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/04/google-plus-notification1.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/04/google-plus-notification1.png&#34; alt=&#34;google-plus-notification&#34; width=&#34;283&#34; height=&#34;167&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-3137&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, Google doesn&amp;rsquo;t allow you to disable notifications. The only way I know to get rid of that irritating red animated 1 button is to click on it so it turns back into a faint gray 0:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/04/google-plus-notification-22.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2013/04/google-plus-notification-22.png&#34; alt=&#34;google-plus-notification-2&#34; width=&#34;444&#34; height=&#34;118&#34; class=&#34;aligncenter size-full wp-image-3138&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No offense, guys, I do consider you friends, but I don&amp;rsquo;t care that you added me to your circles :-\ I don&amp;rsquo;t use Google+, regardless of what Google tries to make you believe. I bet you were probably bullied into adding me, just to make some annoying suggestion box go away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Google+ notifications box is a little harder to hide, because it uses CSS classes to generate the numbers in the box. But a little digging into the page source yielded the following custom AdBlock rules:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
google.com##DIV[id*=&#34;gbgs&#34;]
google.com##SPAN[id*=&#34;gbgs&#34;]&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now all of my Google pages are free of one more time-wasting, attention-disrupting, productivity-killing distraction.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updated spam controls</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/02/18/updated-spam-controls/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2013/02/18/updated-spam-controls/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not using my previous combination of Bad Behaviour + WP-Gatekeeper anymore. I&amp;rsquo;ve removed them in favor of ordinary reCAPTCHA. Although it lets a lot of spammers through (almost a thousand spam comments in the day I&amp;rsquo;ve had it enabled) and Bad Behaviour let only 1 or 2 a month through, it became clear that a lot of people were getting blocked wrongly by Bad Behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that I can&amp;rsquo;t practically moderate the spam queue. If you submit a comment and it doesn&amp;rsquo;t get published, you either went into the spam queue that I ignore, or I decided to censor you ;-) Feel free to email me if you think anything&amp;rsquo;s wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on REST web services</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/11/30/thoughts-on-rest-web-services/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Nov 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/11/30/thoughts-on-rest-web-services/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I usually keep pretty quiet on things that are controversial, and goodness knows you can start a holy war fast with any comments about REST web services. But I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking and working on these things for years &amp;ndash; REST for over a year, SOAP and friends since 2003 &amp;ndash; and maybe my opinions will be interesting to someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I dislike SOAP. I&amp;rsquo;ve worked a lot with it, doing about a dozen major integrations with platforms from companies like Amazon, Google, and Yahoo, using several different programming languages, primarily .NET languages and Perl. I have never worked heavily on the server side with SOAP; I&amp;rsquo;ve always been a client. From the client side it&amp;rsquo;s bad enough, and I do consider myself pretty fluent with most of the standards, though some of the WS- standards never were relevant to me. Regardless, I used to be able to read a raw WSDL for a complex service like Adwords, and tell you exactly what XML you needed to send and what you&amp;rsquo;d get back (primarily because the SOAP libraries available never worked right, and I had to write my own in both C# and Perl).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s wrong with SOAP? Complexity. SOAP (and XML in general) is a sledgehammer to crack a nut. It does, however, provide a lot of nice features. You can in theory develop tools for every step of the process: to generate WSDL, write code for servers and clients automatically, and so on. SOAP works, and it generally works well with minor problems caused by quirks of some client libraries not working well with some server implementations (the .NET SOAP libraries never worked right with the WSDLs from Amazon&amp;rsquo;s early merchant integration services, though they were valid). SOAP is not the most efficient thing that could ever be done, both from the computing and from the human standpoint. You can theoretically do that with other technologies too, but SOAP is the most obvious success story to illustrate (Thrift, CORBA, Protocol Buffers, etc could also be mentioned &amp;ndash; but they are not apples-to-apples in this discussion). SOAP is just too heavyweight. I always thought there needs to be something more straightforward and efficient that achieves the same goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d heard about REST but never looked into it deeply until a couple years ago, when I gained a passing familiarity through some adjacent technologies. Around a year ago I got involved with writing a set of web APIs (I&amp;rsquo;ll avoid calling them REST APIs) and worked a little more closely to REST. I quickly learned that I didn&amp;rsquo;t know much, and most of my assumptions were gently shown to be wrong by other team members. But as I learned more, I decided I don&amp;rsquo;t like REST either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s wrong with REST? Naivety and idealism. No matter how much we dream the dream, things are not self-describing and infinitely fluid, and people seem to fall in love with the &amp;ldquo;elegance&amp;rdquo; of HATEOS (which is one of the least elegant acronyms ever created, on any level). When you write a client against a service, the client and all of the systems it&amp;rsquo;s connected to represent an ossification of some ideas about the interface the service exposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interface of any type is a contract, a promise to the world. The client trusts the promise, and if the promise changes, the client&amp;rsquo;s code and persistence structures must change to match. The &amp;ldquo;semantic web&amp;rdquo; is a wonderful daydream for the day when computers understand &amp;ldquo;meaning,&amp;rdquo; but for the time being, very few real useful systems I&amp;rsquo;m aware of are in the habit of persisting and working with information that might or might not contain anything or nothing in any or no structured format. REST APIs are supposed to somehow be magically discoverable and traversable on demand &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;want to know what&amp;rsquo;s available through the API? Browse the API and see what you find!&amp;rdquo; This is completely unrealistic. If it were realistic, then why does every REST API have documentation that tells you what you&amp;rsquo;ll find when you browse the API, and what it means? QED.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another bit of idealism is the use of HTTP verbs exclusively. HTTP verbs aren&amp;rsquo;t sacred and somehow sufficient for everything. Designing to four primary verbs encourages a tremendously simplistic (actually, very complicated in &lt;a href=&#34;http://jcalcote.wordpress.com/2008/10/16/put-or-post-the-rest-of-the-story/&#34;&gt;subtle ways&lt;/a&gt;) worldview of what an efficient API does. Most quasi-REST services I&amp;rsquo;ve seen (there are very few that really follow the rules) would force one-at-a-time loops over operations involving a lot of data, for example. They were designed by people who&amp;rsquo;d never heard of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fallacies_of_Distributed_Computing&#34;&gt;fallacies of distributed computing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this has been said by many others, and probably more succinctly. What do I have to contribute? Only this: to point you to a good design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that one of the best service designs I&amp;rsquo;ve ever seen is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/adwords/api/docs/&#34;&gt;Google Adwords API&lt;/a&gt;. It uses SOAP, but that&amp;rsquo;s just a transport &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s not important. What&amp;rsquo;s important is the design. It&amp;rsquo;s made for efficiency on a very large scale &amp;ndash; on both the client and the server side &amp;ndash; and to work well with a large variety of client platforms, including Javascript in the browser. It uses batch operations nearly everywhere, and sensibly distills the verbs down to &amp;ldquo;read&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;write.&amp;rdquo; (Okay, they call it &amp;ldquo;get&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;mutate.&amp;rdquo;) The Adwords API actually doesn&amp;rsquo;t resemble early versions very much &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing client code against it since 2004 or so &amp;ndash; and the evolution of its design is a case study in large-scale API design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About a year ago I was cooking up a hybrid of JSON over HTTP, with many design decisions influenced by Adwords&amp;rsquo; design, and called it WORK (as opposed to REST, and because I wanted something that would work). The definitions of the operations and data types (yes, I do believe data types and operations should be predefined and agreed-upon, not discovered dynamically because that Just Doesn&amp;rsquo;t Work, as explained previously) were all written into a small JSON file. This served as an IDL that could, in theory and mostly in practice, be used to autogenerate client and server code. I didn&amp;rsquo;t see that project through to completion, but it remains an approach I&amp;rsquo;d use again in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in conclusion I would not recommend that anyone try to develop a REST web service. I&amp;rsquo;d recommend something more like RPC-over-JSON-using-parts-of-HTTP. This is what most so-called REST services really are anyway. I don&amp;rsquo;t care if anyone calls them REST, but Roy T. Fielding does, so out of respect for him I&amp;rsquo;ll use the terms somewhat carefully.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Organize to resist SOPA in DC</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/01/16/organize-to-resist-sopa-in-dc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2012 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2012/01/16/organize-to-resist-sopa-in-dc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re in the DC area, there&amp;rsquo;s an emergency meeting of the DC Tech Meetup to get involved in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/DC-Tech-Meetup/events/48101142/&#34;&gt;advocating against SOPA and PIPA&lt;/a&gt; legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can&amp;rsquo;t make it in person, you can &lt;a href=&#34;https://action.eff.org/o/9042/p/dia/action/public/?action_KEY=8173&#34;&gt;use the EFF&amp;rsquo;s online form to write your representatives about SOPA and PIPA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t wait until it&amp;rsquo;s too late. The Internet is a vital part of our freedom. Well-intentioned legislators could damage that greatly while trying to solve problems they don&amp;rsquo;t understand fully.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using the Nook Color as a full-featured Android tablet</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2011/06/04/using-the-nook-color-as-a-full-featured-android-tablet/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2011 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2011/06/04/using-the-nook-color-as-a-full-featured-android-tablet/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I bought a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Barnes-Noble-Color-eBook-Tablet/dp/1400532655/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Barnes and Noble Nook Color&lt;/a&gt; e-book reader and ripped out the Nook software, replacing it with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cyanogenmod.com/&#34;&gt;CyanogenMod&lt;/a&gt; distribution of the Android OS. It&amp;rsquo;s really, really nice hardware, and CyanogenMod (CM) is really, really nice software. I love them both, and my regular readers will remember that I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;em&gt;not a gadget guy&lt;/em&gt;. Read on for more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never thought I&amp;rsquo;d get a tablet, until my phone died and I got a Droid 2 as a replacement. With all those gadgets, I just started to find myself using my phone for reading my RSS feeds and so on &amp;ndash; but hating how small the screen was. I started to think again about a tablet after experiencing how handy the smartphone&amp;rsquo;s extra features are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;The Nook Color Hardware&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Nook Color is a medium-sized Android tablet with a screen that&amp;rsquo;s the same size as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Samsung-Galaxy-Tab-AT-T/dp/B004CYEQF0/?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Samsung Galaxy Tab&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s a perfect size for carrying around &amp;ndash; much better than iPads and Xooms and so on, which are just too big for my taste. This device literally fits in the pocket of my jeans (&lt;a href=&#34;https://nookdeveloper.barnesandnoble.com/product/nook-color-specs.html&#34;&gt;specs&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The screen is amazing. It&amp;rsquo;s super sharp. But the Nook Color doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a microphone or a camera, and it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have any phone service. This is fine. I don&amp;rsquo;t want these items. I want a tablet to use primarily at home for consuming content such as blogs, books, newspapers, music, movies, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best parts: 1) it&amp;rsquo;s way cheaper than a Galaxy Tab or similar tablets. It&amp;rsquo;s $250 at the store. And 2) it&amp;rsquo;s really easy to take off the stripped-down version of Android that comes with it, and put something better on it. Which brings me to my next point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;The Software&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you unpack the box, the Nook has a pretty nice little e-reader installed, with a simplified Android interface. It has limited functionality, which is fine. It does have a web browser and a couple other things, and BN recently added their own application store. But it&amp;rsquo;s really kind of lame. You can only get a small fraction of the apps that you could get through the Android Market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I updated to CyanogenMod in two stages. First, I simply rooted the device and made it possible to install arbitrary apps from the Android Market. There&amp;rsquo;s a nice, easy process to do this. It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;a href=&#34;http://forum.xda-developers.com/showpost.php?p=13270739&amp;amp;#038;postcount=1&#34;&gt;Manual Nooter&lt;/a&gt;. I tried this first instead of just going to CyanogenMod because I wanted to see what it was like. It was okay, but it was really obvious that it was a sort of layer on top of the underlying Nook. Pressing the Home button, for example, brought up a prompt to use the Nook home screen or the hijacked home screen for the new software. I tinkered around with this for a while, enough to determine that I didn&amp;rsquo;t like the patched look and feel. At the same time, I learned that the applications I wanted would work just fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I moved on to CyanogenMod. Early reviews I&amp;rsquo;d read of this said it wasn&amp;rsquo;t ready for prime time on the Nook, but the newer updates seemed to be well received. So I backed up everything and took the plunge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s really ridiculously easy to install CyanogenMod on the Nook, even easier if you don&amp;rsquo;t first update your Nook operating system. It took me longer to burn a bootable ROM on a MicroSD card than anything else. Full instructions can be found beginning at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cyanogenmod.com/devices/nook-color&#34;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is just brilliant. I&amp;rsquo;ve now installed my preferred apps, stripped down the interface by removing some stuff I don&amp;rsquo;t want, such as multiple desktops (CyanogenMod is jammed with features), and I have a simple, elegant, perfectly functioning Android tablet. And I really mean it &amp;ndash; there are no rough edges or crashes or anything you might expect from a third-party OS on your tablet. In fact, one of the things I like the most is that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t come with pre-installed adware, as my Droid did (and the stuff on the Droid can&amp;rsquo;t be uninstalled without rooting it and voiding the warranty, which is not something I&amp;rsquo;m going to do on my work phone).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want a small, light, thin tablet with WiFi that you can hold in one hand for reading books and newspapers and so on, which is easy to put in a pocket or purse and carry with you, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t cost much, then consider the Nook Color. If you want to turn it into something much more full-featured, then consider ripping out the Nook software and replacing it with CyanogenMod. The result is really superb.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The drawbacks of shortlinks</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2011/04/21/the-drawbacks-of-shortlinks/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2011 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2011/04/21/the-drawbacks-of-shortlinks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;These days it seems that people would rather generate a shortlink than use a real link, even when it&amp;rsquo;s not much shorter. It&amp;rsquo;s hip, after all. (Peter actually caught me doing this. It was for a link that used to be long but was shortened recently so a shortlink isn&amp;rsquo;t needed anymore. I did it to continue a habit, not for hipness.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve begun to see an increasing number of drawbacks to short link services. Here are a few I can think of: 1) if the service is down, the link is broken; this just happened to me. 2) I can&amp;rsquo;t see where it&amp;rsquo;s headed, so I don&amp;rsquo;t know if I&amp;rsquo;ve already read it. 3) I don&amp;rsquo;t know what I&amp;rsquo;m about to click through to, so I&amp;rsquo;m less likely to trust and click. 4) I&amp;rsquo;m much more interested in the content if I know what it is. Some of these problems are helped by links that are chosen not to be a random hash, but not all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m starting to feel that it&amp;rsquo;s bad netiquette to use shortlinks unless they are really needed. And I&amp;rsquo;m a little troubled by what happens if tinyurl and bit.ly go bankrupt &amp;ndash; half the Internet will be full of broken links. Oh wait, that will mostly affect Twitter&amp;hellip; maybe it&amp;rsquo;s not so bad after all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why measure pageviews per month?</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2010/10/01/why-measure-pageviews-per-month/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2010 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2010/10/01/why-measure-pageviews-per-month/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t get why companies talk about how many pageviews they get per month. Maybe it is a handy metric when thinking about revenue, but when thinking about performance, it&amp;rsquo;s not a convenient way to measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, &amp;ldquo;we get 50M page views per month.&amp;rdquo; Let&amp;rsquo;s translate that into something useful for an engineer: 20 page views per second. How about 2.5B pageviews per month? Roughly 1000 per second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much easier to think about what this means. And not so impressive.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breaking news: SHOW INNODB STATUS ported to XML</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2010/04/20/breaking-news-show-innodb-status-ported-to-xml/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2010 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2010/04/20/breaking-news-show-innodb-status-ported-to-xml/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re like me, you&amp;rsquo;ve gotten tired of writing endless test cases for parsers that can understand the thousands of variations of text output by SHOW INNODB STATUS. I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to solve this issue once and for all by patching MySQL and InnoDB to output XML, the universal markup format, so tools can understand and manipulate it easily. Here&amp;rsquo;s a sample snippet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&amp;lt;status&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[
=====================================
100320 15:46:24 INNODB MONITOR OUTPUT
=====================================
... text omitted, but you get the idea ...
]]&gt;
&amp;lt/status&amp;gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS: Yes, this is a late April Fool&amp;rsquo;s joke.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to lie beautifully with FusionCharts</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2009/09/28/how-to-lie-beautifully-with-fusioncharts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2009 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2009/09/28/how-to-lie-beautifully-with-fusioncharts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Gotta love those three-dimensional charts. They sure are shiny! Look at this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;attachment_1311&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption aligncenter&#34; style=&#34;width: 474px&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2009/09/graphs.png&#34; alt=&#34;FusionCharts graphs&#34; title=&#34;FusionCharts graphs&#34; width=&#34;464&#34; height=&#34;195&#34; class=&#34;size-full wp-image-1311&#34; /&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;
    FusionCharts graphs
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a screenshot of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fusioncharts.com/&#34;&gt;FusionCharts graphs&lt;/a&gt;. But wait, on closer inspection: 5 and 7 are the same height? 6 is exactly twice as tall as 2?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pseudo-three-dimensional charts are the bane of my existence. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Visual-Display-Quantitative-Information-2nd/dp/0961392142?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;Tufte&lt;/a&gt; would definitely not approve. (If you don&amp;rsquo;t have &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Visual-Display-Quantitative-Information-2nd/dp/0961392142?tag=xaprb-20&#34;&gt;The Visual Display of Quantitative Information&lt;/a&gt;, you should really get it and give it a read.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stopping spam on Google Groups</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2009/09/13/stopping-spam-on-google-groups/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2009 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2009/09/13/stopping-spam-on-google-groups/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Spammers seem to have gotten smarter recently, and able to post garbage to Google Groups. There was some spam on a couple of the groups I&amp;rsquo;ve created, and members helped me find a way to stop it. I&amp;rsquo;m glad they did, because since then it&amp;rsquo;s stopped an increasing flow of spam. I just deleted and banned a whole bunch of emails titled &amp;ldquo;answer group&amp;rdquo; across different groups, and I see the same crud got through to a group I&amp;rsquo;m on but don&amp;rsquo;t own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the recipe:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moderate messages from new members.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all. Then you can log in and delete emails from spammers, and ban them, so that at least only you, and not the whole group, gets spammed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speaking at EdUI Conference 2009</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2009/08/13/speaking-at-edui-conference-2009/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Aug 2009 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2009/08/13/speaking-at-edui-conference-2009/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to present at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eduiconf.org/&#34;&gt;EdUIConf conference 2009&lt;/a&gt;. This is a conference focused in two directions: Web professionals in higher education, and higher education for web professionals. I believe it&amp;rsquo;s going to be comparable to, or at least in the same vein as, some of the more popular conferences about user interface design, Web standards, and the like. (It&amp;rsquo;ll also be much more affordable.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speaker lineup boasts a number of heavy hitters. I&amp;rsquo;m guessing those of you in the Web design profession will know the following name: &lt;a href=&#34;http://molly.com/&#34;&gt;Molly Holzschlag&lt;/a&gt;. If you don&amp;rsquo;t, crawl out from whatever rock you&amp;rsquo;ve been hiding under!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own session at this conference will be on the topic of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eduiconf.org/session/high-performance-schwartz/&#34;&gt;Web front-end performance&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve dubbed it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eduiconf.org/session/high-performance-schwartz/&#34;&gt;High-Performance Web Interface Design&lt;/a&gt;, and I&amp;rsquo;ll focus on a practical approach to performance. Nothing I&amp;rsquo;ll show you is revolutionary. The problem is, even though it&amp;rsquo;s not revolutionary to get good client-side performance, people don&amp;rsquo;t do it, and users suffer terrible interfaces that don&amp;rsquo;t download, render, or interact in a snappy fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be a relatively fast-paced overview of Web front-end performance, and I&amp;rsquo;ll show you a demo of a badly performing website (such as the type I see often), make some changes to it, and let you see the performance difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you register, I would appreciate you entering my name in the &amp;ldquo;how did you hear about this&amp;rdquo; text box. That will give me a chance to win a laptop. *grin*&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wikipedia&#39;s concensus: Linux is an operating system</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2009/07/01/wikipedias-concensus-linux-is-an-operating-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2009 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2009/07/01/wikipedias-concensus-linux-is-an-operating-system/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My brother sent me these thoughts, slightly edited:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I looked at the [Wikipedia] Linux page. To my surprise it&amp;rsquo;s not about the kernel Linux, it&amp;rsquo;s about the &amp;ldquo;OS&amp;rdquo;. I looked at discussion and it appears that by general consensus the term Linux applies to the unix like operating system, and so it is correct for Wikipedia to follow that consensus. So, instead of providing information, they are deliberately misleading folks&amp;hellip; Often what the majority does is wrong because the majority of people are not the experts. By definition, the experts are a minority.
You&amp;rsquo;d expect a higher standard from Wikipedia, wouldn&amp;rsquo;t you? Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t you? Aw, come on, surely you don&amp;rsquo;t mean to imply that Wikipedia is a place where things become true because most people say so, do you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consensus, when used in this way, is nothing other than mind-rot for the masses, group-think at its worst. There is a valid use of the word when it applies to decision-making. But this isn&amp;rsquo;t about decision-making, it&amp;rsquo;s about out-voting or out-discussing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s interesting to me is that I heard a radio interview with Wikipedia&amp;rsquo;s founder Jimmy Wales, and he was extremely careful to say GNU/Linux when discussing the operating system that runs the website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saying that Linux is an operating system has not, does not, and never will make it true any more than saying that a steering wheel is a car makes it so.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to add a wiki homepage, sidebar, and TOC in Google Code</title>
      <link>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2009/07/01/how-to-add-a-wiki-homepage-sidebar-and-toc-in-google-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2009 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.xaprb.com/blog/2009/07/01/how-to-add-a-wiki-homepage-sidebar-and-toc-in-google-code/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just adore Google Code. But the default wiki view (a list of pages, sorted by last-modified) is lacking something. Fortunately, it&amp;rsquo;s fixable. Here&amp;rsquo;s the before:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;attachment_1167&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption alignnone&#34; style=&#34;width: 642px&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2009/07/Screenshot-Wiki-Pages-maatkit-Google-Code-Mozilla-Firefox.png&#34; alt=&#34;Default wiki list&#34; title=&#34;Default wiki list&#34; width=&#34;632&#34; height=&#34;342&#34; class=&#34;size-full wp-image-1167&#34; /&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;
    Default wiki list
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here&amp;rsquo;s the after:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;attachment_1168&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption alignnone&#34; style=&#34;width: 642px&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.xaprb.com/media/2009/07/Screenshot-Wiki-Pages-maatkit-Google-Code-Mozilla-Firefox1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Wiki with sidebar and default page&#34; title=&#34;Wiki with sidebar and default page&#34; width=&#34;632&#34; height=&#34;342&#34; class=&#34;size-full wp-image-1168&#34; /&gt;&lt;p class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;
    Wiki with sidebar and default page
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s how:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a wiki page called TableOfContents, or something like that. Using normal wiki syntax, enter links and text for your table of contents. The best way to do this is to use bulleted lists to organize and outline the pages. Keep in mind that we&amp;rsquo;ll use this same text for the sidebar, so keep it brief.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to Administer/Wiki and enter that wiki page&amp;rsquo;s name in the &amp;ldquo;Wiki Sidebar&amp;rdquo; box. Save the changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to Administer/Tabs and enter the same page in the Wiki box. Save the changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now both the wiki &amp;ldquo;homepage&amp;rdquo; and the sidebar will contain the page you created. No more ugly list-of-pages. And as you navigate through the wiki pages, the sidebar automatically expands and closes the outline to show where you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want, you can use a different homepage and sidebar, but I&amp;rsquo;ve found that it works well for me to use the same page for both. It&amp;rsquo;s a preference, that&amp;rsquo;s all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s one more trick I&amp;rsquo;d like to share: you can add the text &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;wiki:toc /&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; at the top of any page to create a small table of contents for that page. There are ways to customize it &amp;ndash; check the documentation for more options.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>